Prologue

The fate of Harry and Meghan, the Duke and Duchess of Sussex, continues to arrest public attention. It does not tend to be generated from universal sympathy for the couple, nor from the widespread criticism they provoke. Rather, many across the globe are intrigued by whether they will continue to thrive or merely survive.

The debate between their admirers and critics seems to focus on the endgame. Divorce, debt and disaster are constant themes about the Sussexes’ future. Many gloat that Harry is no longer the Royal Family’s ‘spare’ but has become Meghan’s. Indeed, in an interview for Harper’s Bazaar’s Christmas 2025 issue, Meghan appeared to revel in Harry’s puppy love for her.

Ever since they moved to California in 2020, many have speculated that the Sussexes’ marriage was doomed. Harry, it was said, would fall out of love with the sea and sunshine and pine for his British roots – his family and the friends he left behind. Others predicted that Meghan would become bored with the Prince and even entice a Silicon Valley billionaire to provide the wealth and status she craves. Current evidence suggests that the doom-mongers are wrong – so far. But every week the Sussexes’ antics provoke speculation.

Their narrative is propelled by their incessant search for publicity. Hardly a day passes without Meghan posting photos, videos and comments on social media. To establish herself as a glamorous icon, Meghan ceaselessly appears at venues across America to declare her opinions about managing motherhood, building a business and coping with fame. At key moments she gives an interview to a supposedly trusted writer. Often light on substance saying little new; nevertheless, every word is examined by Sussexologists to glean revelations and new insights. By strictly controlling her narrative, she has created mystery about an exceptional phenomenon. Namely, the journey of a little-known B-list actress, who, after marriage to a prince, turned her global stardom into a lucrative revolt against the world’s oldest monarchy.

Interspersed between Meghan’s carefully orchestrated appearances, Harry has increasingly struggled to protect his princely status. With nothing overtly original to say, he has steadfastly refused to acknowledge the harm caused by Spare, his bestselling autobiography, and his subversive TV interviews. Trading on his birthright, he is heralded when promoting a charity but criticised when he uses his name to earn an extremely handsome fee.

Five years ago, Revenge, my book about the Sussexes’ war against the Windsors, exposed the truth about Meghan’s past. It revealed how she had ditched her family, friends and others to become famous. Simultaneously, the book traced her manipulation of past events to rewrite her history. The climax of her ‘truth’ was her interview with Oprah Winfrey in 2021. Since then, she has appeared to separate herself from Harry except when a joint appearance would enrich her publicity. Meghan’s self-promotion as Her Royal Highness, the Duchess of Sussex, has become more sophisticated. Entrenched in California, her bid for commercial success relies on her ‘truth’, which others would say bears little resemblance to objective facts. However, no humiliation or criticism has crippled her breathtaking ambition.

At the same time, Harry’s troubles have mounted. Isolated from Britain, his charitable activities have become threadbare and his desperation noticeable to many. Permanently alienated from William and Kate, Harry was reportedly stunned by his brother’s ferocious reaction to the man now known as Andrew Mountbatten-Windsor’s relationship with the convicted paedophile Jeffrey Epstein. Leaning on his ailing father, William ensured that the King stripped his own brother of all his titles, honours and stately home. The unpredicted and unimagined humiliation of Andrew shocked Harry. Rightly, Harry fears that the future King William could remove all the Sussexes’ titles and effectively banish him from Britain. Whether Meghan understands the potential consequences of any deliberate aggravation of the Prince and Princess of Wales remains to be seen.

With the Royal Family weakened by scandal and sickness, the Sussexes and the British monarchy are at a crossroads. The dramatic events of the past five years and new disclosures about details of their lives before ‘Megxit’ justify a new book with a fresh and penetrative look at Meghan, Harry and the Royal Family. In many ways, 2026 will be a make-or-break year for them all.

The book opens during the momentous week of Queen Elizabeth II’s death in September 2022.

CHAPTER 1

Manchester, 5th September 2022

In the countdown to the big moment, Ella Robertson read Meghan Markle’s proposed speech on the Autocue. ‘She’s fucked it,’ groaned Robertson. Instead of speaking as agreed about the charity One Young World, Meghan’s speech was focused on herself. Nearly fifty times in just ten minutes, she intended to say ‘I’.

On 5th September 2022, Meghan was due to address 2,300 people for One Young World’s conference in Manchester. Founded in 2010 in London, the organisation brought young leaders together every year in a different country to discuss global challenges.

The co-founder, Kate Robertson, and her daughter Ella had been nervous about inviting Meghan to Manchester. ‘Megxit’ was still a hotly emotional topic – Harry and Meghan had only left the UK in March 2020 – and the Sussexes’ anticipated return to Britain from California had excited intense speculation. Buckingham Palace had disclosed that the Queen would not meet her grandson.[1] Similarly, Princes Charles and William were indisposed to the couple. Fearful of the Sussexes’ disloyalty, especially with the imminent broadcast of their Netflix series and the publication of Harry’s autobiography, the Royal Family no longer trusted Harry or his wife.

Despite the snubs, the Sussexes had conjured a short itinerary of three events headlined ‘Compassion in Action’. First, they would appear in Manchester, then dash to Düsseldorf to promote the 2023 Invictus Games before returning to London for Harry to host the WellChild awards. Given recent explosive events, the Sussexes’ appearances were guaranteed publicity.

Despite the widespread anger among older Britons towards Harry and Meghan, many young people hailed the couple as heroes. Among those younger factions their popularity was undeniably magnetic. Meghan, they believed, was the victim of the racist royals, and that undoubtedly Harry had been abused by his father and brother. A new generation of aspiring young leaders, the Robertsons had decided, would welcome Meghan in Manchester. ‘They were the most attention-grabbing couple in the world,’ judged Ella. ‘No one else could get so much attention for an event.’

Yet the Robertsons had good reason to be fearful.

During endless conversations and emails with the Sussexes’ staff in California, Ella Robertson had sought guarantees that there would be no ‘explosions’ to distract from the conference. Ever since Meghan’s interview with Oprah Winfrey in 2021, everything she said had become sensational. Although sensitive to criticism, Meghan was proud of the Oprah interview, not least because the reward for denouncing the Royal Family was renewed global stardom. Robertson sought reassurances from James Holt, the Sussexes’ chief of staff. ‘Nothing’s coming up that I’m aware of,’ he affirmed. Holt evidently forgot to mention that Meghan would be hosting a series of podcasts and the imminent publication of an interview with The Cut, a New York magazine. Holt’s priority was to fuel Meghan’s celebrity, especially as the champion of humanitarian causes.

In July 2022, Holt confirmed Meghan’s appearance in Manchester. One Young World agreed to pay for the return flights from Los Angeles for the Sussexes’ entourage – a total of eleven people. Five would travel first-class, two in business and four in economy.

Appropriately, Meghan had agreed that her short speech in Manchester would focus on empowering women and gender equality. Pointedly, she was asked not to speak about herself and not to wear expensive clothes. From past experience, the Robertsons had reasons to be nervous.

During her rise to stardom, Meghan had previously worked with One Young World and it clearly helped to boost her celebrity. Although the actress was largely unknown in 2014, Kate Robertson had been persuaded by the photographer Misan Harriman to give Meghan a slot at the Dublin conference. ‘Choose her. She’ll be a star,’ urged Harriman. Not only because she was acting in Suits, the American cable TV series, explained Harriman, but because ‘she’s a hustler and a climber. She’s looking for ins and ups.’

Two years later, in September 2016, Meghan was booked to appear at the One Young World conference in Ottawa. By then, she had been secretly dating Harry for three months. Her ambition, she had confessed to her publicist Gina Nelthorpe-Cowne, was to marry the Prince. ‘With Harry by my side,’ she had whispered at a London restaurant, ‘we can change the world.’

During those action-packed two days in Ottawa, the Robertsons and Nelthorpe-Cowne noticed how Meghan had altered from just two years previously. Forthrightly, she demanded to feature in the official photographs with the Canadian prime minister Justin Trudeau, UN Secretary-General Kofi Annan and Bob Geldof. She also demanded equivalence with the actress Emma Watson. She had inveigled her way into Vanity Fair’s photograph featuring ‘exceptional young leaders’ and had scrutinised whether her name featured as a ‘Very Very Important Person’ (VVIP) on the roster. Disgruntled by her failure to secure top billing, she abruptly announced that she was needed on the Suits set in Toronto and departed without making her listed speech to the conference. Nelthorpe-Cowne was left tearful. With a move that could seem heartless towards those unable to further her ambitions, it was becoming apparent that Meghan would allow no one to forget that she was to become one of the world’s most famous women.

Despite that disruption, Ella Robertson could not resist again inviting Meghan to address 2,000 young leaders at the One Young World conference in London’s Royal Albert Hall on 22nd October 2019. Now the newly married Duchess was certain to be a star attraction. Un-surprisingly, the negotiations were complicated. Jason Knauf, Meghan’s young American-born Palace press secretary, was emphatic: ‘Meghan demands that you big up her humanitarian credentials.’ Calls to confirm Meghan’s presence were answered ‘yes’ by Kensington Palace and then followed up by uncertainty.

‘It’s a vipers’ nest in her office,’ complained Ella Robertson. Every request to confirm Meghan’s participation produced conflicting replies from her assistants – positive from Amy Pickerill; frosty from Beth Herlihy; encouraging from Sara Latham, a Kensington Palace media official who replied, ‘We want to do the project and we want to do it now’; and finally hectic from Samantha Cohen, the Sussexes’ most senior advisor. ‘It became a nightmare to get her to the event,’ recalled Robertson.

The chaos had spread to the London headquarters of the Invictus Games, Harry’s successful sports competition for wounded military veterans. ‘It’s a shit show over there,’ chief executive Don Reid reported about Kensington Palace. ‘Harry has no idea what’s happening.’ The nub was a breakdown of relations between the Sussexes and their staff – and everyone knew the reason.

Finally, Meghan agreed to appear at the Royal Albert Hall. In return, One Young World funded a £200,000 scholarship for Meghan to mention in her speech.

The agreement soon unravelled. Prince Charles ordered that Meghan cancel her appearance. Her date clashed with his official visit to Japan and he feared her appearance would overshadow his trip.The agreed compromise was a round-table discussion about gender equality chaired by Meghan that would be filmed by the BBC in Windsor.

On meeting Meghan in Windsor Castle for the discussion about her favourite topic – feminism – Ella Robertson was surprised. Five months after Archie’s birth, ‘She was traumatised, shell-shocked and brittle.’ Nevertheless, Meghan behaved professionally. Well prepared, she introduced her ‘surprise guest’ to the panel – Harry. He had just finalised the membership of Britain’s team to compete at the following year’s Invictus Games in the Hague. With Harry in a supporting role, the BBC’s film featured the Sussexes as genuine stars.[2]

By then, gossip about the confusion and arguments among the Sussexes and Cambridges – the so-called ‘Fab Four’ – in Kensington Palace and beyond had seeped into the media. By now dubbed ‘Duchess Difficult’, Meghan was wilting under the pressure.

Meghan’s plight attracted sympathy in Westminster. Seventy-two female MPs expressed their ‘solidarity’ with her against the media and, implicitly, the Palace. Simultaneously, American politicians including Hillary Clinton and Michelle Obama hailed Meghan as a hero. With targeted briefings, Meghan was successfully building a narrative about her suffering. Like many young people, her audience at the Royal Albert Hall hailed Meghan as ‘a global champion for the rights of women and girls, activist and philanthropist’.

Just two weeks later, the Sussexes departed for a remote waterfront mansion on Vancouver Island, the first stage of their dash to California. Harry would call that journey ‘running like hell’.[3] Palace press officer Sara Latham voiced an alternative take about ‘Megxit’: ‘Ultimately, we’ve all been had.’

Since their exit from Britain in 2019, Meghan had devoted money and effort to craft a global image as a feminist, philanthropist, activist and American ‘mom’. The Robertsons were baffled: ‘It’s just really hard to see that she’s ever really been a leader of anything other than her own image creation.’ Nevertheless, in 2022 they could not resist inviting the global star to Manchester.

In Meghan’s new career, media advisors were supreme. At that moment, no one was more important in Los Angeles than Meghan’s in-house media managers: Beth Herlihy, Miranda Barbot and Ashley Hansen. Barbot had worked on Barack Obama’s 2012 election team and Hansen came from Universal Pictures. The most important outsider was Keleigh Thomas Morgan of Sunshine Sachs, a Los Angeles PR agency.

As the Sussexes’ global press secretary, Hansen described herself as ‘the brain behind Prince Harry and Meghan Markle’s PR and communications strategy’.[4] She had overseen their Netflix docu-series Harry & Meghan and she was preparing for the launches of Prince Harry’s memoir Spare and Meghan’s Archetypes podcasts. Like Meghan, Hansen was a Californian, passionate about food, exercise and meditation.

Daily, Hansen and her team of four monitored every media outlet for coverage of their employer. ‘We know, especially with tabloids, there’s an agenda there,’ said Hansen. ‘And it’s a negative one for the most part.’ In anticipation of their arrival in Manchester, Herlihy admitted, ‘All bets are off with the British media. And the trolls are out in force.’ Snapping orders, Hansen was the salty voice of the Sussexes’ war machine.[5]

Long before she arrived in Britain for the One Young World event in 2022, there was always a risk that the appearance would be used for Meghan’s own benefit rather than that of the charity. Building on her successful September issue for Vogue in 2019, Meghan asked the magazine’s editor Edward Enninful to feature her on Vogue’s front cover ahead of the Manchester event. Over the following weeks, their discussions soured. Meghan’s demands for control over the content reportedly infuriated Enninful. Plus, he had already chosen a cover and her demands for an online version were exhausting. Her proposal was dumped. In the fall-out, Meghan would not be invited in 2024 by Enninful to feature in the photograph for his last edition featuring Vogue’s forty ‘legendary’ women.[6] Meghan risked the same reaction from the Robertsons as she headed to Manchester.

Hansen perfectly understood the challenge. Even the timing of Meghan’s appearance was a high-wire act. At the same time as she was due to walk on to the stage, the Conservative Party would announce that Liz Truss had been elected as the new Tory leader and the next prime minister. Remarkably, Hansen had negotiated that Sky TV would cut from Westminster to capture Meghan’s live appearance.

Hansen recognised that Meghan was sensitive to slights. To limit any embarrassment in Manchester, there was to be tight scrutiny of ticketing to exclude any protesters, a ban on spectators standing outside the venue, and all journalists were to be excluded from the hall. Hansen demanded that only Omid Scobie, a trusted author, and the photographer Misan Harriman were to be given access to the event. Harriman’s photos would be published only in Town & Country magazine, ordered Hansen.[7] Not the mainstream media. Harriman was surprised to be the sole photographer. Despite producing Meghan’s Vogue cover and photos of baby Archie, he’d had no contact from her ever since. In Meghan’s world, it seemed tradesmen were ignored until required.

Any protest that the media restrictions would damage Meghan’s request to be globally positioned as a philanthropist was dismissed by Keleigh Thomas Morgan. ‘KTM’s as useless as a chocolate teapot,’ scoffed an organiser. ‘Completely out of her depth.’ Yet Meghan knew no better. Risks were unacceptable to the Duchess.

‘I’ve been abandoned,’ complained Harry days before the event. Stressed about their security, Harry had been told that the Home Office refused to provide armed protection in Manchester and London. But with Meghan’s insistence that her appearance was essential to sustain her brand, he decided to ‘risk assassination’. At least Manchester police provided extra cover to avoid a major incident. And a whole rail carriage was reserved for the journey from London to Manchester. Although the public would be barred from access to the ‘royal carriage’, Harry later complained about the dangers he faced ‘because of his proximity to the public’.[8]

Before leaving Frogmore Cottage, still their Windsor home, Charlotte Tilbury herself had spent three hours on Meghan’s make-up. The final touch-up was completed at the Kimpton Clocktower Hotel in Manchester. After lunch and a rest, the couple were driven to The Bridgewater Hall. Over 2,300 eager young people were waiting. Herlihy refused the suggestion that they enter through the kitchen. They would brave the crowd. As they emerged on to the empty pavement, Harry heard ‘God Save the Queen’ booming from a circling van and a few distant boos. ‘They’re all paid by the tabloids to show up,’ Harry later pronounced.

Anxious about her speech, Meghan stood waiting off-stage while Harry, ever the professional, humoured his hosts with small talk. Hovering alongside was her publicist Ashley Hansen. Dressed in over-the-top Californian lifestyle clothes – a large trench coat, a big hat and sunglasses – Hansen symbolised Meghan’s similar discomfort of appearing in front of a British audience.

Escorted amid a standing ovation on to the stage, Meghan, wearing a red dress, adopted her rictus Hollywood smile, while Harry clapped with what was now arguably his perma-scowl. Meghan had abandoned the billed theme: ‘Ethical leadership – how can we instil transparency, honesty and integrity as core values for leaders?’ To Ella Robertson’s anger, her speech praised One Young World, who ‘saw in me what I wanted to see fully in myself’. And over the next ten minutes, she spoke exclusively about herself and her rise to fame.[9]

‘She’s tone-deaf to others,’ Robertson realised. ‘She just can’t do what we wanted. She’s toxic.’ Every organisation inviting the Sussexes, she concluded, would need to factor in disappointment and an inevitable storm. At the end of Meghan’s speech, the audience clapped politely.

Anxious about missing the train back to London, the Sussexes rushed from the building oblivious to the organisers’ indignation and the impression it gave that the couple felt that the British people were irrelevant and easy to ignore. In Meghan’s mind, the British and their country were irrelevant. Dissatisfied Brits were apparently easy to ignore, not least the Royal Family. She had accumulated all the ingredients for her career. She would appear to enjoy irritating her critics and enemies. Whatever had happened in the preceding months, Meghan clearly saw herself as the victor.

* * *

The next few days were hectic for the couple. Encouraged by Harry to play on the Royal Family’s popularity in Germany, the Invictus executives had arranged for a flight the next day on a Luftwaffe jet from RAF Northolt, a small airport in west London, to get the couple to their event in Düsseldorf. After landing, they were driven in a high-speed police convoy to the city’s town hall, where they were greeted at the end of a red carpet as heads of state by Mayor Stephan Keller. Unlike in Manchester, Harry was happy to be interviewed. ‘Great,’ he told the Invictus executives, clearly pleased to be feted.

On his return to London for the WellChild awards ceremony in the Lancaster Gate Hotel, Harry flourished as the popular prince – genuinely friendly towards the children and their parents and hailed as thoroughly good. At the end of the day, Harry returned to Frogmore anticipating his imminent return to Los Angeles. Deeply distrusted by the royal household, Harry had been purposely kept ignorant of events occurring in Scotland.

That night, 7th September 2022, Edward Young, the Queen’s private secretary, was near his 96-year-old sovereign at Balmoral. The Queen’s life, he knew, was ebbing away. Bone marrow cancer had taken its toll. Princess Anne was by her mother’s bedside. Prince Charles was hosting a dinner 150 miles away by road, at Dumfries House in Ayrshire. Operation London Bridge, the plans for a state funeral, Charles’s accession and much more after the monarch’s death, was under way. The following morning, Harry and Meghan would discover the depth of the Royal Family’s distrust towards them.

CHAPTER 2

Global Celebrity

Ever since Harry and Meghan met, on her initiative, on a blind date arranged in July 2016 while she was working at London’s Wimbledon tennis championships, Meghan had given thanks for her amazing luck. At the time, she was on the verge of losing her role in the cable TV series Suits and her Canadian boyfriend, Cory Vitiello, too. Landing Harry had transformed the life of a single, potentially unemployed 34-year-old actress who had just confessed to her publicist that she planned to freeze her eggs.

Scrambling through Google and newspaper profiles, she discovered how Harry was a confused character crying out for love and punished for his vulnerability. After their first meeting in London’s Soho House, she had called Harry to arrange a second meeting and then snapped up his invitation to stay with him at a safari camp in Botswana.

Over many days in the African bush, Meghan listened to his list of woes, clearly satisfying Harry’s quest for sympathy. She was so unlike his last long-term girlfriend, Cressida Bonas, the aspiring British actress who had tired of Harry’s conviction that spies were watching him through every window – even when they visited friends for dinner – and how he was a target to be shot. Bonas was exhausted from standing next to a man who seemed to be on the edge of a nervous breakdown. One of the many reasons for Harry’s love of Meghan was her patience.

Unlike Bonas, who ended the relationship with Harry in 2014, Meghan appeared to be sympathetic to the torrent of his paranoid fears, much of it repeats of what he had told his therapist. ‘Generational trauma’ was the victims’ catchphrase to lament how their emotional needs were not satisfied. Meghan encouraged Harry’s certainty that anything he passionately believed must be true. Objective facts – namely, the real truth – were disposable if inconvenient. Within weeks, their mutual commitment was sealed. Harry was besotted by his new soulmate – a surrogate mother, homemaker, confessor, consigliera and safety net. Within months, cynical Palace officials were whispering about Meghan having ‘found a meal ticket’. Their suspicions outraged Harry.

Unreservedly, Harry identified with Meghan’s discomfort. ‘The hierarchy of my family,’ he said, was to blame. For thirty years, he complained, the institution had controlled and imprisoned him. Throughout his life, no one wanted to understand his frustration and his sense of inferiority. Few had listened to his need for an identity, any identity other than being the unloved ‘spare’. Beyond that personal torment, Harry was evidently too inarticulate and too adrift to be able to explain to Meghan the royal hierarchy. He felt himself pushed by his family to the side of the stage.

Aware of Harry’s complaints, the Palace had devoted enormous efforts during the months before their glittering wedding on 19th May 2018 – a glorious sunny day – to familiarise Meghan with the reality of life as a royal. Although Meghan would tell Oprah Winfrey in 2021 that Palace officials had never explained what she could expect, senior courtiers had obeyed the Queen’s orders to coach Meghan for her role in a constitutional monarchy.

Among the formalities designed to teach Meghan about her new life was the service to become a member of the Church of England. Unaware of the teachings of the Bible, she was helped by the Archbishop of Canterbury, Justin Welby, to understand the religious procedures. To underline its importance, the whole Royal Family led by the Queen and Prince Philip gathered in St James’s Chapel Royal to witness the thirty-minute ritual of Meghan’s baptism and confirmation. At the end, few eyewitnesses believed that Meghan had taken her vows seriously.

To ensure that the 37-year-old American was aware of the complications of marrying into the Royal Family, Edward Lane Fox, Harry’s private secretary, presented a specially prepared thirty-point dossier to Meghan covering every aspect of royal life. It explained how, as patrons of hundreds of organisations, from lifeboats to the Royal Opera House and many community charities, the Royal Family embodied the heart of British society, applauding tens of thousands of generous volunteers. The politically powerless family represented the nation and its shared values, the glue that held Britain’s disparate society together. Some would conclude that Meghan did not read the dossier.

A parallel attempt was made by Samantha Cohen, appointed by the Queen to explain royal life and the monarch’s neutrality. The Queen’s genius was to disguise her beliefs by never revealing an opinion, especially about controversial causes. Dedicated to serving Britons and the Commonwealth, her primary duty was to cultivate goodwill, dissolve tension, and defend Christianity and the culture of her peoples. Palace officials suspected that all those conversations passed Meghan by. Harry would later write, ‘Meghan wasn’t given one minute of training.’[10]

Already fearing disaster, a senior member of the Establishment was asked to explain personally to Meghan what to expect as Harry’s wife. Every month, he met Meghan in Kensington Palace for ninety minutes. Occasionally, Harry was present. Meghan, he discovered, dominated their relationship. Assuming the minor role, Harry appeared to be proudly besotted by his fiancée.

‘You’re not just marrying Harry Windsor,’ said the official, ‘you’re marrying the British constitution.’ Meghan smiled. Her future life in the Royal Family, she was told, would be inside a bubble. Beyond the wealth and traditions, there would be fences restricting her life. And a lot of standing up and curtsying. And always someone watching. Meghan smiled again. Conscious of her looks, she gazed into the distance, unwilling to accept the warning about the limitations that would be imposed on her. There’ll be a lot you can’t do, she was told. Again, Meghan’s eyes glazed over. She was unwilling to understand that the institution would take over her life and the boundaries were strict.

After a few weeks, the senior official mentioned the Abdication – the decision in December 1936 by Edward VIII to renounce the throne in order to marry the American divorcee Wallis Simpson. After leaving Britain, Meghan was told, the Windsors had ended up in a cul-de-sac. She clearly sympathised with the Duchess of Windsor. But in her mind, she would dictate her own terms. Sycophantic submission was certainly not contemplated by the Californian.

The senior official grasped that Meghan saw herself at the centre of every situation. With a sense of her own important role, she anticipated remaining in total control of her own future. Any talk about hierarchy passed over her head. Lurking beneath the surface, he realised, was her refusal to be bound by Britain’s traditions. She would decide her actions for herself and if the Palace imposed constraints, then she would have the rules changed. If there were no changes, she would go. The official was startled. The marriage would be bumpy, he told an aide. If it lasted. He knew that no Palace official or member of the Royal Family would be able to control Meghan if she refused to conform. Everyone in Buckingham Palace would be powerless.

Another official lamented that the Californian refused to grasp that, ‘the Royal Family is the nation’s family and a national obsession. The royals may appear to be ordinary people but to maintain the monarchy, they relied on the public’s willingness to treat them like gods.’[11] Meghan, the advisor belatedly realised, ‘thought she should also be treated as a god’. It was clear that Meghan was ignoring all the advice. Meghan, one muttered, saw the Prince as her prize.

Meghan’s unpredictability dawned on Palace officials when ‘family’ was mentioned. Meghan admitted that she brought baggage to the marriage. The model of a stable marriage had not existed in her own life. Her childhood, she said, had been difficult. Her relations with her family, she explained, were bad. Particularly with her father, Thomas Markle. Those speaking with her were surprised by her sense of isolation. But worse, she showed no interest in fostering better relations with Harry’s family. She refused to engage with those speaking about compromise and obedience. Fears about her intentions were confirmed after she disclosed, weeks before the ceremony, that ‘I hope my father won’t be coming to the wedding.’ The admission shocked her audience.

In the months before the wedding, officials noticed that Meghan had sidelined her father from the arrangements. He was not sent an invitation, nor did Meghan ask a British embassy official to offer him help, as she had in the case of her mother. More telling, Harry had not tried to meet Thomas Markle in Los Angeles. As the international media aggressively doorstepped the retired studio lighting technician’s home in Mexico, Meghan appeared to abandon him. Palace officials assumed Meghan had good reason to distance herself from Thomas Markle, especially after he famously lied about staging photographs of his preparations for the wedding. That was just one of many surprises causing alarm.

By then, those Palace officials closely involved had concluded that both Meghan and the Royal Family had ‘unrealistic expectations’ about her life after the marriage ceremony. For Meghan’s part, she clearly refused to accept any restrictions. On the other side, the Royal Family were deluding themselves. From the Queen down, they assumed she would somehow slot into her place. None of the senior royals understood that Meghan was questioning a thousand years of history. No official can recall that among the senior royals one voice was heard warning, ‘This must work. We cannot have another Diana.’ Six years later, Meghan explained her stance: ‘I was just so done with the prove-it game.’ She refused to be judged. She admitted challenging the Royal Family: ‘If you can’t see it, I don’t have to prove it to you.’[12]

As Meghan set out her own expectations, a senior member of the Establishment noted Meghan’s rejection of royalty’s mystique. Uninterested in the monarchy’s place in Britain, she ignored the special aura that elevated the Royal Family. In her mind, the royals were more like super-celebrities.

Meghan spoke about The Firm, believing that the Queen ran the monarchy like the president of Universal Studios. She didn’t want to understand the labyrinthine network of personal relationships, interlinked organisations, livery companies and secret committees that comprised the Establishment. In her self-focused manner, she knew nothing about the ghosts of the past. Nor could she imagine the Queen’s private secretaries receiving calls from all over the world asking, ‘What does the Queen think?’ And, ‘What will she do?’

The Queen’s suspicions about Meghan surfaced before their wedding. To the monarch’s displeasure, Meghan insisted on making many of the decisions about the arrangements without consulting anyone. Not only did Meghan refuse to discuss with the Queen her wedding dress – the monarch complained it was ‘too white’ for a divorcee – but Meghan had approached the Archbishop of Canterbury to conduct the wedding without first consulting the Dean of Windsor.[13] An argument erupted after the Queen reprimanded Harry about his fiancée’s demanding behaviour. Harry retorted that Meghan was being treated badly. In his fury, Harry shared Meghan’s conviction that he too was being disrespected. The sovereign’s warnings were ignored. Harry was baffled. Meghan was acting no differently than Harry himself in his daily life. To him, she had a right to command. He aligned himself with Meghan and away from his military virtue of loyalty. Meghan, as senior Palace officials had realised, was loyal to no one. Even to the Queen.

Having made little effort to understand the reasons for global admiration of the Queen, Meghan, as the guest editor of Vogue in September 2019, would exclude the monarch from her list of fifteen ‘Game Changers’. The Queen’s senior advisors were not surprised. They acknowledged by then that the Queen’s efforts to welcome Meghan into the family had been rebuffed even before her wedding, notably by Meghan’s preference to sidestep protocols and traditions.

The report of Meghan’s 45-minute visit to the headquarters of the College of Arms located since 1555 in London’s Queen Victoria Street confirmed the Establishment’s worst fears. On the Queen’s orders, Meghan, the new Duchess of Sussex, was to have her own coat of arms. The design would be supervised by Thomas Woodcock, the Garter Principal King of Arms. Meghan’s arrival in Woodcock’s office was unexceptional. Every newly created peer visited to discuss his or her title and every aspect of Britain’s heraldry for their elevated position. The Californian had entered into an alien world of ancient British families, chivalry and their symbols. She would have been surprised to hear that Woodcook’s annual salary, set in 1618, was just £47, reduced from £100!

Woodcock’s task was to prevent any embarrassments but Meghan’s request was unprecedented. Convinced that she had been created a duchess in her own right, unrelated to Harry being the duke, she told Woodcock: ‘I want on the coat of arms a songbird with its tongue cut out.’ Woodcock was flummoxed. Any hint of nostalgia was quashed by her moral certitude. The Duchess eventually agreed to a nightingale, but without the image of it being forcibly silenced.

* * *

None of the 1 billion TV viewers watching Harry and his best man Prince William chatting warmly at the St George’s Chapel altar before the arrival of the bride could have imagined their fractured relationship. Similarly, there was no hint of the tension as Meghan was escorted down the aisle by Prince Charles. Few knew about the tears and tantrums as Thomas Markle was prevented from flying to London after a heart attack. Having been depicted as an ogre, some officials were not surprised that Meghan had spoken of her fear of her father ‘suddenly’ arriving in Britain. The Royal Family praised Charles’s concern for Meghan, her actions having galvanised his efforts to offer help. Many observers spotted the inspiration of her dramatic solo appearance at the Chapel entrance before walking alone into the church, namely that she was choosing to replicate Maria at her wedding to Captain von Trapp in The Sound of Music. Her wedding was a feast of self-celebration.

After a somewhat unconventional ceremony, during which the TV cameras spotted Camilla, Duchess of Cornwall, stifling laughter and Kate, Duchess of Cambridge, wearing an unwaveringly stern expression, Meghan’s magnificent performance as she rode through Windsor in the open carriage with Harry was triumphant. Thanks to her Hollywood pedigree, she smiled majestically, waved gracefully and exuded genuine empathy to the crowds lining the streets. Many black Britons who identified with her had travelled especially to see the happy spectacle. By the end of the wedding day, which had cost £32 million, Meghan was confirmed as a global celebrity.

Those later dissecting the event with Kate were less enthusiastic. Meghan’s guest list for the ceremony and dinner included Hollywood celebrities whom she barely knew. The exclusion from the same dinner of some of Harry’s oldest friends did not go unnoticed. Meghan’s apparent dislike of rowdy Englishmen who shared Harry’s fondness for crude jokes had been detected. ‘She scoffed that on Fridays, Harry’s friends oiled their guns for the weekend,’ recalled a Palace official. That signalled, they speculated, her intention to return eventually to California. At the end of the wedding day, the gulf between Meghan and the Royal Family was firmly entrenched.

Within six months, Meghan was irritated that there was little by the way of gushing praise for the few official duties she undertook. Compared to Hollywood, everything in Kensington Palace was strait-laced and straightforward. She felt unrecognised and unrewarded. Meghan’s unwillingness to accept the Royal Family’s diffidence towards Hollywood celebrity was matched by the Royal Family’s reluctance to bestow outright approval of her. The excited fizz among officials after her arrival had waned as her bolshiness grew. And no one became more aggrieved about Meghan’s subversion of royal tradition than William and Kate.

CHAPTER 3

The Tea Party

‘If you don’t mind, get your finger out of my face,’ Meghan Markle snapped at William. The teatime reconciliation meeting between the brothers and their wives had spun out of control.

Tea had been served in the usual traditional atmosphere befitting a medieval palace. The formalities failed to camouflage the tension. Sitting in the Cambridges’ recently redecorated twenty-room Kensington Palace apartment, soon after the Sussexes returned from their honeymoon in June 2018, Harry watched the confrontation escalate. William’s dislike of Meghan had been obvious after his warning to Harry before their engagement. ‘It’s gone too quickly,’ William had said about the speed of Harry’s relationship with ‘the American actress’. William’s suspicion of Meghan was echoed by his wife.

Kate, Harry was convinced, saw Meghan as a threat. The antagonism had started once their engagement was announced. Kate had not appreciated a streetwise, self-confident rival. Clever and stylish, Meghan was clearly unwilling to obediently serve the British people as a member of the royal team. As Meghan would later tell the tennis champion Serena Williams, the Royal Family ‘hates’ ambition. That was associated with vulgar pushiness.[14]

Even before their engagement was announced, Kensington Palace officials had spotted Meghan’s shock about the limited money and perks available to the royals. She had expected marriage to transform her from a starlet into a star, to shine in the spotlight. Compared to the American’s imagining of palatial splendour, Harry’s allowance was less than a Hollywood B-movie actor earned. That must have been intolerable.

As they entered the Cambridges’ apartment, Harry had spotted Kate’s disapproval of Meghan’s torn jeans. Previously, Kate had disapproved of Meghan wearing jeans at Wimbledon. Meghan’s behaviour, Kate decided, was incomprehensible. After all, Meghan would not have gone to the Kentucky Derby in ripped denim.

Harry had been similarly distraught about Kate’s visible ‘disgust’ after Meghan asked to share her lip gloss. Watching Meghan scrape gloss on to her finger, Kate’s glacial freeze had destroyed any suggestion of friendship.‘I was a hugger,’ recalled Meghan. ‘I didn’t realise that that is really jarring for a lot of Brits.’ In Harry’s opinion, while Meghan ‘spread kindness’, the Cambridges responded with spite.

Naturally, Meghan’s undisguised disdain for the Palace’s hierarchy had aroused Kate’s distrust. Kate did not hide her own suspicions. Her restraint was seen as hostility. For her part, Meghan was contemptuous of the Cambridges’ aloofness, it being a far cry from her own personal style: Kate was boring; William had cried himself to sleep at Eton. Both were so detached from her reality.

Meghan believed that Harry was right to feel the Cambridges were jealous of her successful career – just like the Royal Family had been envious of Diana’s. Even after two years in London, Meghan did not understand how seriously the Cambridges and all members of the Royal Family took their roles. The Royal Family was a job. Duty, hard work and self-sacrifice without a big pay cheque was alien to someone brought up in Hollywood. But Meghan had laughed off Charles’s suggestion that she continue working as an actress. Hollywood, she knew, had rejected her.

In this clash of two worlds, Meghan was irritated by the royals’ inflexible hierarchy. More than ever, she resented their ordered and impersonal lifestyle, and that birth dictated seniority. Impatient with the protocol of the royals’ relationships, she mocked that even in private encounters, relations curtsied to acknowledge another’s seniority. She could not understand that the curtsy was to preserve the royals’ aura. How ridiculous, she thought and proclaimed so publicly in years to come, that Harry greeted the Queen with a bow of his head followed by ‘Your Majesty. Granny!’

With that certainty, there was no mystery about Meghan’s unwillingness to curtsy to Kate. Her own talent and popularity, in that reckoning, proved her superiority. Meghan gave the impression that she regarded Kate as an untalented prude, who ought to show the respect she, Meghan, deserved. As seeming proof, Kate had recently hired Virginia Chadwyck-Healey, a former Vogue editor and stylist, to match Meghan with a youthful, lighter haircut and a new wardrobe.[15] Some even came to believe that Meghan saw herself as a more fitting future Queen than Kate.

While Meghan’s certainty of purpose had seduced Harry, her talents had alarmed his brother and Kate. Both knew Harry’s problems – he’d had a damaged youth, confused by drink, drugs and therapy after his mother’s death, and had been unable to cement a balanced relationship with a woman. Both evidently saw Meghan as a threat rather than an ally. Yet Meghan didn’t seem to understand that she could not compete with Kate, the future Queen, nor accept that her task was to support her.

The Cambridges believed that Meghan was not reconciled to what was deemed her destiny in London. She lamented Harry’s unlikely chances of one day being King, just as she regretted the possibility that she would never be the Queen. With Meghan’s encouragement, Harry started to move beyond the Palace’s control. Instead of the likes of his colourless Uncle Edward, Harry refused any longer to accept his fate as the superfluous ‘spare’.

So, on that fateful day, amid all those conflicting, undisguised emotions, the two couples engaged in strained small talk over tea. Then the conversation switched to the cause of their disagreements. Unable to hold back, Meghan took the initiative to list their disputes: Kate’s unhappiness about the Sussexes’ failure to give her children Easter presents, Meghan’s assertion about her superior fashion expertise and, finally, Princess Charlotte’s bridesmaid dress. The dress had become the lightning rod for their acrimony.

Givenchy’s Clare Waight Keller had produced what was considered a poorly fitting wedding dress for Meghan. Similarly, the dresses for the bridesmaids were baggy. So much so that just before the wedding, Kate’s three-year-old daughter Charlotte had burst into tears after trying on her dress. A Kensington Palace staffer had summoned Ajay Mirpuri, a West End tailor. ‘The whole thing,’ Mirpuri later revealed, ‘was ill-fitting and needed to be recut.’[16]

The text messages after Kate told Meghan about the problem reflected their antipathy. Meghan texted, ‘I told you the tailor has been standing by since 8am. Here. At KP.Can you take Charlotte to have it altered as the other mums are doing?’ Kate replied, ‘No, all the dresses need to be remade.’ When they met for Charlotte’s fitting, Kate was anxious.

Kate had given birth to Louis just three weeks earlier. The 36-year-old’s emotions were clearly still fragile. The additional stress caused by Meghan’s attitude during the refitting of Charlotte’s dress provoked Kate to have a tearful outburst, not only about the dress but also about the numerous complaints of Meghan’s treatment towards her staff. Even the Queen was disturbed by reports that Meghan spoke in a harsh, boss-like manner.[17]

Meghan was puzzled. The Palace’s language was alien. The familiar British undertone of asking ‘Are you really going to?’ implying disapproval was the opposite of Meghan’s literal, unequivocal style. A senior Buckingham Palace official had spotted the problem: ‘Meghan cannot understand that you can’t speak to the Royal Family in normal language. Everything is spoken in code.’

Arguments had erupted about Meghan’s acceptance of freebies – especially clothes and cosmetics. In Meghan’s opinion, her aides’ veto of gifts appeared disloyal. After they had also disapproved of her broadcasting controversial opinions, she became annoyed. She wanted them to be governed by her rules. Samantha Cohen, Amy Pickerill and her other Kensington Palace aides described her behaviour as unreasonable. ‘Passively aggressive’ and ‘manipulative’ were among the critical terms they used about Meghan’s behaviour. ‘It’s not my job to coddle people,’ Meghan retorted to a Palace official after being urged to be a little less strident. Those bad vibes disturbed Kate. On the day of the dress fitting, she burst into tears.

Despite Kate’s distress, she had sought peace by personally delivering a bunch of flowers to Meghan. That offering had not resolved the situation. Any sentimentality had vanished long ago. During the reconciliation tea party, she abruptly interrupted Kate.

Meghan declared the cause of their problems was ‘because of your hormones’.[18]

‘You talk about my hormones?’ glared Kate wide-eyed. ‘We’re not close enough for you to talk about my hormones.’

‘It’s no big deal,’ Meghan replied. ‘It’s baby brain.’

‘That’s rude, Meghan,’ William interrupted, jabbing his finger at her face. ‘That’s not how things are done here.’ Her Californian babble irritated William. Scorning his wife had crossed the line.

There had to be a lot of trust before the Cambridges listened to anyone’s advice, and even more trust before listening to criticism.

As he watched the argument, Harry wanted revenge. Not just for the attacks on his new wife but for the torment throughout his life. The Cambridges’ negativity, he was certain, infected his whole family and through them, the media. Everyone had a hostile agenda against him and Meghan. He lived in a palace of lies and liars.

Kate’s particular antagonism, he decided, was deep-rooted. Cool, focused and competitive by nature, Kate in his view had spotted Meghan as a challenger. In style and modernity, Kate feared that Meghan had the edge – the top dog unwilling to compromise or sympathise. In Harry and Meghan’s opinion, Kate had spurned Meghan’s offer of friendship.

That conviction fed Harry’s irritation about the media’s collusion in glorifying Kate. Carefully orchestrated by Buckingham Palace’s communications team, Kate had become the beautifully dressed idol to win popular support for the monarchy. But the public, Harry fumed, failed to see the truth. Kate’s status concealed her insecurities and ambition. By later quoting the novelist Hilary Mantel, Harry appeared to sympathise with her description of Kate as trapped within an institution – the ‘plastic princess’ and ‘a gloss-varnished mannequin selected only for breeding’.[19] Harry was given the words to express his disdain. Kate, he said, fitted the ‘mould’ of what was expected of a royal spouse. Despite the obvious hurt caused to William, Harry hinted his brother’s marriage was from duty not love.[20]

It never appeared that Meghan sincerely wanted a friendship with Kate. Other than with a publicist, Isabel May, and Soho House’s global membership director, Markus Anderson, she had not forged sincere relationships with any Brits.

All those emotions infected the peace-making tea party. Even entering the twenty-room apartment had reawakened Harry’s resentment about his inferiority to William. The Sussexes had come from Nottingham Cottage, their two-bedroom home with inadequate heating and, famously, ‘no ice-maker’. Condemned by Meghan as ‘soooo small’, the cramped darkness within Kensington Palace was starkly inferior to the Cambridges’ extravagantly decorated living room. It was adorned by a seventeenth-century Dutch landscape painting called The Negro Page, showing a young black man holding a white man’s horse.[21]

Harry’s handicap was his inability to express his rivalry coherently. Memories of their intense childhood fights resurfaced, along with rankling about his smaller bedroom. Yet now he also begrudged William for failing to persuade their father to give him more money, a better home and a role in the state.

Meghan would not have understood a senior Palace courtier’s observation: ‘Harry should have sucked the lemon,’ the sentiment that after leaving school the Prince should have accepted the bitter reality of being the ‘spare’ and solved his own predicament.

Back in the Cambridges’ drawing room, unconcerned by Harry’s pique, William’s formal politeness evaporated as his temper rose. He asked Meghan for an apology to Kate and then struck another blow. Meghan, he said, was ‘a difficult person’ who had made ‘enemies of half the staff’.

Harry interrupted. Meghan had no problems with the staff, he insisted. The problem was caused by William ‘parroting the media’s’ lies about Meghan’s childhood and her divorced parents. Thomas Markle’s frequent media appearances attacking his daughter were fuelling the flames.

Whatever the explanation, that afternoon the couples parted on bad terms. They had crossed the Rubicon. The split between the brothers was sealed. Reconciliation would be difficult.

Returning to Nottingham Cottage, Meghan and Harry were distraught. Sitting in their drawing room, it would be easy to surmise that Meghan’s outlook towards her new family hardened and that, beyond Harry’s comprehension, his wife was consumed by a new determination. She hated people who refused to recognise her importance, and wished to destroy those standing in her way to stardom.

CHAPTER 4

William and Harry

Before he met Meghan, Harry had enjoyed a happy relationship with William and Kate, albeit that he had seen less of his brother since Prince George’s birth in 2013. At first, everything appeared better after he met Meghan. ‘When Meghan arrived,’ recalled a senior Buckingham Palace official, ‘it seemed so good on so many counts. Everyone fizzed.’[22]

Battered by his mother’s death, Harry had fallen into Meghan’s arms as a needy casualty of a dysfunctional family. Caring for the ‘spare’ had been beyond the royal institution’s agenda. Even the Queen ignored Harry’s fate – a surprise to those who recall how her sister Margaret suffered emotionally and financially as the ‘spare’. Harry never realised how he misunderstood his grandmother. Behind her genuine warmth, she correctly assessed Harry’s weaknesses. Unlike the Queen’s careful nurturing of William as a future monarch, eyewitnesses recalled that she had been ‘patronising’ towards Harry. ‘The younger brother was psychologically oppressed,’ admitted one senior Palace official disliked by Harry.[23]

Over regular Sunday teatimes in Windsor Castle, the Etonian schoolboy William had bonded with the Queen. Familiar with the truism that Hanoverians could never get on with their elder son, the Queen had a greater influence on William than Charles. Down to earth, insightful, indiscreet, amusing and practical, the Queen taught her grandson that the royals must be polite to everyone. Always under observation, the royals could only trust personal relationships after a long probationary period. Forge a tight circle of reliable friends, she advised, but expect times of loneliness. At the same time, she advised him to experience the normal world to see around corners. Her tutelage was aided by her private secretary, Christopher Geidt. Regularly, Geidt – a former diplomat – ensured that William received government papers, witnessed the Queen meeting foreign ambassadors in Buckingham Palace and visited Commonwealth countries.[24]

While William was carefully steered by his grandmother to choose a suitable wife to create a winning team, Harry remained the victim of generations of poor parenting. Charles had inherited problems with fatherhood. Prince Philip had endured a torrid childhood shipped between unwelcoming relations and marked by little contact with his own father, Prince Andrew of Greece, who had disappeared in 1937. In turn, Charles was himself an absent father who shied away from confrontation with his younger son, indulgently saying ‘No’ rarely. Lurking in the background was always the suspicion that Charles was not Harry’s father. Harry recalled Charles’s quip, ‘Who knows if I’m even your real father?’[25], a suggestion believed by some Palace officials to be too close to the bone.

The limited bond between Charles and Harry was partly rooted in Diana’s lack of education and her differing cultural interests. Blessed with a profound intuition and a strong personality – ‘tough as nails’, some would say – Diana refused to encourage her sons to share Charles’s passion for music, architecture, civilisation, religion, the environment and much more. Even on those days spent together shooting, riding and skiing, Harry and Charles shared little in common. Every parental attempt to treat the brothers as equals was undermined by William’s destiny and the unreality of royal life. Diana had even described Harry as a needy thumb-sucker sitting on her lap demanding attention.[26]

Commuting in chauffeured cars between Kensington Palace, Buckingham Palace, Sandringham, Balmoral and his friends’ country homes, surrounded by bodyguards and obsequious courtiers, Harry always relied on others to do his chores – his shopping, cleaning and even calling for his car. The man who never carried cash, never had a door key in his pocket and never travelled by Tube was oblivious to the real world.

Undoubtedly, Harry was preoccupied with his parents’ divorce, the walk at the age of twelve behind his mother’s coffin and Charles’s relationship with Camilla Parker Bowles. As a reportedly disruptive pupil at Eton, he achieved two poor A-levels – a grade D in geography and, with the secret help of his teacher, a B in art. ‘I’m bottom of the class,’ one fellow Etonian lamented to Harry. ‘It’s all right for you,’ Harry replied, ‘I’m bottom of the school.’[27] Some were sympathetic to Harry’s predicament. He felt imprisoned by having to conform to court rules and public parades. Others scoffed about his extraordinary privileges, not least the dark side of life known to many except, apparently, his father.

Relying on his staff to supervise Harry, Charles allowed his teenage son to spend thousands of pounds on Krug and Grey Goose vodka in Boujis, Mahiki and other London nightclubs – and on drugs. Exposed by the tabloids when he was seventeen for snorting cocaine, including in ‘Club H’, a basement at Highgrove, Charles’s country house, Harry told the Palace to deny the truth.[28] Yet, the Palace had refused to lie to protect him. At his expense, he fumed, they lied about him to protect William, the sacred heir. Fearing that he was a lifelong loser, it was clear Harry would prefer not to admit one truth: he was furious not to be the heir.

Being the ‘spare’ had become intolerable. He was, in his words, ‘the shadow, the support, the plan B . . . the back-up, distraction, diversion and if necessary a “spare” part. Kidney, perhaps.’[29] Convinced that William had even controlled his wedding, he could not imagine his father’s turmoil in anticipation of becoming the king. Charles did nothing to alleviate those anxieties.

Harry blamed his father for his misery. Charles had married Diana out of duty and he had failed to live up to his responsibility to remain loyal to his mother and his children. Instead of understanding his father’s burdens – unhappy schooldays, distant parents and bowing to pressure for his first, loveless marriage – Harry turned against his father, describing him as emotionally dead. Proof was Charles’s failure to hug his son on that fateful August morning in Balmoral when he sat on his bed to tell him that Diana was dead. And later, disregarding his two sons’ pleas, he married Camilla Parker Bowles.

In 2009, the journalist Mark Hollingsworth wrote in the London Evening Standard that Harry had an ‘uneasy relationship with his father’ because ‘Prince Charles was an absentee father.’ Lesotho and his charity work, continued Hollingsworth, had become Harry’s sanctuary ‘far away from the disapproving and detached gaze of his father’. The Standard’s magazine editor received a formal protest from the Palace: ‘There is absolutely no truth in any of these assertions,’ wrote the communications director, Paddy Harverson. ‘The claims made, without any evidence, are incorrect.’[30]

Four years later, in January 2013, Charles understood Harry’s trauma better than others. The army had been Harry’s lifebelt. Hugely popular, he had flourished in Afghanistan as an officer amid real camaraderie. Hearing about his sudden evacuation after a newspaper had revealed his presence, Charles had rushed from Highgrove to meet his son’s returning plane at snowy Brize Norton. Harry, he suspected, would struggle to establish a satisfying life as a civilian.

Suffering ‘post-traumatic stress injury’, Harry was ‘unravelling’. As he later admitted, ‘the first few bubbles started coming out . . . and then it was chaos. My emotions were sprayed all over the wall, everywhere . . . I started to go slightly off the rails, and deal with it through drinking and drugs . . . Unfortunately, like most of us, the first time you consider therapy is when you’re lying on the floor in a foetal position probably wishing you had dealt with some of this stuff previously.’[31]

Harry’s saviour, he had told the journalist Bryony Gordon, was William: ‘He kept saying, “This is not right, this is not normal, you need to talk to someone about stuff. It’s OK.” Bless him, he was a huge support to me.’[32]

With William’s encouragement, in 2016, the brothers founded Heads Together, a campaign to persuade people to feel no guilt about mental health problems. By then Harry was also certain he had been cured. ‘I am not a person with a disorder,’ he said that year.[33]

In hindsight, Harry would complain that his future had been precarious. As the ‘spare’, he protested, he had ‘no money, no status, no decent home and no job’. Palace officials refused to create a separate court for Harry or negotiate an accommodation for him to fit in like his aunt, Princess Anne, or even his great-aunt Margaret. ‘Don’t bother to compete against William,’ a senior Palace official advised him.[34] Frustrated, he found that his father ignored both his complaints and the danger signals. Until he met Meghan, Harry accepted his fate. ‘He always seemed so friendly,’ recalled one Palace official, ‘even as his role declined.’

The official was mistaken. While Harry assumed that he shared with his brother an unbreakable lifetime bond of misery over Diana’s death, he baulked at the barriers erected after William’s marriage to Kate in 2011. After the Cambridges were given more staff, bigger cars and a bigger home, Harry felt himself ‘an outsider, a non-person within my own family’.[35] Convinced that he was being ostracised by the Cambridges, trifling incidents in Kensington Palace became magnified. Arguments about a parking space and disputes about a lack of natural sunlight into his home fired him up. And so did Meghan. Consumed by the memory of Diana, Harry told William, ‘I feel as though she helped me find Meg.’ William was surprised. ‘Well now, Harold, I’m not sure about that. I wouldn’t say that.’

CHAPTER 5

Briefings

During the weeks following the tea party fracas, Meghan seemingly fed Harry’s suspicions, leading Harry to challenge his family.[36]

As his relationships with his family splintered, Harry seemed to be unaware how Meghan had ruthlessly dished her own family – her uncles, aunts, cousins and half-sister – and, more important, had done little to contradict the negative description of her generous father in order to justify repudiating him. Encouraging a similar break between Harry and Charles did not seem to trouble Meghan. ‘They’re racist,’ she suggested was the view to take, and publicly too.

‘I’m being hounded by the media,’ said Meghan. Like the media, she explained, his family distorted the facts to suit their agenda. They manipulated the media against him. ‘Just like against your mother.’ The mere mention of Diana by Meghan triggered an outpouring of Harry’s bitterness.

‘My mother was chased to her death when she was in a relationship with someone who wasn’t white,’ Harry recalled, ‘and look what happened.’[37]

Harry had refused for many years even to acknowledge that his mother was dead. Only that she had ‘disappeared’. Harry chose not to believe that the car crash in Paris in August 1997 had happened because Mohamed Fayed’s drunken chauffeur Henri Paul drove over the speed limit into a dangerous curve – or that his mother had contributed to her own death by failing to wear a seat belt. Contrary to the conclusions of two exhaustive investigations by a French judge and a former chief of New Scotland Yard, and the verdict of a four-month coroner’s inquest in London of an accident, Harry unreservedly blamed the seven paparazzi on motorbikes for having ‘chased Diana to her death’. Journalists, he cursed, were all blood hunters. ‘Shooting, shooting, shooting,’ was Harry’s description of events that night in the Paris tunnel. His mother, he believed, was ‘murdered’ by the paparazzi’s flashes blinding the car’s driver.[38]

Twenty-one years later, Harry declared, ‘History is repeating itself.’ The same tabloids were now hounding Meghan: ‘They’re not going to stop until she dies.’[39]

Harry did not properly understand either his mother or grasp Diana’s own misconception of her effect on others. Deeply disillusioned that her fairy-tale marriage had been a disaster from the outset, Diana grappled with the awful fate of being a royal. Not just the hard work, but also the inevitable disloyalty of some she had trusted. Among the betrayals was that of Panorama’s Martin Bashir, who used forged bank statements produced for him for the BBC to persuade her of treachery within the Palace. Bashir’s lies persuaded Diana to agree to be interviewed. Once the BBC’s dishonesty was exposed, her fears intensified. But one truth did emerge during her Panorama interview: her passion to destroy Charles’s reputation.

Harry preferred to ignore that Bashir was just one of many journalists with whom Diana conspired during her charmingly manipulative conversations. After trusting Andrew Morton to write an excoriating book, unleashing the ‘War of the Waleses’, she had frequently entertained trusted tabloid journalists in Kensington Palace or met them in restaurants and even in their cars to incite mayhem. Her close ties to the paparazzi, especially Jason Fraser, climaxed while she holidayed in the summer of 1997 in the South of France with Dodi, the son of Harrods’ owner Mohamed Fayed, a cocaine-addicted wastrel spending his dishonest father’s money.

On 18th July, the Mirror’s editor Piers Morgan got a call from Fayed in St Tropez. With Diana barking instructions in the background, Morgan was told of the beach where the Princess could be photographed cartwheeling, wearing a leopard-print bikini. Diana had plotted to dominate the following morning’s front pages to eclipse the fiftieth birthday party Charles was hosting that evening for Camilla at Highgrove.[40] Effortlessly attracting global attention, Diana enjoyed casting herself alternately as the victim and the rebel, while at the same time using the media to attack Charles.

But Harry refused to believe that few people manipulated the media more successfully than his mother. Ignoring the truth, Harry would praise Netflix’s version of his mother’s relationship with the Fayeds and her death. The Crown, Harry said, ‘humanised them. It made them relatable.’ Rather than face reality, Harry preferred Netflix’s sympathetic fiction. Portrayed as a scapegoat and the black sheep, Harry felt sorry for himself. ‘I’m way more comfortable with The Crown,’ Harry confirmed, ‘than I am seeing the [newspaper] stories written about my family, my wife or myself.’[41]

Harry was forgetting that communication was critical to the monarchy’s survival. In all the royal households, the national newspapers were laid out every morning on the coffee table. The Royal Family hated the media but relied upon relationships with trusted journalists to project the monarchy’s popularity. Inevitably, there were risks. The same newspaper that one day glorified the royals would publish an embarrassing investigation on another. Harry confused the Palace’s daily media operations to secure good coverage and to bury bad news with deliberate distortion.

At the time of Diana’s death in 1997, the Establishment was grappling with an existential problem: how to protect the thousand-year institution from her sabotage. In 2019, Palace officials realised that Meghan posed the same threat. Harry and Meghan were concocting their own scheme for destruction. In hindsight, Camilla would conclude that in the months after their wedding, Harry had been ‘radicalised by Meghan’.

The Sun’s famous royal photographer Arthur Edwards blamed Meghan too. ‘Harry was a photographer’s dream,’ he recalled. ‘He always projected warmth and kindness across the world. He always had time for a drink, especially in Africa.’ During his famous tour of Jamaica in 2012, Harry told Arthur and others, ‘I’m here to make it work for you guys.’ Soon after he had met Meghan, Edwards realised, ‘Everything had changed. He could not even look at me, let alone talk to me.’ During his visit to Ireland in July 2018, Harry ignored the photographer’s suggestion that he hit a ball with a hurling stick. ‘Usually,’ recalled Edwards, ‘he would join in with the children at schools. Girls would hug him. Great pics. After Meghan, everything became awful.’[42] Something had ruptured.

At heart, Meghan remained commercially minded – a dedicated professional influencer. Unquestioningly, she obeyed the Palace order to close down The Tig, her profitable website endorsing food, cosmetics and lifestyle, after her relationship with Harry was formalised in 2016. Thereafter, the Crown vetoed any commercial activity for personal gain. Just two years later, she questioned why she was not paid for visiting an English town to meet the public.[43] The restrictions were infuriating. She chafed at the wasted opportunity of exploiting the Royal Family as an invaluable money-maker.

Meghan would have learned during her life on the fringes of Hollywood that control of the image maximised celebrities’ income. Instinctively, she had live-streamed Harry proposing marriage to her in Nottingham Cottage with a simultaneous commentary to her then-best friend Jess Mulroney in Toronto. ‘Oh my God, Jess, Jess, Jess. It’s happening. It’s happening.’ And then, ‘He’s really doing it.’ The video recording and the accompanying narrative, she calculated, would surely one day be valuable.

Immediately after her wedding, Meghan resumed contact with her agents in Hollywood, and tasked them to quietly build the foundations for her return to California. ‘Leaving Britain,’ Meghan would say, ‘gave us a chance to create that home we had always wanted.’[44]

The eventual split surfaced four months after the wedding, in September 2018. The Queen’s private secretary, Edward Young, had ‘become angry with Harry for not playing by the rules,’ observed one senior official. ‘Harry was constantly making demands which were inappropriate for his position. He had a constant sense of feeling left out of the family’s private conversations. He wanted to be invited and to participate in their decisions. But frequently he and Meghan were excluded from major events. That was frustrating and hurtful. Both Harry and Meghan were denied access to the Queen. They decided that Young and other officials were deliberately keeping them away from her.’[45] Young understood Harry was a problem, but he was not inclined to pause and produce a solution.

Incited by Meghan’s unhappiness, Harry became visibly angry. Young and others stood silent as Harry fumed. Meghan’s complaints became vocal. ‘Before the wedding, she was told in uncompromising terms the deal for marrying into the Royal Family,’ recalled an official. ‘She began crossing red lines.’ Young underestimated the developing crisis.

In response to the Sussexes’ dislike of Nottingham Cottage, they were offered Frogmore cottages on the Windsor estate. The dilapidated buildings would need complete refurbishment. Anxious to leave Kensington Palace, they ignored the complications involved and those of leaving London for an undistinguished house under the flight path to Heathrow.

Next, Harry declared that he could no longer share an office with William. Not even in the same building (Kensington Palace). Instead of finding the Sussexes an office in Windsor Castle, the Queen ordered that they should be allocated a few rooms in Buckingham Palace. But it was regarded by the Sussexes as a snub.

Amid that turmoil, the Palace and the Foreign Office, in consultation with the Sussexes, finalised preparations for the couple to fly to Sydney on 14th October for a sixteen-day tour of Australia and New Zealand. The last days of preparation were beset with problems. The good news was that Meghan was pregnant. The bad news was that Meghan stole the limelight by revealing her news at the wedding of Eugenie, Prince Andrew’s daughter. Inevitably, the following day the tabloids relegated the wedding and headlined Meghan’s revelation.

But the biggest problem was the uproar among Meghan’s staff. On the eve of the Australian trip, two staffers submitted formal complaints to Jason Knauf, communications secretary to the Duke and Duchess of Sussex, about Meghan’s behaviour. Accused of being polite one moment and rude the next, or blanking a person entirely, the tearful women told Knauf they felt ‘traumatised’.[46]

Outraged that Meghan was under attack, Harry urged Knauf not to pursue the complaints in exchange for urging Meghan to show greater understanding. Employees, he said, could not take ‘constructive criticism’. The media, said Harry, should be told his version and the employees should be asked to sign NDAs. Critical reports of Meghan’s behaviour were reported in newspapers. The Cambridges were to blame, Harry said. They had ‘a knack for backstabbing, a talent for intrigue’ based on ‘rumours and lies’ fed to the media.[47] Harry wanted Jason Knauf to protect Meghan, especially from the criticism of ‘bullying’ her staff. But Knauf and his staff refused. Their policy was not to engage with the tabloids’ tittle-tattle and certainly not to lie. The media reports about the fact of her staff’s complaints were, after all, true. Harry’s explanation was starkly different from his family’s. Harry understood so much better how he had been misled. The genuine ‘truth’ was what Harry himself believed.

The previously loyal Knauf switched sides. He composed a memorandum to Simon Case, William’s private secretary. ‘I am very concerned,’ Knauf wrote, ‘that the duchess was able to bully two PAs out of the household in the past year.’ According to her former staff, he continued, Meghan was vindictive: ‘The duchess seems intent on always having someone in her sights.’ The treatment of one person, he wrote, ‘was totally unacceptable’ and her ‘bullying’ of another seemed to be an attempt ‘to undermine her confidence’. Eyewitnesses reported her as ‘very challenging’ and guilty of ‘unacceptable behaviour’.[48] Meghan, he explained, played mind games with her staff. On one occasion, she had encouraged a staff member in a meeting to undertake a task, but at the next meeting she ignored that person and asked another to do the same work. ‘We have had report after report from people who have witnessed unacceptable behaviour,’ Knauf recounted from what had been dubbed the ‘Sussex Survivors Club’. But since Harry and Meghan were about to leave for Australia, Knauf did not send his memorandum to Case. On Harry’s instructions, his lawyers would later deny that Harry had even discussed the issue with Knauf or had interfered.

Large crowds welcomed the Sussexes on 15th October to Sydney. In Harry’s eyes, the Australians’ excited admiration for his wife over the next sixteen days proved that Meghan, as Harry later proclaimed in his memoir, was more than a ‘supporting act’ for the Royal Family but was ‘stealing the limelight’ and ‘doing the job better than the person who is born to do this’. Namely, his own family. Harry was convinced that Meghan was a global superstar. Though any pleasure looked to be undermined by the undiluted resentment he had brought to Australia from Britain.

Reading through media reports every night, Harry and Meghan were convinced that Buckingham Palace’s silence about their success was born of jealousy. Harry blamed the media for ‘distorting the truth and trying to manipulate the power of positive thinking’.[49] Harry was by now on his path to being determined to destroy the tabloids, the purveyors of bad news and worse.[50]

For her part, Meghan never understood that when she was greeted by thousands of enthusiastic crowds it was not just because of her celebrity but to hail the Royal Family and its embodiment of Britain’s best traditions, culture and values. The Sussexes’ frustration was magnified by the ceaseless cascade of vitriol spouted by anonymous trolls on the web.

The arrival of David Beckham in Sydney stirred up more trouble. The football star had been invited by Harry to sit alongside him at the Sydney Invictus Games. Beckham had especially flown to Australia with his family to oblige the Prince. But after arriving at the stadium, he was snubbed. In her anger, Meghan forbade Harry to meet him.[51] So Harry had ordered that under no circumstances would he meet Beckham or be photographed with him. After waiting, forlornly, Beckham returned to his rented house on North Shore.

Behind the scenes, Meghan’s conduct had become increasingly intolerable for her staff. Both Meghan and Harry were accused of screaming at and bullying their employees. She had thrown a cup of tea into the air in the High Commissioner’s residence.[52] Her staff’s renewed complaints from Australia to Knauf triggered his decision to forward his summary to Simon Case on 26th October: ‘I am very concerned [about] some very serious problems.’ The continuing Australian tour, wrote Knauf, was ‘very challenging’ and ‘made worse by the behaviour of the duchess’. The head of human resources at Clarence House, Samantha Carruthers, agreed ‘that the situation was very serious’. A few weeks later, a member of Meghan’s staff, Melissa Toubati, accused Meghan of being ‘dictatorial’ and resigned after only six months’ employment. Hearing about the revolt, Meghan would later conclude, ‘Most people need to find someone to blame.’[53] That excuse would bear little credibility after the Queen drove across the Windsor estate to Frogmore to reprimand Meghan for insulting a sub-gardener.[54]

The Sussexes’ welcome on returning to London was cool. Buckingham Palace’s officials failed to congratulate them and neither the Queen nor Charles mentioned their success. Reports about the turmoil on the Australian tour were appearing in newspapers and on YouTube channels. William was furious. Among the royals, there was a code to show genuine gratitude towards their staff. Not only for their loyalty but also for enduring long hours despite low salaries. Customary good manners, William believed, had been breached by Harry for siding with his wife.

William arranged to meet Harry at Nottingham Cottage. In Harry’s version, William was a tinderbox when he stood in the kitchen berating his brother and Meghan for insulting their staff.[55] Some would say that behind an inscrutable veil, William’s temper revealed his true character. His elder brother, Harry would say, had perfected a level of complexity of double betrayal.

Harry denied the accusations. William, he said, shouldn’t believe newspaper headlines about ‘Duchess Difficult’. A violent argument broke out between the brothers. In Harry’s account, William unexpectedly pushed his brother. Harry fell to the floor, broke a dog bowl and discovered that his neck chain had been ripped. Dazed, he demanded that William leave the house. To seek help, since Meghan was not at home, Harry called his therapist. At the age of thirty-four, he still could not cope with such an argument.[56]

In the background, aggravating the Sussexes, was Thomas Markle’s continuing denunciation of his daughter on TV and in newspapers. Thomas’s coruscating condemnation of Meghan was watched by millions across the globe. Despite the tension within her office, Meghan still relied on Knauf to solve her problems. With his help, in August 2018, Meghan had handwritten a letter to her father urging him to refrain from public criticism. Although she assumed that her letter would eventually be leaked to a newspaper, it was sent to her Los Angeles business manager Andrew Meyer for delivery to Thomas in Mexico.

Simultaneously, Meghan asked Knauf to spend two hours briefing journalist Omid Scobie about her background for his proposed book about the Sussexes. At the time it was untitled, but eventually published under the title Finding Freedom. Despite anticipating that Scobie’s book would support Meghan and represent her case against the Royal Family, Knauf helped the journalist with personal information provided by Meghan. Later, Meghan would sign a legal statement that she had never asked Knauf to speak to Scobie.

Few outsiders knew about the fractured relations when the Royal Family gathered at Sandringham for the annual Christmas party in December 2018. Photographs of the family’s famous walk to church on Christmas Day showed the smiling Fab Four together. Their performance was perfect. Within Sandringham, though, eyewitnesses saw entrenched frostiness between the two families. The Sussexes had every reason to feel isolated. Distrusted by his family, Harry watched his wife spiral into misery after reading the media’s accounts of her misconduct.

Sandringham offered Meghan no comfort. Under grey skies on flat Norfolk countryside, its old furnishings reeked of the post-war era, with antiquated bathrooms installed shortly after 1945. Visitors were offered sausage sizzles and walks. The hierarchical atmosphere within the gloomy house was deemed to be the legacy of Queen Mary, the austere wife of George V. Her rigid rules imposed unnatural formalities on close relatives. ‘Your father,’ she told her two sons, ‘is the King. Address him as “Sir”.’ Her legacy still permeated Sandringham seventy years after she died. ‘It’s hell to live as a hangover of Mary,’ said one of Mary’s descendants. ‘It’s hell to be a royal.’

On her return to London, Meghan poured out her grief to her American girlfriends. The golden days of the wedding, a mere seven months earlier, were long forgotten. During those frequent calls, Meghan’s friends commiserated and encouraged her disdain about the Royal Family. They supported her desire to shine like Californian glitterati, not live like a hermit with the discretion demanded by Buckingham Palace. They listened sympathetically to her complaints that the hierarchy was stifling her potential. ‘They’re suppressing my creativity,’ she complained. ‘I can’t express my true self.’ She was fighting ‘in the trenches’, she later recalled.[57] Being ordered by Palace officials to wear ‘nude pantyhose all the time’ made her feel ‘inauthentic’, she complained.[58] A homily offered by the NBC executive who launched Suits, Bonnie Hammer, appealed to Meghan. Namely, the importance of ‘self-love’, having ‘a very strong sense of self’ and ‘finding someone who believes in you’. Harry had filled that role. And Harry, Meghan said, should also adopt self-love.

Whether anyone realised that Meghan had reached a tipping point is doubtful. In Meghan’s version, on 16th January 2019, she felt suicidal. ‘I just didn’t want to be alive any more,’ she would say.[59] If she could not be the Queen, then she would destroy her enemies, just as she had her father and anyone who frustrated her ambition.

The publication of America’s People magazine on 6th February 2019 sealed her fate. Actress Abigail Spencer had approached Dan Wakeford, the magazine’s editor, and revealed Meghan’s deep misery. Four other girlfriends of Meghan also agreed to speak ‘anonymously’ to the magazine about the horrors Meghan was facing. Two of those women also disclosed a version of Meghan’s letter to her father. The confirmation of the existence of that letter and the quotes of Meghan’s words could only have originated from Meghan.[60] The global reaction to People’s revelations was explosive. Once again, to the world it seemed that Meghan had betrayed her father.

Despite Meghan’s hysterical demands that Knauf deny the truth on her behalf, he refused to reply to the hundreds of media enquiries. Stonewalling the world with ‘no comment’, the Royal Family and Palace officials concluded that Harry, influenced by Meghan’s vengeance, had become her uncontrollable accomplice.

In Mexico, Thomas Markle was outraged by the magazine’s portrayal of the letter as Meghan’s bid for reconciliation. ‘A total lie,’ he told the Mail on Sunday’s Caroline Graham. ‘Meghan’s a total liar and very controlling.’ To prove Meghan’s duplicity, Markle showed Graham his daughter’s letter. In Thomas’s version, Meghan’s letter was a reprimand combined with implicit threats. Excerpts were published in the London newspaper.[61]

The battle between the media and Meghan had become public and brutal. Her supporters, alias the ‘Sussex Squad’, condemned journalists as ‘sexist, racist and snobs’.

CHAPTER 6

A Divisive Agent

Meghan sensed a turning point. Throughout her life, she had desired media attention. To many, her ambition and opportunism had spurred her eagerness to marry Harry, but her ultimate goal was unattainable. Ever since the wedding, she had felt trapped. Having given Harry emotional security, her influence bestowed power – and an opportunity to influence Harry’s relationship with the Crown, his family and, finally, with Britain. Every step to resolve the complications of his life, especially his obsessions about his mother, the media and his mental health, was carefully considered. Either genuinely disturbed or the master of a Hollywood performance, Meghan gradually convinced Harry that, like Diana, she too was the victim of Palace intrigue. To escape persecution and as the cure to his unhappiness, Meghan suggested they might need to leave Britain.[62]

‘It was bittersweet, you know?’ Meghan reflected later. ‘Knowing that none of it had to be this way.’[63] If Palace officials and the Royal Family had bowed to her demands, she suggested, she would not have returned to California. The realities dictated it was her way or the highway.

As they discussed the solution to their combined misery, Harry did not contemplate his disloyalty to his family. On the contrary, he accused them of treachery.[64] ‘I was obsessed,’ Harry would admit about the hours he spent during the day and night searching the internet.[65] The British media, said Harry, was ‘toxic [and] destroying my mental health’. Like Meghan, he was unable to resist reading the online condemnation. He was consumed by the media’s refusal to regard Meghan as utterly perfect, a paragon of virtue. Eager to ‘destroy’ his and Meghan’s lives, the ‘wolves’ were ‘distorting the truth’.[66] Every slight confirmed that the monster was devouring him. Creeping isolation gnawed at his self-confidence.

‘Don’t read it,’ Charles told Harry about the media, but his son clearly could not resist. Harry was certain that his family were ‘complicit’ in the ‘pain and suffering’ inflicted on Meghan by trolls and the tabloids. In Harry’s version there was a conspiracy between Palace officials and the media to plant negative stories about the Sussexes. The Royal Family’s motive, he said, was self-protection from the media’s possession of a ‘shit ton of dirt about my family’. Probably, he said, Kate and William were fuelling the antagonism. His beloved Meghan now shared his own fate as the victim of ‘institutional gaslighting’. Both their reputations were being trashed.[67] His mother’s murderers, he was convinced, would destroy his next great love.

In the midst of that discussion, on 20th February 2019, just six weeks before giving birth to Archie, Meghan arrived in New York for a baby shower. Hosted by Serena Williams the extravagant party for fifteen Americans in a £57,000-a-day penthouse suite at The Mark Hotel signalled Meghan’s rejection of drab royalty and her embrace of Hollywood glitz. All of her friends were later seen to monetise their relationship with the Duchess, just as she used the trip to lay the foundations for her return to Los Angeles. Two years later, Meghan ridiculously accused the Palace of taking away her passport to prevent her travelling.[68]

On the advice of her Hollywood agent, Meghan swiftly organised a new website to promote Brand Sussex. ‘She can call her own shots,’ said her spokesman.[69] In a familiar pattern, as she opened her new website, she told an audience, ‘I don’t read any social media.’[70]

While Meghan secretly negotiated her return to California – and openly pitched to Hollywood producers to re-establish her acting career – Harry went through the motions of creating a separate office for the Sussexes’ own charities in London. Disingenuously, Buckingham Palace’s announcement on 14th March about the creation of two offices for the Sussexes and Cambridges denied there had been a ‘rift’ between the ‘Fab Four’. In reality, the split was even deeper than insiders acknowledged.

Amid a deliberate plan to confuse the public and the Palace about the timings, Harry’s son Archie was born on 6th May at the Portland, a private hospital in London. Although the gynaecologist was named as Melissa Drake with remote support by childbirth expert Gowri Motha, over the following weeks, due to the lack of information being made public, conspiracy theories flourished and Meghan’s critics became convinced that Archie was delivered from a surrogate mother.

To protect her family’s ‘privacy’, Meghan broke convention by forbidding any pictures of Archie with the Queen and Prince Philip to be shared with the media. Buckingham Palace’s most senior officials quietly agreed for the first time that Meghan was a liar.[71] ‘We weren’t asked to take a picture,’ Meghan initially explained. ‘That was part of the spin; that was really damaging.’[72] Clearly realising that was inaccurate, she then admitted that she herself had banned photographs. That was, she told Oprah Winfrey, her protest about the Palace denying Archie a prince’s title and also police protection: ‘I was very scared of having to offer up our baby, knowing that they weren’t going to be kept safe.’[73] Both those explanations were untrue, but contradictions in Meghan’s narrative were not unusual.

After his birth, Meghan announced that Archie would be a ‘private citizen’ without a title.[74] Later, she insisted that the Royal Family had denied Archie a title – and because he had no title, he would not be protected by the police. And her reason for both denials was the Royal Family’s objection to Archie’s brown skin. ‘How does that make sense?’ she would ask Oprah Winfrey.[75] Those accusations were untrue. On his birth, Archie became Lord Dumbarton, a traditional title given to the Duke’s son, a vital detail Meghan left out of the conversations.

Three years later, Meghan gave another reason: she refused to allow the first photos of Archie to be distributed to the British media because the tabloids were ‘the very people that are calling my children the N-word’.[76] It was a statement that was clearly designed to shock but inaccurate, the original reference in question coming from a tabloid headline highlighting ‘niggling doubts’, an old Danish phrase that can be traced back to the Vikings with no connection to race.

The real truth to many senior officials was that since the newspapers would not pay her for the photographs, Meghan decided there was no reason to co-operate. Unknown to the public and the Palace, before Archie’s birth, Meghan had already laid the groundwork for an agreement leading to her interview in 2021 with Oprah Winfrey and the American broadcaster CBS. The first photographs of Archie were available only to CBS.

Harry was aware of Meghan’s transaction. To establish the Sussexes’ financial foothold in America, Harry had also agreed to tell his personal family story in a series called Mental Wellness with Apple TV. The producer would be Oprah Winfrey. Everything was falling into place for a headline-grabbing exit from Britain.

William’s original fear was materialising. Meghan had become a divisive agent. To please her, Harry was ignoring his old friends. He had even changed his telephone number without telling his family.

During the summer of 2019, the Sussexes’ office was more chaotic than usual, while anger and hysterics raged within the Sussexes’ home. Harry’s few remaining friends witnessed a man transformed. The jovial lad about town had become possessed by seeking revenge. Increasingly, his character mirrored Meghan’s. Emotionally, he veered towards extremes. Simple dislikes became passionate hatred. ‘Meghan’s brainwashed Harry,’ Camilla told a friend.[77]

Harry’s and Meghan’s behaviour had prompted another two aides, Samantha Cohen and Amy Pickerill, to resign. ‘We have very exhausting principals,’ admitted Marnie Gaffney, Buckingham Palace’s media assistant attached to the Sussexes. Owing to Meghan’s self-love and Harry’s mean-mindedness, the couple blamed the staff for the fall-out. Harry conjured the scenario for their departure. ‘The breaking point for me,’ he said, ‘was finding Meghan in tears while breastfeeding Archie. The cause was the poisonous tabloids’ reports about “Duchess Difficult”,’ continued Harry. ‘And she is someone who doesn’t read the stories. She would be dead if she was reading the stories.’[78] How Meghan became aware of the media’s stories highlighting her impertinence without reading them online was unexplained. Nor whether her tears were genuine. As she once boasted to fellow actors, she could produce tears on demand. ‘I can do that so well. Oh my God, it’s crazy.’[79]

In July 2019, Meghan rejected the Queen’s invitation to visit Balmoral. Archie, she explained, was too young to fly. Days later, though, she flew with her two-month-old baby to the South of France as guests of Elton John. The world assumed that the Sussexes’ jaunt on Elton John’s private jet was for a holiday. No one knew that the singer had arranged for Harry to meet David Sherborne, a barrister specialising in suing newspapers.

Aged fifty, Sherborne was mocked as a vain, slick operator dressed in unusually tight suits with dyed hair and skin toned by a sunbed. He was also notorious for his colourful relationships with women. Following two marriages and two divorces, he had brushed with scandal after enjoying an affair with a fellow lawyer while both worked on the Leveson inquiry, a controversial investigation in 2011 into the illegal practices by newspapers to invade celebrities’ private lives in search of news and scandal.

Sherborne was on a mission. Consumed by his desire to expose newspapers’ crimes, he had represented actors and entertainment professionals, including Elton John and Hugh Grant. His loathing of newspapers appeared to be matched by his desire to push himself in front of cameras alongside his famous clients. Adding Harry would naturally hugely boost his campaign. Not only would a royal’s inclusion be unprecedented but the chances of success would improve. ‘We needed someone with money,’ Hugh Grant admitted in an ITV documentary.[80]

In the warm, affluent atmosphere of Elton John’s Mediterranean villa, Harry willingly fell into Sherborne’s lap. His sales patter was no doubt enticing. Among his past clients, said Sherborne, were Michael Douglas, Tony Blair and Harry’s mother, Princess Diana. Critically, as a lawyer in the Leveson inquiry, Sherborne had seen the list of payments by the newspapers to private investigators between 2005 and 2011. Only with great reluctance had the newspapers handed over that potentially incriminating evidence, relying on Judge Leveson’s promise that their documents would never be published. They would be sealed by law, promised Leveson, and could not be published without Ministerial permission. Sherborne did not forget what he had read.

Sherborne added a critical ingredient to his fluent sales patter. In 2015, he had won a notable victory against the Mirror Group.The judge, Anthony Mann, had decided that the Mirror’s journalists and editors were immersed in a widespread culture of ‘extensive and habitual’ unlawful activities including hacking telephone voicemails.[81] ‘Habitual’ meant that illegality was routine for the journalists during that period. If a journalist had contact with a hacker, said Sherborne, the journalist was himself a hacker. Many journalists, he believed, had lied to Leveson and destroyed incriminating evidence.

Eight claimants won against the Mirror. Rival lawyers were stunned by Judge Mann’s antagonism towards the newspaper group and his generosity to Sherborne. Demolished by that judgement, the Mirror Group, which had published an apology for phone hacking even before the first trial started, thereafter settled other claims, paying damages and costs.

To Harry’s glee, Sherborne added that Rupert Murdoch’s News UK was equally culpable. Rebekah Brooks, the former editor of the News of the World and the Sun, had been identified by Leveson as knowing about her journalists’ unlawful activities. Brooks had been prosecuted and acquitted, Sherborne acknowledged, but she could still be sued to recover damages. News UK’s records, continued Sherborne, showed hundreds of payments by their newspapers to private investigators. Among their targets was Harry’s former girlfriend, the Zimbabwean Chelsy Davy. Unlawfully, they had hacked into her voicemail, emails and Facebook account, it would later be claimed.[82]

Sherborne then surely delivered the final inducement: the litigation would cost Harry very little. He would bear no financial risk. The reason was that all the claimants’ lawyers worked on a contingency basis – no win, no fee. All Harry needed was an insurance policy to cover the newspapers’ costs in the unlikely event he lost. And Sherborne had never lost. That formula would earn Sherborne at least £40 million and enrich Temple Legal Protection, the insurance company which pocketed a large slice of the damages awarded by the judges to the claimants. To monopolise the litigation, Sherborne and the solicitors staggered their cases: first the Mirror, next News UK, and finally they would target the Daily Mail group.

Sherborne, Harry decided, was ‘a lovely fellow who knew more about the hacking scandal than anyone I’d ever met’.[83] With that, he unleashed his fury. He damned newspapers for ruining his life. And vowed to get his revenge.

For over ten years, Harry believed, the tabloids had targeted him by unlawful means. Sherborne crafted his sentiments about the tabloids: ‘They would very quickly seek to try and break up [every relationship] by putting as much strain on it and creating as much distrust as humanly possible.’ He believed the tabloids’ malice continued: ‘This twisted objective is still pursued to this day even though I’m now married.’ He felt ‘as though the tabloid press thought that they owned me absolutely’.[84]

Trusting the lawyer, Harry admitted: ‘I could have been hacked on a daily basis. I simply don’t know.’ All he knew was their intrusion had been horrendous. Similarly, he also said that Meghan was the ‘prey’ for online ‘hunters’.[85]

Harry went further though. He blamed the media for his own mistakes – drunkenness, drugs, wearing a Nazi uniform at a party and being filmed nude at a Las Vegas hotel. Newspapers, he believed, should have suppressed the truth. He made no allowance that other royals had suffered worse. Not least Charles and Camilla, with the excruciatingly embarrassing ‘Tampongate’ recording in 1989, and his mother with ‘Squidgygate’ – taped calls of her conversations in the late 1980s with her lover James Gilbey.

How, Harry asked Sherborne, could he ‘find a way to stop the abuse, intrusion and hate that was coming towards me and my wife?’[86] In the past, his desire to attack the media had been blocked by the Palace, but now he wanted to wage war. Except, in public, he spoke about his ‘life’s mission to reform the media’. The Palace, he explained, had blocked his previous attempts for retribution by citing a secret agreement between News Group and Buckingham Palace concluded in 2012 or earlier. To keep the media onside while Charles smoothed Camilla’s path to become Queen, the Royal Family had agreed not to sue News Group for hacking their telephones. In 2017, continued Harry, the Royal Family with the Queen’s agreement concluded a settlement with Murdoch for News Group’s ‘unlawful information gathering’. William was paid £1 million but Harry received nothing. Thereafter, said Harry, Charles discouraged him from bringing a claim against News Group.[87] There was no evidence, Charles had said, that Harry had been hacked. His father, said Harry, had been involved in the cover-up.

‘Why not hire your own lawyer?’ asked Sherborne. By suing newspapers he could discover if he had been hacked. That had never occurred to Harry.[88] Under Sherborne’s tutelage, the Prince let him dictate the next steps. The Sussexes had crossed a boundary. They were about to embark on an eight-year battle against Britain’s newspapers.

On their return to London, Harry consulted the Royal Family’s trusted solicitor Gerrard Tyrrell of Harbottle & Lewis. Yet the lawyer advised against suing News Group. Swiftly, Meghan convinced Harry that Tyrrell was ‘taking directions from Clarence House’. The same solicitor had advised Meghan not to sue the Mail on Sunday for breaching her privacy and copyright by publishing excerpts from her letter to her father. Meghan had ignored Tyrrell and the Palace and, on Sherborne’s advice, hired Schillings.

Keith Schillings is an aggressive London solicitor not previously employed by the Royal Family. Proudly, he is the antithesis of Tyrrell, a pukka West End lawyer.

Before he acted, Harry called William. His brother suggested that ‘I seek permission from Granny.’ Harry called the Queen and, he claimed, she agreed he could bring an action. Palace officials were not consulted. The timetable for what followed was set by Schillings.[89]

Relying on Sherborne and his publicists, Harry also agreed to issue court claims against Mirror Group Newspapers and News UK for their unlawful activities. At the same time, Meghan would ignore the Palace’s advice and claim against the Mail on Sunday. Schillings’ argument was precise: Meghan’s relationship with her father was private. No public interest could justify breaching her copyright and privacy by publishing her letter.

Attacking the media would be the Sussexes’ curtain-raiser to leaving Britain. Their declaration of war was to be broadcast in South Africa.

CHAPTER 7

Leaving Britain

On the eve of leaving for a ten-day official tour of South Africa on 23rd September, Beth Herlihy, a private secretary in Kensington Palace, noticed that Meghan was suffering from ‘baby blues’. ‘She’s having a breakdown,’ Herlihy confided. ‘She’s very unhappy and Harry can’t fix it.’

Over the previous months, Palace officials had devoted huge effort to please the Sussexes’ constantly changing demands. Their procrastination and indecisiveness had, in the opinion of one senior Palace advisor, become a ‘sickness’. Unexpectedly, even Archie became a tool of the Sussexes’ brand. Meghan insisted that their son, at only four months old, should also come on the official tour to South Africa. Palace officials were puzzled. Just three weeks earlier, Meghan had refused to visit the Queen in Balmoral because Archie was too young to fly. Some now understood her intentions and, more significantly, Harry’s insincerity.[90] Africa, Harry had repeatedly said, was critical to his life. Yet it appeared that he was planning to ignore the importance of Britain’s reputation during the tour to publicise his personal agenda.

During the first days in South Africa, the tour was hugely successful. Corralled British journalists, kept away from the Sussexes, ecstatically reported Meghan’s virtuoso speeches. Posing as ‘a mother, feminist and advocate’, she addressed eager audiences as a Hollywood celebrity, the women’s champion, an anti-racist warrior and, above all, as ‘your sister’.

Unreported was the Sussexes’ conduct. Both Meghan and Harry were ignoring advice from all their courtiers. Sara Latham, on the Sussexes’ media staff, was seen in tears and another member of her staff condemned Meghan as ‘a nightmare’. Jason Knauf and the human resources director Samantha Carruthers had both resigned. Carruthers complained of being ‘treated harshly’. Those convulsions remained unreported by the media, but worse was imminent. Harry planned to deliver a bombshell statement prepared by his lawyers in London.

Ignoring pleas by Palace officials not to ruin the tour, Harry fired his first shot. Journalists in South Africa were directed to read Harry’s post on the Sussexes’ official website that had been drafted by Sherborne. The Prince denounced the ‘press pack’ for ‘relentless propaganda’ against Meghan by pursuing ‘a game, and one that we have been unwilling to play from the start’. Harry continued, ‘Unfortunately, my wife has become one of the latest victims of a British tabloid press that wages campaigns against individuals with no thought to the consequences, a ruthless campaign that has escalated over the past year, throughout her pregnancy and while raising our newborn son. There is a human cost to this relentless propaganda, specifically when it is knowingly false and malicious, and though we have continued to put on a brave face, as so many of you can relate to, I cannot begin to describe how painful it has been. Because in today’s digital age, press fabrications are repurposed as truth across the globe. One day’s coverage is no longer tomorrow’s chip paper.’

Clearly forgetting her New York baby shower, Harry claimed that the media had created ‘lie after lie at her expense simply because she has not been visible while on maternity leave’. While failing to identify the ‘lies’, he revealed their anguish: ‘I have been a silent witness to her private suffering for too long . . . To stand back and do nothing would be contrary to everything we believe in. There comes a point when the only thing to do is to stand up to this behaviour, because it destroys people and destroys lives. Put simply, it is bullying, which scares and silences people. We all know this isn’t acceptable.’

Finally, he referenced Princess Diana, the omnipresent shadow of his mother. Meghan, he said, was ‘falling victim to the same powerful forces’ and his ‘deepest fear is history repeating itself. I’ve seen what happens when someone I love is commoditised to the point that they are no longer treated or seen as a real person. I lost my mother and now I watch my wife falling victim to the same powerful forces.’

Shortly afterwards, legal firm Schillings issued a High Court claim on Meghan’s behalf against the Mail on Sunday. British judges, Keith Schilling knew, could be trusted to protect the Royal Family from embarrassment. The Mail on Sunday, Meghan claimed, was ‘deliberately stirring up’ a dispute between Meghan and Thomas Markle as part of an ‘agenda’. Her father, described as a ‘vulnerable and fragile individual’ had been ‘exploited . . . harassed and manipulated’ by the media. Hours later, Thomas Markle robustly ridiculed those suggestions.

‘Hysterical’, ‘ill-advised’, ‘hot-headed’, ‘self-indulgent’ and ‘over-emotional’ were a few of the newspapers’ verdicts about Harry’s statement and Meghan’s High Court claim. The mood on the tour turned sour. The Sussexes had tainted months of hard work to improve Britain’s status in South Africa.

The third assault, a full-frontal attack on the Royal Family, was simultaneously being filmed in South Africa for ITV by Tom Bradby, a trusted friend of Harry’s. The TV documentary, Harry & Meghan: An African Journey, was meant to focus on the Sussexes talking about South Africa’s human tragedies. Instead, the Sussexes used Bradby to issue their declaration of war.

Seemingly uninterested in the distressful lives of the people living in a nearby township as portrayed by ITV, the Sussexes spoke about their own plight. Harry retold how Diana’s death had brought him close to a breakdown. The trauma of walking behind his mother’s coffin in public reminded him of the ‘bad stuff’ and ‘a wound that festers’. He continued, ‘I think being part of this family, in this role, in this job, every single time I see a camera, every single time I hear a click, every single time I see a flash it takes me straight back, so in that respect it’s the worst reminder of her life as opposed to the best.’ Then he made his bombshell revelation. Persuaded by Meghan that all relationships were dispensable, Harry disclosed that his relationship with William was fractured: ‘We’re on different paths at the moment.’

Meghan provided an even more explosive interview. Clearly rehearsed, she dramatically bit her lip in the falling light as she whispered to Bradby that she felt ‘vulnerable’ during her pregnancy, how the pressure was ‘hard’ and the experience of ‘just trying to be a new mother or trying to be a newlywed’ was ‘made really challenging’. As tears welled up, she blamed the British tabloids for trying to destroy her life. American newspapers, she emphasised, would never criticise her. ‘I really tried to adopt this sensibility of the British stiff upper lip . . . I never thought this would be easy, but I thought it would be fair.’ Though many will sympathise with the emotional plight of a new mother, it should not be forgotten that Meghan had boasted she could produce tears on demand.[91]

Would it be fair, asked Bradby, to say that she is ‘not really OK’? Another tear dramatically fell as Meghan replied with a swipe at the Royal Family: ‘Yes. And also, thank you for asking, because not many people have asked if I’m OK. But it’s a very real thing to be going through behind the scenes.’ With a hint of more tears, she deftly added another rehearsed line: ‘It’s not enough to just survive something, right? That is not the point of life. You’ve got to thrive.’

Left dangling was the Sussexes’ future. ‘I don’t know,’ replied Meghan. ‘You do just take each day as it comes.’ Harry had already made his plans: ‘I did what any husband and father would do. I needed to get my family out of there.’[92] The royal tour came to an abrupt end and the pair returned to Britain ‘confident’ and ‘courageous’, as recalled by a Palace employee. Two years later, Meghan claimed that during her marriage, she had been forcibly ‘silenced’ by the Palace, not allowed to express any opinions.[93] Yet their defiance at that time had made their South African tour a success – for themselves.

Harry was summoned to Buckingham Palace to meet Edward Young and Clive Alderton, the Queen’s and Charles’s private secretaries. Tall with floppy hair, Alderton, aged fifty-two, educated at Abingdon School, had entered the Foreign Office despite not going to university. After serving as a diplomat, he had been appointed to work in Clarence House in 2006, shortly after Charles’s and Camilla’s marriage. To have survived in Charles’s service for that long proved Alderton had exceptional talent never to challenge his employer. As a charming old-school courtier, he could both reassure Charles of his obedience but also steer his employer in the right direction.

By contrast, Young, aged fifty-three, bespectacled and stubby, was a cautious former corporate head of communications who had been deputy to Christopher Geidt, the Queen’s legendary and loyal private secretary. Geidt had been ousted in 2017 by Charles and Prince Andrew for seeking to control their dangerous excesses. Both princes were involved in what Geidt believed were damaging financial activities. And in Andrew’s case, particularly his relationship with the American paedophile Jeffrey Epstein. Geidt wanted to control both princes from Buckingham Palace. Yet despite his impressive military bearing, Geidt’s weakness was arguably his lack of leadership qualities. After his dismissal, the royal households were staffed by contrary courtiers – especially Young versus Alderton – each guarding their fiefdoms, torn between serving individual members of the Royal Family and the institution of the monarchy. To the Crown’s misfortune, Young had been an ideal deputy but was regarded by insiders to have been promoted above his abilities.

In the case of Harry’s war against the media, Alderton and Young were united. Both ‘demanded’ that Harry did not sue News UK.[94] Harry ignored their advice. There was worse to come.

ITV planned to broadcast Bradby’s South African interviews during the Cambridges’ official visit to Pakistan. The tour was important both for British diplomacy and to showcase Kate’s transformation during her maternity leave into a more glamorous, self-confident woman. Harry was asked to negotiate with ITV to delay the broadcast. He refused. It was a move that was judged to be wanton sabotage of the Cambridges. An almost unnoticed casualty was another TV documentary, crafted to promote Camilla.[95] Among members of the Royal Family, the Sussexes had lost the benefit of any doubt.

On 12th November, Hillary Clinton visited Meghan at Frogmore House. As Meghan unloaded her anxieties, Clinton offered her unqualified understanding. Meghan’s treatment, Clinton believed, was ‘heart-breaking and wrong’. In the politician’s opinion, Meghan’s meteoric rise was being crushed by the Royal Family. The Sussexes, she believed, were ‘struggling to have a life of meaning and integrity on their own terms’.[96] Clinton, it appeared, had willingly participated in Meghan’s well-crafted choreography to escape from the Royal Family.

By then, Meghan’s publicist Keleigh Thomas Morgan had found a temporary home for the Sussexes – a secluded seaside mansion on Vancouver Island, conveniently north of Los Angeles. Three weeks later, the Sussexes arrived at Mille Fleurs, a luxurious five-bedroomed waterfront mansion where they would be guarded by six Canadian government protection officers. Their stay had been arranged by the 71-year-old Canadian music producer David Foster, a friend and neighbour in Santa Barbara of Oprah Winfrey. Like Meghan, Foster was represented by Keleigh Thomas Morgan.

Officially, the Sussexes would not spend Christmas at Sandringham after all. Their spokesman briefed that the couple would establish a presence in a Commonwealth country. From Vancouver, said her spokeswoman, Meghan could ‘resume her business activities’.[97] Located in the same time zone as Los Angeles, Meghan was in constant communication with Andrew Meyer, her business manager, Rick Genow, her lawyer and Keleigh Thomas Morgan. Together, they plotted their final journey – to Los Angeles.

CHAPTER 8

Sandringham

Harry and Meghan knew exactly what they wanted from the Royal Family – status, money and protection. Only eighteen months after their wedding, they were negotiating their exit.

Under Meghan’s guidance, Harry had composed an email to his father setting out their demands. Fearing it would be leaked to the media over Christmas, he held it back. He was unaware that a member of his own staff had passed it to Dan Wootton, the Sun’s showbiz editor. But, concerned about a backlash after the Palace had strongly denied the truth about the Sussexes leaving Britain, the newspaper’s editor refused to publish Wootton’s scoop.The Sussexes, wrote Wootton, planned to divide their time in North America between representing the Crown and, at the same time, using their royal titles to earn money.

Even without reading Harry’s email, Charles and the Queen knew from telephone conversations with him that he wanted to disengage from royal service in Britain. Not least because among his proposals, Harry suggested that if a solution could not be found, ‘we would be willing to relinquish our Sussexes titles, if need be’.[98] He failed to mention that the titles could probably only be revoked by an Act of Parliament. After several exhausting calls, the 93-year-old monarch told her grandson to speak exclusively to Charles. For his part, Charles was united with William that they should not concede to Harry’s demands. All three royals sought advice from their private secretaries. The most important was the Queen’s private secretary, Edward Young.

Unsure how to resolve the Sussexes’ demands, Young consulted Charles’s private secretary, Clive Alderton. Alderton’s suspicions about Meghan were shared by Simon Case, William’s secretary. By then, the three had discussed Knauf’s complaints about Meghan’s mistreatment of her staff but had done absolutely nothing. Meghan’s staff remained unprotected and she had not been formally advised to control her behaviour. All three had obeyed their bosses: the Queen, Charles and William. Nothing, the three had decided, should be done to further inflame the Sussexes.

All three private secretaries had similar qualities. They were solid, loyal and decent. They were also cautious courtiers accustomed not to take the initiative. Their survival depended on giving advice that they knew would please their royal masters. Stepping out of line was unimaginable. Notoriously, Charles instantly dismissed anyone who failed to give him unquestioned obedience, whereas the Queen usually listened to advice before making a decision. William was known to take advice but occasionally failed to control his temper. All three private secretaries understood that the royal command was final. In those circumstances they had failed during November to fully persuade the Royal Family that the Sussex crisis, brewing since the wedding eighteen months earlier, was about to escalate.

Confirmation of the Sussexes’ real intentions arrived in London just before Christmas 2019 from the British High Commission in Ottawa and the Canadian government. Conversations with the Sussexes and others indicated that the couple intended to stay in North America and never return permanently to Britain. The Queen was not surprised by Young’s report that the Sussexes weren’t coming back: ‘Of course not. They took the dogs.’[99] On the Queen’s orders, Young ensured that no photograph of the Sussexes stood on the table beside the Queen during her Christmas broadcast. Watching in Vancouver, Harry was shocked, not understanding the consequences of his actions.

Discussions were to begin again in the new year. Before leaving Vancouver for London on 5th January with Meghan, Harry expected to head from Heathrow to Sandringham for tea with the Queen and to stay overnight. During those hours, he planned to persuade his grand-mother to approve their planned semi-exile. Later, Harry would claim that the Queen was not surprised that he went to America. ‘She knew what was going on. She knew how hard it was. She never said to me she was angry. I think she was sad it got to that point.’[100]

But other opinions would suggest that Harry had deluded himself. The Queen’s closest officials recorded that the Queen was mystified by the Sussexes’ behaviour. She did not trust Meghan and suspected Harry had been manipulated. She was easily persuaded by Charles and William that the Sussexes should not be invited to Sandringham after they arrived. Accordingly, just before boarding the plane, Harry was told that the arrangement was cancelled. He called his grandmother. ‘There’s something in my diary I didn’t know I had,’ the Queen told him. ‘I didn’t know I was busy. I’ve been told that I’m busy all week.’

During the nine-hour flight, Harry fumed. ‘They’re blocking a grandson from seeing his grandmother,’ he told Meghan. He blamed his family’s three private secretaries. ‘I’d spent my life dealing with courtiers, scores of them,’ Harry would recall. ‘But now I dealt with just three, all middle-aged white men who’d managed to consolidate power through a series of bold Machiavellian manoeuvres.’[101]

The following year, with the help of the ghostwriter of his autobiography, Harry would categorise the three private secretaries. Simon Case, William’s private secretary, known in Kensington Palace as ‘master of circumvention’, was called the Fly: ‘The Fly had spent much of his career adjacent to and indeed drawn to shit. The offal of government media and wormy entrails, he loved it, grew fat on it, rubbed his hands in glee over it.’[102]

Clive Alderton, Charles’s private secretary, was the Wasp: ‘He was great at pretending to be polite, even servile . . . A short while later, without warning, he’d give you such a stab with his outsized stinger that you’d cry out in confusion: Where the fuck did that come from?’

Edward Young was dubbed the Bee: ‘Poised that people didn’t fear him [which was] a big mistake, sometimes their last mistake.’

Harry’s colourful exaggeration of the men’s abilities was dictated by his attitude towards those who refused to give him what he wanted: ‘I disliked these men and they didn’t have any use for me. They considered me irrelevant at best, stupid at worst.’ In his naivety Harry refused to understand that the private secretaries owed their loyalty to the interest of the monarchy and the Queen, and to no one else. Their task was to protect the Crown.

After landing in London, Harry telephoned Young. Controlling his emotions, Harry described his mental health problems. Unable to cope with the stress, he told Young it would be best to make a public statement and return immediately to Canada. Young urged Harry not to annoy the Queen. She expected to see him at Sandringham after the various options had been considered. That would happen within one week.

Yet the following morning, 7th January, the Sun published Harry’s emailed proposals of giving up a life of public service. Harry was incandescent. Charles, he was sure, had leaked his email to sabotage the negotiations. Nothing, he raged to Meghan, had changed in six years. It was just the Palace’s latest smear of ‘leaking and planting of stories against me and my wife’.[103]

Prompted by the leak, Harry emailed his proposals to Charles on 8th January 2020. At the same time, he and Meghan issued a public statement that they would be ‘stepping back’ as full-time senior royals. In future, they would split their time between Britain and North America ‘to carve out a progressive new role within the institution’. The public challenge to the Royal Family was dubbed ‘Megxit’.

On the same day, the three private secretaries met in Alderton’s office in Clarence House with an official from the Cabinet Office to discuss the Sussexes’ fate. They planned to wait for Meghan to return to her son in Canada before inviting Harry to Sandringham. The three knew that the Queen had some sympathy for Charles’s second son. Her own father had faced the same predicament, as had her sister Margaret. The family had never fully considered the needs of the ‘spare’. She wanted to accommodate the Sussexes, as long as they didn’t try to have it both ways. But she was not prepared to allow them – especially Meghan – to earn money while retaining their royal status. Exploiting the Crown for commercial enrichment was unacceptable. There could be no compromise, the Queen insisted. The three private secretaries understood that. Meghan did not. Harry was too consumed by rage to grasp one truth: what many saw as Meghan’s betrayal of the Royal Family was matched by his own wish to destabilise it.

Harry understood that Meghan planned to exploit the Royal Family label. The foundations of Meghan’s monetisation of the monarchy had been already laid by her Los Angeles business advisors. They had registered in Delaware a slew of domestic items – pens to clothing – to be sold under the Sussex Royal logo. In their statement, the Sussexes said they planned to ‘work to become financially independent’.

On 11th January, Edward Young sent Harry a draft proposal, written by Simon Case, with the five options for the arrangements for his future life. The options ranged from carrying on as working royals to the full severance as representatives of the Royal Family with the loss of security. This, option five, was not acceptable to the Sussexes. Meghan encouraged Harry’s conviction that he could deliver her wishes during the summit negotiations in Sandringham. With that, she returned to Vancouver but intended to join the summit over Zoom on her return. Just before Harry entered Sandringham’s Long Library on 13th January, Young announced that Meghan would not be allowed to participate. No one trusted Meghan not to record and monetise the conversation in the future. Subsequently, Meghan denounced her exclusion – ‘as a mom and a mother’ – as disgracefully misogynistic.[104] But the Queen, who was present, was a mother and none of the other royal spouses attended the meeting. And it’s a truth universally acknowledged that families owe each other loyalty. Meghan’s fractured relationships with her own family and ex-husband showed that neither she nor Harry had considered the circumstances beyond their self-interest. ‘I want a family, not an institution,’ Harry later said, sadly not understanding the ramifications of his actions.[105]

Some recall Harry’s meeting in Sandringham with Charles, William, the Queen and their private secretaries as tense but sober. By contrast, Harry, commenting on the last time he would sit around a table with his family, regarded them all as ‘cold’ and William as a ‘rolling catastrophe’. Fearful of Meghan’s popularity, Harry would say that his family were terrified of the Sussexes. ‘It was terrible,’ Harry said, ‘to have my brother scream and shout at me, and my father say things that simply weren’t true and my grandmother quietly sit there and sort of take it all in.’[106] Harry conveniently blamed Charles and William rather than the Queen for the outcome.

Harry’s portrayal of the Queen as a sweet but powerless puppet operating at the mercy of darker, superior forces, obeying orders from courtiers and her family, exposed his misunderstanding of reality. Harry couldn’t imagine that the Queen was horrified by his behaviour. She hated confrontation and was aware that marriage had changed him for the worse. Although his grandmother undoubtedly cherished their close relationship, she cared more about her family as a whole – and the monarchy. Harry, she realised, was beyond reason. He would only listen to Meghan. ‘You’re either in or you’re out,’ the Queen declared.

But Harry was right that the Queen no longer wanted to be at the centre of arguments. On Charles’s orders, she had sacrificed her long-serving private secretary Christopher Geidt, an invaluable advisor. In the aftermath, she preferred not to take some decisions. They were delegated to Charles and William.

At the end of ninety minutes, Young distributed a draft of the statement the Palace would be publishing. Option five was the outcome. Ordering Harry to give up all his appointments and his HRH title, the Prince was told that neither he nor Meghan could use their royal titles to earn money.

The public statement, approved by the Queen, did leave the door open, though. While the Sussexes would ‘always be much-loved members of my family’ the Queen publicly acknowledged, ‘I recognise the challenges they have experienced as a result of intense scrutiny over the last two years and support their wish for a more independent life.’ She hoped ‘they would start building a happy and peaceful life’. In return, Harry pledged that the Sussexes would always remain loyal servants but he left his family unable to understand why the Queen had ruled out the compromise he wanted.

For Harry, a defining moment came as he was driven from Sandringham through the flat Norfolk countryside back to London. Kensington Palace, Harry heard on the radio, had responded to a newspaper report that Harry and Meghan were leaving Britain because William had bullied the Sussexes. Kensington Palace’s rebuttal described the newspaper’s accusation as ‘false and offensive’. To Harry’s fury, the statement was issued in both his and William’s names. ‘I couldn’t believe it,’ Harry later said. ‘No one had asked my permission to put my name to a statement like that.’ He telephoned Meghan. ‘She burst into floods of tears because they were happy to lie to protect my brother, yet for three years they were never willing to tell the truth to protect us.’[107]

Harry blamed William for assuming the responsibility of protecting the ‘institution’. Some insiders agreed that William dictated the terms of banishment. Primogeniture, they said, had poisoned the brothers’ relationship. Encouraged by Kate, William wanted everything down to the last 5 per cent. Rather than giving Harry £3 million a year and telling him to be obediently quiet, the Prince was denied money, support and permanent protection. Brotherly spite, Harry believed, was responsible for stripping him of his military commands, which had been the rock of his life. ‘William looked as if he planned to murder me,’ Harry wrote. Anyone defending the institution, hated by himself and Meghan, was an enemy. He and Meghan cared only about ‘staying alive’.[108]

Meghan believed that it was a critical moment: ‘Suddenly what clicked in my head was “It’s never going to stop”.’ Harry agreed, explaining later: ‘So there was no other option at this point. I said, “We need to get out of here.”’ [109] In truth, they had decided to leave Britain more than one year earlier.

The naivety of Edward Young and the other courtiers emerged on the eve of Harry’s return to Canada. At the Palace’s request, Boris Johnson, the prime minister, was asked to persuade Harry to reconsider his proposed exile. Meeting Harry in east London, Johnson realised before the end of their twenty-minute conversation that he was immersed in ‘a ridiculous business . . . when they made me try to persuade Harry to stay. Kind of manly pep talk. Totally hopeless.’[110] No politician could undo what had been plotted for two years. Against an agent of destruction, the failure of imagination among the Windsors and their officials was carelessly inflicting lasting damage on the monarchy itself. Without any obvious resolution to the Sussexes’ insurrection, no one anticipated how the melodrama could be steered away from a tragic showdown.

Back on the remote Vancouver Island, Harry and Meghan grappled with the reality of isolation. His family, Harry concluded, had decided to make the Sussexes irrelevant. The summit was ‘just for show’. Harry could not accept that Young had simply obeyed the Queen’s orders.[111] Only weeks later did the former soldier finally realise that he had got the bullet. ‘He was once the Queen’s grandson,’ one observer noted. ‘Now he’s his wife’s husband. That is his tragedy. It’s also hers.’ Harry never understood how his fate had evolved to lead him to this very point.

The public’s reaction to ‘Megxit’ was divided. Some were outraged by the Sussexes’ ingratitude and self-destruction after being universally welcomed on their wedding day. A substantial minority were convinced that the Sussexes were the victims of the merciless white Royal Family. ‘Black Britons know why Meghan wants out,’ wrote Afua Hirsch in the New York Times. ‘It’s the racism.’[112] That opinion, Meghan and Harry believed, justified their next steps.

CHAPTER 9

Freedom

Heathrow’s Windsor Lounge is a sanctuary for the rich and famous. For about £3,000, an airline passenger can buy privacy and supreme comfort before being driven personally to the aircraft’s steps. Undoubtedly, the building has been a watershed for many lives and none more than Prince Harry’s as he waited for his return flight to Vancouver in January 2020.

In the hours since the battle in Sandringham, Meghan had hastened to confirm their commercial agreements. Her business manager and agent in Los Angeles assured her that a contract with Netflix was certain. Filming could start as soon as they arrived in California. Oprah Winfrey was eagerly waiting. Meghan also encouraged Harry to see that monetising his anger was the best cure. Everything he said would change their lives for the better because he was right. Betrayal, she knew, was a good story, and evidently best told on TV and as an autobiography.

Meghan arranged for Jennifer Rudolph Walsh at William Morris Endeavor to be confirmed as Harry’s literary agent. Promoting herself as one of America’s most successful agents with links to Oprah Winfrey and other women celebrities, the steely Walsh acknowledged Harry’s promise to deliver a brutal exposé of his life within the Royal Family. The Prince never considered his hypocrisy.

‘It’s amazing what people will do when offered a huge amount of money,’ Harry said about Thomas Markle accepting $1,500 to stage paparazzi photographs before Meghan’s wedding.[113] Meghan’s mother Doria joined the public lynching: ‘I was stunned Tom would be part of this circus, that he would capitalise.’[114] Harry had also damned Thomas Markle for selling interviews about his daughter, yet he was about to do exactly the same for considerably more money. Harry knew exactly what he was doing – it was no different from Diana in her many interviews. He was aiming to damage the Royal Family as much as possible. On Harry’s behalf, Walsh pitched a three-book deal. America’s biggest publishers were told that Harry would need a ghostwriter.

Similarly, while Meghan complained that her father gave TV and magazine interviews despite being told not to speak, she too was about to give interviews to Vogue, People magazine, Oprah Winfrey and Netflix.

All Meghan’s planning since her marriage was bearing fruit. She was well advanced in the process of recruiting a director for Archewell, her Californian commercial organisation dedicated to ‘illuminating, thought-provoking and diverse narratives that underscore our common humanity and celebrate community’. Their later protestations of arriving penniless in America were inaccurate.[115] Not only had Harry inherited over £10 million from his mother and grandmother and Meghan had saved about $2 million, their agents had also promised multi-million-dollar advances.

Yet secluded on Vancouver Island, Harry’s indecisiveness delayed the couple’s next step.Harry feared making the final break to Los Angeles. All his promises at Sandringham about working loyally for the Crown while living in Canada and not financially exploiting his royal status would be shown as worthless.

But first they would return to London on 5th March to stage a Hollywood-style farewell. Astutely, Meghan choreographed photo opportunities in the City, while Harry made an emotional farewell to the Royal Marines at the Royal Albert Hall. Jointly, they made a final tense appearance with the unfriendly Cambridges at the Royal Family’s Commonwealth Day Service in Westminster Abbey. The Royal Family’s obvious disdain for the exiles set the scene that Omid Scobie witnessed at Buckingham Palace. ‘It didn’t have to be this way,’ she told their authorised biographer.

To ensure that her message was publicised to her fans, she told a ‘friend’ – a publicist – to deliver her parting words to the Daily Mail: ‘I gave up my entire life for this family. I was willing to do whatever it takes, but here we are. It’s very sad.’ In words that sound accompanied by violins, her curated elegy appealed to her supporters, including ITV’s Tom Bradby. Obligingly, the journalist went on to criticise the ‘racist’ Royal Family: ‘Few meaningful attempts were made by anyone to heal the wounds.’[116] Others were outraged by the actress’s dishonesty. To them, she had sacrificed nothing and gained invaluable status. Marriage had transformed an unemployed, virtually unknown actress into a global celebrity. After exploiting the Royal Family for three years, she had become a master creator of smokescreens. Even the New York Times endorsed her contrived lament. The Sussexes, the newspaper pronounced, had left London for ‘an uncertain life as semi-royals’ in ‘a distant frontier outpost’.

Soon after their return to Vancouver Island – just as his Palace staff had forewarned Harry – the Canadian government announced that the 24-hour taxpayer-funded police protection around their remote home would be withdrawn. ‘Vipers,’ Harry complained, publicising his fear about not being ‘able to protect my son’.[117] Harry was also reminded by the Palace that the deadline to cease being a working royal was 31st March. To comply, the SussexRoyal Instagram account should be immediately closed. One other message sealed his fate.

In March, Jennifer Rudolph Walsh advised Harry that Penguin Random House in New York was likely to make the best bid for his autobiography. If three bestselling books were delivered, the Sussexes could earn in excess of $20 million. Harry’s first book would be guaranteed about $3 million. The contract would not be signed for some time but he needed to start work. They should resettle in California as soon as possible.

Always fearful of lacking sufficient money but also aware that her celebrity should now be more fruitful than the kind of freebies she had extracted from her lifestyle blog The Tig, Meghan sought the loan of a suitable home in Los Angeles and a free private jet to take all their possessions from Vancouver. She relied on Keleigh Thomas Morgan. The publicist didn’t understand Britain or the Royal Family, but specialised in Hollywood celebrity. The two agreed that Meghan should appeal for help as the target of the Royal Family’s racism. Their pleas were answered by Tyler Perry, a high-profile black film producer. On 14th March, shortly before American air space was restricted by the Covid crisis, the Sussexes loaded all their possessions on to Perry’s private jet and flew to Los Angeles. The countdown to pocketing millions of dollars from their royal lives began on that flight.

‘Good morning,’ said Harry after pressing ‘video’ on his mobile phone. ‘It’s 6am on 14th March and we are on the Freedom Flight. We are leaving Canada and we are headed to Los Angeles.’ He added a lament about escaping the ‘level of hate that is being stirred up in the last three years, particularly against my wife and my son’.

The melodramatic statement had been suggested by their Los Angeles agent. Netflix, he said, would pay more if they delivered hours of private videos shot in their most intimate moments. Meghan understood perfectly. She had been collecting that material since she met Harry, not least when he proposed to her.

For Harry, it was different. He was escaping what he later called ‘the constant harassment (online and off), intimidation and abuse that my wife and I have suffered at the hands of the tabloids’.[118] He didn’t like being the object of the media, he would tell a judge. He wanted privacy outside the spotlight. As he got off the plane in sunny California, Harry began to feel that he was now beyond anyone’s control. He had dumped his family, his constitutional obligations, the need for self-restraint, the care for self-control and the past.

By the end of the day, the Sussexes were settling into Tyler Perry’s eight-bedroom home in Beverly Ridge set in twenty-two acres. ‘For many reasons,’ said Meghan, ‘I’m glad to be home.’[119]

Meghan’s return was welcomed by her supporters – a coalition of feminists, Democrats, liberals and anti-monarchists. Peggy Drexler, a research psychologist sympathetic to Meghan, typified those who accepted Meghan’s claim that what she demanded most was total privacy: ‘They no longer wished to be trailed by the media, obsessed over, watched. Harry didn’t want to be constantly reminded of his mother’s tragic death every time he and Meghan were photographed; Meghan didn’t want to be tabloid fodder for what she wore, how she did her hair, where she was from or how much she did or didn’t enjoy the spotlight. They wanted to reach financial independence, live as regular people, raise their children in private.’[120] Like many sympathisers, Drexler was destined to be surprised.

Unconcerned about Harry’s promises in Sandringham not to financially exploit his family, Meghan ordered Archewell to be rebranded sussex.com with the coat of arms granted to her by the Queen. Their website was headed ‘The Office of Prince Harry and Meghan. The Duke and Duchess of Sussex.’ Harry would claim that Sussex was their family name, but he knew that was untrue – Archie’s birth certificate accurately recorded their family surname as Mountbatten-Windsor.[121] Archewell would need to raise $100 million to rank as an effective Hollywood foundation.

In London, Princess Anne predicted to a friend exactly what would follow. Meghan, she said, was gripped by ‘red carpet fever’. Nothing, it seemed, would deter her search for the spotlight.

Status was vital to the Sussexes. Harry would have expected a home fit for a prince. An agent offered them paradise in Montecito, near Santa Barbara and ninety miles north of Los Angeles. Known as the American Riviera because a mountain range cascades down to golden sands, Montecito was paradise for about 10,000 people seeking discretion inside plots surrounded by cypresses and cacti. The mix of actors, Hollywood producers, industrialists and TV celebrities was serviced by luxury shops, exorbitantly priced restaurants, elite beach clubs and hotels united by a common denominator: anyone asking the price couldn’t afford it. Detractors visiting from Britain offered another impression: ‘It’s Dorking with cacti cursed by a noisy trainline slicing through the middle.’

Set in 7.4 acres, the 18,000 square feet, nine-bedroom and fourteen-bathroom Mediterranean-style mansion on Rockbridge Road included a gym, tennis court, swimming pool, five-car garage and a two-bedroomed guest house. The Russian owner’s fire sale price of $14.65 million (£11 million), reduced from $34 million, was a bargain. The Sussexes paid Sergey Grishin $5 million cash and raised a $9.5 million mortgage, an arrangement that undermined Harry’s later assertion to Oprah Winfrey that the family arrived ‘without any money’ because his father ‘cut me off financially’. But to finance their staff, bodyguards and general living expenses, they would need an income of at least $3 million a year.

Meghan assumed that her title and mansion automatically enrolled her into California’s royalty. Like all her neighbours, she would naturally be a philanthropist and receive invitations to the big-ticket charity functions. Archie would go to a nursery majoring in emotional literacy, mindfulness and sustainability.[122] Harry would be welcomed at the Santa Barbara Polo and Racquet Club and train alongside his new Argentinian friend Nacho Figueras on a friendly billionaire’s polo pitch.

Yet their ‘journey to freedom’ took an unprecedented turn when, on the first morning after they moved into their new Montecito home, Meghan suffered a miscarriage. Harry publicly asserted that the cause was the Mail on Sunday’s publication of Meghan’s letter to her father,[123] and in fact she had subsequently taken legal action against them, accusing the newspaper of misuse of private information and infringement of copyright. Yet however sad the reality of losing a child, Harry’s is a fairly wild accusation given that about 20 per cent of pregnancies end in miscarriages and, perhaps of more relevance, Harry did not reveal that Meghan suffered from pre-eclampsia, a complication during her first pregnancy that causes high blood pressure and can lead to serious complications.[124] And, moreover, at the time of the miscarriage, Meghan anticipated outright victory in her litigation.[125]

Despite the splendour and the sunshine, Harry felt lonely in his mansion. After excluding some of his closest friends from his wedding dinner, there were few people he could call in Britain. Instead, he called Buckingham Palace. He wanted to speak to the Queen. Demanding apologies and money, the conversations became fractious. Insiders reported that Harry shouted and even swore. Irritated by Harry’s unreasonableness, the Queen suggested that Harry speak only with his father. In turn, Charles was frequently ‘unavailable’.

Any loneliness in California was mitigated by the urgency of settling into their new home. To work on his book and establish Archewell, the couple needed staff and a chief executive. The Sussexes persuaded James Holt, formerly employed in Kensington Palace for the Sussexes, to relocate to California. Previously, Holt had been a communications director for the Liberal Democrats and a special advisor to the deputy prime minister, Nick Clegg. His loyalty to the Sussexes was unquestionable.

* * *

Any doubts Harry may have harboured about his tell-all auto-biography evaporated due to his awareness that Charles had secretly completed his own book. His source was the Spencer family. Soon after Diana had given her interview to BBC TV’s Panorama in 1995, Charles resumed work on a manuscript he had started in the aftermath of Andrew Morton’s revelatory bestseller Diana: Her True Story, written with the Princess’s secret help in 1992. Sparing no feelings, Charles’s heartfelt criticism of his parents and his anger towards Diana was pure retaliation and therapeutic. He allowed Robert Fellowes, the Queen’s former private secretary, to read the completed manuscript before it was placed in a safe for a future generation. It is unlikely that Charles’s subsequent staff were made aware of the document. Harry’s book would counter that unknown bombshell.

Random House’s senior editor Ben Greenberg was tasked with finding a ghostwriter for Harry. From the outset, Meghan was involved in the selection. Those considered included award-winning writer Buzz Bissinger but finally 56-year-old John Moehringer was selected. The former New York Times journalist known as J.R. Moehringer had ghostwritten Andre Agassi’s prize-winning autobiography Open. Ghostwriting, Moehringer believed, was a ‘vital public service’.[126] Moehringer was also known for his autobiographical memoir The Tender Bar, describing life with his mother after she fled a violent relationship with his father when he was seven months old. A film based on the book had been directed by George Clooney.

Moehringer’s method and style was evident from The Tender Bar. The Chandleresque narrative flowed with the help of a flood of dramatic, unspoken thoughts. Channelled through Moehringer’s keyboard, the indiscriminate recollections of a vengeful prince would become a gripping narrative. Some would say that, considering the many similarities between The Tender Bar and Harry’s book, Moehringer transferred his own life into the Prince’s autobiography. Coincidentally, Shannon Welch, an editor at Penguin Random House, was Moehringer’s wife. The project would remain secret until March 2021, even within the publisher’s headquarters.

Covid restrictions prevented Harry, Moehringer and Meghan meeting personally. Introducing each other over Zoom, Moehringer recollected that they hit it off immediately.[127] Both men were ‘incredibly sensitive, tetchy and preoccupied by their feelings’,[128] and they bonded.

Moehringer’s brief, set by the editors in New York, was to ‘unflinchingly chronicle an intimate and honest human experience’.[129] Encouraged by Moehringer, Harry didn’t hesitate to use his ghostwriter as his therapist. Harry spoke about his wish to rebut ‘every lie published about me’ and to extract endless retractions from his enemies. In his own words, Harry was a man more sinned against than sinning, and his paranoia was matched by Meghan’s appetite for attention. Harry, she assured Moehringer, would be unflinchingly candid. No amount of self-exposure, she indicated, was off limits so long as the casualties – that was, their enemies – were less than incidental.[130]

In reality, Harry also wanted the spotlight – but on his terms. He spoke about loyalty but to many he was selling his soul and settling scores. Betraying his family appeared to give him satisfaction, rewarded not least by millions of dollars. Clearly envious that William was always the centre of attention, this move would focus the media more on Harry – and on him alone – partly to encourage public recognition that William was ‘jealous’ of his freedom in California.

Listening to Harry, Moehringer realised the Prince wanted not only to wage a personal vendetta but also to settle scores with Kate, Camilla, Charles and even the Queen. All of them, Harry complained, were out to get him. And yet, in writing his book, he would be invading their privacy, retelling intimate conversations, knowing that his family could not answer back. This was not just ‘a wounded lad’ pouring out his random thoughts, but clearly a man motivated by spite and determined to cause harm – and spread damage on a massive scale.

In their early conversations, Harry complained to Moehringer about media intrusion. Moehringer’s text would feed the same media which Harry so desperately loathed – and the very media he blamed for killing his mother. His pain became his punchlines. ‘I fully accept that writing a book is feeding the beast,’ Harry would later admit.[131] As Harry told his story in those early sessions, Moehringer might have wondered whether Harry was unable to control his emotions or understand what he was saying. But Moehringer’s commissioning editor knew the financial value of Harry’s outpourings.

During their early intensive Zoom discussions, Moehringer noted Harry’s sense of isolation. He sympathised with his gripe about being ‘unappreciated’, ‘a bit unloved’ and ‘a non-person within my own family . . . relegated to the hinterlands’. Those simple sentiments were easy to translate. Picking up on his self-pity, Harry’s descriptions of excess drinking, drug-taking and riotous nightclubbing with named friends – especially his close friends Guy Pelly, Tommy Inskip and other Etonians – were easy to encapsulate in Harry’s confession that ‘perhaps I was the one with brain damage’.[132]

Moehringer described how the book would give Harry an identity. Moehringer believed in deep emotions – not just those stemming from Harry’s relationship with Charles and William, but around losing his mother when young. Moehringer had also lost his mother. ‘You’re the air in someone else’s trumpet,’ Moehringer said about the art of ghostwriting, capturing his subject’s voice.[133] That interpretation appealed to Harry.

The editors in New York began to suspect that Harry did not realise how Moehringer’s vision of the book was fundamentally different from his own. Harry’s purpose was to justify his decision to leave his family and to expose the British media as the criminals responsible for his mother’s murder and a cause of his misery. Moehringer’s concept, agreed by his editor in New York, was to portray Harry as a bird trapped in a cage, a boy struggling to conquer his personal demons amid a dysfunctional family. Hearing from both sides about their remote conversations, one New York editor would come to believe that neither man properly understood the other. Harry expected total obedience from a paid employee. Other than when he had been in the army, he was unaccustomed to anyone failing to do what he expected. But Moehringer was his own man, unwilling to compromise on pursuing what he conceived the story to be. Physically separated from Harry, the writer couldn’t walk along the beach with the Prince, chewing the cud and properly grasping the excesses and constraints of growing up as an heir to the British throne.

During those early stages, the editors in Manhattan believed that the differences would get ironed out. Or not, and that didn’t matter. Penguin Random House had landed a big fish and Moehringer would deliver a blockbuster script. He was paid to look for sensational headlines, not to protect Harry from self-destruction.

And Harry was seemingly fixated by his penis. The royal genitalia, the writer knew, would grab readers’ attention. The word ‘penis’ would be mentioned eight times in the published book and ‘todger’ – Harry’s frozen penis – six times. Frostbitten during a trip in the Arctic, Harry delivered the priceless detail that the cure – Elizabeth Arden Eight Hour Cream – prompted his ‘memory’ that Diana used the same cream on her lips: ‘The moment I opened it, the smell transported me through time.’ In a subsequent trip to the Antarctic, he was given ‘a bespoke cock cushion’ to protect himself.[134]

Harry was also forthcoming about the loss of his virginity in 2001 at the age of sixteen on a ‘grassy field’ behind the Vine Tree Inn in Norton, Wiltshire. In Moehringer’s prose, Harry’s simple description of sex with a local nineteen-year-old stable girl he had known for years was translated as ‘an older woman’ who treated him ‘like a young stallion’ during a ‘five minutes wham-bam’. She then ‘smacked my rump and sent me off to graze’. Easily identified by Harry’s friends at the time, forty-year-old Sasha Walpole would be embarrassed by the revelation.[135] But Harry did not seemingly consider it important that Walpole might resent being outed after twenty-one years despite saying, ‘Everyone has a right to privacy,’ on BBC TV in 2016.

Harry was similarly indiscreet about Pat, a matron at Ludgrove, his prep school. To win laughs from his friends, Harry led the torment of the woman who suffered chronic pain as she slowly struggled down the school’s stairs. In Moehringer’s manuscript, Harry sought to ‘make the miserable Pat bust a gut’,[136] the cruelty to a defenceless woman in this instance apparently not troubling to Harry at all.

Raw hatred for Charles’s wife Camilla clearly influenced Harry’s animosity towards his father. He called Camilla ‘a wicked stepmother’ and ‘dangerous’. In the years previously, he had declared that he ‘loved her to bits’, although he hoped that Charles would not marry her despite her making his father ‘happy’.[137] Underlying his ire was a conviction that without Camilla, Diana would still be alive and married to Charles. Misunderstanding both his mother and her marriage, he poured out to Moehringer his passion to punish Camilla and Charles for Diana’s death. And it had all started, he mistakenly pinpointed, in the summer of 1996 after Charles employed the accomplished publicist Mark Bolland to improve Camilla’s image.[138] Over the following years, Harry protested, Camilla was ‘sacrificing’ him on ‘her personal PR altar’ to develop her ‘campaign directed towards marriage and, with time, the Crown’.[139] Reading those outpourings, the New York editors seemingly did not suggest to Moehringer that he question Harry about his double standards: he hated criticism of Meghan but wilfully attacked Charles, Camilla, Kate and William.

One bombshell followed after another. The book’s editors were delighted by Harry’s confessions about taking drugs. Starting with cannabis at Eton, he admitted taking a series of increasingly dangerous substances, including cocaine, ketamine, magic mushrooms, ayahuasca and Nepalese hashish Temple Balls. In the past, Harry had accused the media of reporting lies about his drug habits. Now he admitted that the newspapers had reported the truth. Teasing the details out of Harry was not a problem. The Prince was keen to reveal that ‘marijuana really did help me’; cocaine ‘did nothing’ except make him feel part of a group; and after swallowing magic mushrooms at a party in 2016 in the home of friends of the actress Courteney Cox, he hallucinated in a bathroom, imagining a pedal bin as a human. He was seeking relief, he said, from ‘chaos’, grief and the trauma of losing his mother. ‘For me, they cleared the windscreen, the removal of life’s filters . . . I would say it was one of the fundamental parts of my life that changed me and helped me with the traumas and the pains of the past.’

His editors evidently did not caution Harry that ‘bragging and encouraging illegal drug use’ and detailing his mental illness could be ridiculed. No one in New York questioned whether his petulance undermined the monarchy and even himself as a serious personality. Not least because they were republicans focused on a publishing sensation. Penguin Random House had bought a sure-fire global blockbuster selling secrets for millions of dollars: sex, drugs and astonishing revelations about the Royal Family.

CHAPTER 10

Netflix

The Sussexes’ ducks were falling into a row.

At the height of the Covid lockdown, the streaming giant Netflix’s income soared as millions of people were confined to their homes and bought subscriptions. Hungry for new programmes, Brandon Riegg, Netflix’s head of content, and his successor Ted Sarandos (and Montecito neighbour), judged the Sussexes’ offer to tell all in an eponymous documentary to be a certain hit. The Sussexes were guaranteed to attract record audiences. To secure the deal, Sarandos agreed that the Sussexes would be contracted to make five series over five years. The surprise was Harry’s readiness to partner with Netflix, the producer of The Crown, the sensational TV series which unashamedly distorted the truth about the Royal Family – a version of his own family story that Harry said he preferred to his own.[140]

Netflix would not get an exclusive for the first blockbuster series, though. Meghan insisted on honouring the agreement she had made in London to first appear on Oprah Winfrey’s show. With one year between the Oprah Winfrey interview and Netflix series, there would be ample new material. As rumours spread that the Netflix deal could be worth $100 million, some were dismayed. ‘They’re star fuckers,’ moaned a disgruntled programme maker who failed to secure a Netflix contract during that flush era.[141]

Brand Meghan was being forged. The Duchess, a warrior for social justice, slotted together the jigsaw: compassion, victimhood, racism, feminism, motherhood and truth. Each piece illustrated Meghan’s ‘suffering’ – and her mission.[142]

In the run-up to the 2020 presidential election, the Sussexes were keen to play a part. With Donald Trump’s low poll ratings suggesting defeat, both openly supported Joe Biden against Trump. In particular, they highlighted the Biden administration’s removal of gender identity from official statements. Making the terms mother, father, daughter and brother unacceptable was part of Biden’s policy to supersede biological sex. By sharing those opinions the Sussexes were welcomed by the wealthy liberal elite – and rewarded by Meghan’s well-publicised virtual meeting with Gavin Newsom, California’s Democrat governor.[143]

Celebrating their inclusion on the list of Time magazine’s 100 most influential people on the planet, the couple broadcast to Americans from their Montecito garden. Meghan urged her audience to ‘build communities of compassion’ and spoke about ‘the most important election of our lifetime’. In his own clear anti-Trump appeal, Harry was emphatic: ‘As we approach this November, it’s vital we reject hate speech, misinformation and online negativity.’

On reflection, Harry’s snubbing of Ivanka Trump during her visit to Buckingham Palace with her father in December 2019 had been clearly inspired by Meghan. Her apparent refusal to appear with Harry at the state dinner in Buckingham Palace for Trump irritated the president. ‘I am not a fan of hers,’ said Trump about Meghan. ‘I wish a lot of luck to Harry because he’s going to need it.’[144]

* * *

Ever since she wrote an article for Elle magazine in 2015, Meghan had spoken as the victim of racism. Although she provided no specific evidence of suffering any personal disadvantage during her life, she explained that after returning from Britain, she realised that America’s race conflict was ‘devastating’. She added, ‘It was so sad to see where our country was.’[145]

The murder of George Floyd in Minneapolis on 25th May 2020 paradoxically provided a historic benchmark for Meghan. The Black Lives Matter (BLM) movement, Meghan said, was ‘a beautiful thing’. Across America, ‘the peaceful protests . . . people were actually owning their own role. It shifted from sadness to a feeling of absolute inspiration because I can see the tide is turning.’[146] She adopted BLM’s arguments about white privilege and Harry echoed her opinions. Although its critics labelled the Black Lives Matter movement as one inspired by Marxism to foment social discontent, Harry shared her view about the white man’s guilt. Britain and its institutions, said Harry in an interview from Montecito, suffered from ‘endemic structural racism’.[147] He criticised a ‘world created by white people for white people’. White society, he believed, produced ‘bias’ with an ‘effect on young people of colour’. White Britons, Harry said, needed to understand people ‘of a different coloured skin’.[148] Influenced by Meghan’s experience, he added, ‘You know when you go into a shop with your children and you see only white dolls, do you even think: “That’s weird, there’s not a black doll there?” ’[149]

The Sussexes muted their overt criticism after Black Lives Matter supporters proposed that presidents George Washington, Thomas Jefferson and Abraham Lincoln be ‘cancelled’ because they had owned slaves. That was followed by BLM’s demand for hundreds of classic literature books to be banned as racist. But the seeds had been sown. As she pondered her appearance with Oprah, Meghan crafted her lines to present her experience of racism on the global platform and she finalised the appointments for her producers and a director for the Netflix programming she and Harry were intending to create.

Yet though their press release announcing the Netflix deal was loaded with rhetoric, Meghan lacked the necessary skills to produce a documentary series and to articulate her vision on a wider scale. The series, she said, would be ‘our love story’. Professionals who would later work with Meghan understood her limitations. Meghan had ‘this naïveté and hopefulness about what’s possible in terms of storytelling’.[150]

Meghan’s limitations had also become apparent in The Bench, an illustrated children’s book she had written. Damned by critics as leaden, others would spot its stark similarity to The Boy and the Bench, a book published in 2018. Over the years, Meghan would often be accused of copying others. Her famous website, The Tig, had been unashamedly based on the success of established influencers. It was noted that she struggled to deliver original ideas.

Many actors have a common trait. Their talent is to look brilliant by masterfully delivering words composed by writers. Their weakness can be exposed by an inability to write their own scripts. Like most ambitious actors, Meghan could not admit to any flaws or mistaken judgements. Besides dogged persistence, her strength was self-belief. She now famously knew what she did and did not like, and what she would and wouldn’t put up with. It appeared that all the self-doubts she had harboured before being cast in Suits had disappeared once she was married. The fawning she had commanded at Kensington Palace – by simply imitating Harry – was richly deserved.

Harry watched from the sidelines as his wife selected the four producers for the series. He did not question why all four were women. Giona Jefferson, one producer, was a black American who described herself as ‘an accomplished interdisciplinary thinker and strategic decision-maker’.

Growing up in Hollywood, Meghan understood the importance of appointing the right director. Her final choice, Garrett Bradley, was the first black woman to win a director’s award at the Sundance Film Festival. Black American women, Bradley had said, were the focal point of her documentaries. ‘I think of myself as a facilitator,’ she explained. ‘How can their experiences open our eyes?’ Meghan was attracted by Bradley ‘trying to create a more just and transparent and loving world’. She also liked Bradley speaking about entering her subject’s ‘head space’ and promoting the ‘resilience of women’. Meghan shared the sentiment of Bradley’s homily: ‘Ultimately, what everybody needs in life in order to feel loved is to be understood, to feel heard.’[151]

Particularly appealing to Meghan was Bradley’s inclination to prioritise race, class and social justice. In turn, the Sussexes’ widely publicised attitude to racism would naturally have stoked Bradley’s excitement. By focusing on Meghan’s victimhood in Britain, the audience would be able to relate to the Sussexes’ experience.

Those thoughts aligned with Meghan’s own homily about ‘being kind to yourself’.[152] Meghan was, however, either unaware or naive about Bradley’s description of her film-making technique: ‘It was really important for me not to go into the project with an agenda or even an opinion.’ As a purist documentary maker, Bradley hated disciplined filming. Expecting unlimited access to the Sussexes’ home, including their bedroom and bathroom, Bradley intended to explore the Sussexes’ intimate ‘space’. ‘My process,’ she explained, ‘is about listening to people and letting the images come to my mind; those images then become the script and then they perform them.’ Favouring long, lingering shoots, she would craft her documentary only after viewing hundreds of hours of constant filming.

Allowing Bradley’s cameras to roll without control to reveal the Sussexes’ ‘universal truths’ was precisely the opposite of Meghan’s plan. In Meghan’s mind, everything should be authentically controlled. In order to showcase her inspirational life without a hair out of place, Bradley’s cameras could not be allowed unscripted freedom. Especially not in her bedroom and bathroom.

Few realised that Meghan’s hairstylist and make-up artist needed over two hours every day before she could appear in public. At that time, no outsider could be allowed to witness her staring at the mirror unmade up.‘Spontaneous truths’ about ‘our love story’ had to be firmly scripted and then carefully edited. The mask could never slip.

Filming started in autumn 2020. Within weeks, Bradley was told to stop. All her videos would be viewed and ditched as ‘chaotic’.[153] Meghan began searching for another woman she could trust. In a now familiar pattern, procrastination and indecision were followed by delays.

CHAPTER 11

‘My Truth’

Though still filled with confidence at the end of 2020, Harry and Meghan were preoccupied with their campaign against the tabloids. Their lawyer, David Sherborne, reported good progress. Harry’s claims against the Mirror and the Sun were heading towards a trial, and he predicted that Meghan would win her case against the Mail on Sunday.

In the Sussexes’ bid to target the journalists responsible for intruding into their privacy and exploiting them ‘as currency for an economy of click-bait and distortion’, they accused Jason Knauf and other Palace employees of leaving Meghan ‘unprotected’ while being forced to endure silently ‘hundreds of thousands of inaccurate articles’. As honourable people, the Sussexes had been ‘completely pulled apart for no good reason’ other than to earn profits. The battle lines were drawn. The contest was between the Sussexes’ ‘truth’ and what others would call ‘irrefutable facts’.

The veracity of the Sussexes’ version of events in the Palace had been corroborated by the publication in August 2020 of Omid Scobie’s book Finding Freedom. To the Sussexes’ delight, Scobie laid out in the starkest terms how Meghan was the victim of sexist and racist Palace courtiers who snidely referred to ‘Harry’s showgirl’. Royal aides were described in Harry’s words as ‘vipers’; William was criticised for provoking a rift with Harry; Thomas Markle was portrayed as a bankrupt, unloving and deceitful father who deliberately failed to arrive at the wedding; and Kate was blamed for snubbing Meghan.

In his book, Scobie thanked the Sussexes and ‘those closest to the couple’ for their help.[154] Since the book was written with that co-operation, few doubted that Scobie reflected the Sussexes’ beliefs. According to the Sussexes’ rules of privacy, media criticism of themselves was unacceptable. But many saw the hypocrisy that apparently they could assist Scobie to criticise the Royal Family.

Scobie’s expressions of gratitude embarrassed the Sussexes. In her legal case against the Mail on Sunday that concluded in 2021, Meghan denied helping Scobie. ‘They did not collaborate with the authors on the book,’ stated Jenny Afia, Meghan’s solicitor, ‘or give authority to anyone to speak to the authors on her behalf.’ Meghan herself described the Mail on Sunday’s allegations that she had helped Scobie as ‘false’, ‘fantastical’ and ‘a conspiracy theory’.[155] She claimed not to know how much help the authors got from her staff[156] and denied being given the opportunity to make changes or fact-check.[157] Meghan’s ‘truth’ was supported by Scobie’s own signed legal statement: ‘Any suggestion that the Duke and Duchess collaborated on the book is false.’[158]

Scobie must have known that wasn’t accurate. He had, after all, been briefed for two hours by Jason Knauf, who read from a detailed memorandum supplied by Meghan. Scobie had also, with Meghan’s approval, been introduced to her friends by the Palace publicist Sara Latham and Keleigh Thomas Morgan.

Meghan also forcefully denied telling any American girlfriends about her letter to her father which featured in People magazine in 2019. ‘It was not me and had nothing to do with me,’ she said. But Meghan knew that she had told two girlfriends about the letter’s contents.[159] These inaccurate statements were a gamble. Ever since she had written her loosely accurate résumé of her career aged twenty-four to promote her career in Hollywood,[160] she had made incorrect assertions about her childhood, parents and career. But she would call it ‘my truth’.

To avoid disclosing her co-operation with Scobie and the text messages to her American girlfriends, Meghan’s lawyers hoped that they could persuade the judges that a trial was unnecessary. She owned the copyright to her own letter, they argued, and there was no public interest in denying her total privacy. She should be granted, claimed her lawyers, a summary judgement – punishment for Britain’s unaccountable media for printing ‘hundreds of thousands of inaccurate articles about her’, knowing they were ‘distorted, false, or invasive beyond reason’.[161]

Judges’ decisions in London’s High Court trials for privacy had become unpredictable. More so if a member of the Royal Family was the claimant. But Meghan’s lawyers were confident that English judges would side with the Royal Family against the tabloids.[162] Victory was certain, advised Keith Schilling’s firm, not least because of the Sussexes’ cast-iron denial of helping any journalist or magazine. Especially Scobie.

That certainty ought to have collapsed after four of Meghan’s aides in Kensington Palace offered to give evidence about Meghan’s conduct. In particular, Jason Knauf and Sara Latham said they knew about the background to the briefing of Scobie and how Meghan’s letter to her father was created with their help.Their irrefutable truth did not persuade Mark Warby, the trial judge. Being royal, declared the judge, did not make ‘one’ public property. Meghan’s relationship with her father was a private matter and all the evidence contradicting Meghan’s statement was worthless. Warby declared that Meghan had won her case without a trial. Meghan escaped scrutiny and the world was denied the truth.

In Montecito, the Sussexes celebrated. ‘We have all won,’ said Meghan. ‘You cannot take somebody’s privacy and exploit it,’ she added. ‘I share the victory with each of you – because we all deserve justice and the truth, and we all deserve better.’ Her treatment by the media, she said, was ‘illegal and dehumanising’. The public, she insisted, was entitled to ‘reliable, fact-checked, high-quality news’.[163] Posing as a champion of media freedom, Meghan went on: ‘When power is enjoyed without responsibility, the trust we all place in this much-needed industry is degraded.’[164] Harry’s self-confidence about defeating the tabloids soared, confirming his belief that British judges could be relied upon to find in his favour.

* * *

In July 2021, Rick Genow, Meghan’s Beverly Hills lawyer, completed the registration of a slew of companies in California and Delaware for the Sussexes. Multiple registrations seemed likely to thwart any meaningful enquiries into the Sussexes’ finances as they embarked on a series of ventures. In anticipation of the Netflix series, book publications and other commercial ventures, Meghan chose meaningful names including, Peca Publishing, Orinoco Publishing, Cobblestone Lane, Baobab Holdings, Bridgement, Hampshire, Riversoul Productions, Cloverdale Inc and Nemawashi Holdings.

The money-spinner was the Netflix series. During her search for a new director, Meghan alighted on Liz Garbus. Aged fifty-one, Garbus had produced an anti-media documentary called Fourth Estate and was currently completing two documentaries for Apple TV about black actors’ achievements. Meghan had first met Garbus while pitching to Netflix an animated children’s series based on a character called Pearl, the historical story of a twelve-year-old girl travelling through time to meet important women. Megan Casey, Netflix’s director of original animation, described the Duchess’s project as, ‘an exciting tale that weaves together fantasy and history. Pearl focuses on a young girl who learns to step into her own power when she embarks on a heroic adventure and meets important women from history along the way.’

News reports of Meghan’s project prompted lawyers representing author Mel Elliott – who had written a strikingly similar series of three bestselling Pearl Power books between 2014 and 2016 – to write to Meghan in July 2021: ‘The similarities between your proposed animation series and my client’s work appear to be too many and too striking to be mere coincidence.’ Not having received a reply, her lawyers wrote again in February 2022. Again, there was no reply. The series was eventually cancelled in May 2022. The excuse issued by Netflix was that Meghan’s pitch failed to tell a visual story.[165]

The good news was that Liz Garbus had agreed to make the Netflix series. Meghan proposed that beside their love story, the series would also feature the Sussexes’ fractured relationship with the Queen and her family, their hatred for the media and their departure from Britain. ‘Viewers’, Garbus would say, ‘came for the love story, or the hot gossip [and] they were able to stay for other provocative and important stuff, [such as] the history of colonialism.’[166] In Meghan’s words, Garbus ‘connected the dots to larger historical issues’ including racism, Empire and how Britain’s monarchy was linked to white supremacy.

Harry was by now apparently fully converted to Meghan’s gospel that the Royal Family was racist. His family’s prejudice, he believed, was shared by all the courtiers and especially the women assigned to help Meghan in Kensington Palace, and had fed the hostility that forced their flight to California. Naturally, the tabloids were the cheerleaders of their persecution, reflecting Britain’s supposed racism. The media, Meghan said, were stirring up hatred with lies ‘to find a way to destroy me’. The Sussexes’ response was to attack the Royal Family.[167]

That scenario was the foundation for the Sussexes’ discussions with the producers of the Oprah with Meghan and Harry television special, and with Oprah herself. Those who had smeared Meghan’s reputation in London about the pre-wedding arguments and her bullying the staff were in her sights for her first interview since leaving Britain. ‘Life is about telling stories, right?’ said Meghan. ‘Telling stories through a truthful lens.’[168]

During their conversations, Oprah Winfrey’s team had no doubts about Meghan’s undisguised hatred of the Royal Family for denying her true destiny. The House of Windsor, she believed, was too small for her greatness. They inhabited a world that was crumbling, even dead, but not yet buried. Their discomfort would give her great pleasure.

The interview, Meghan knew, was a watershed. Appreciating the theatrical debut, her appearance with the American icon guaranteed her everlasting global celebrity. To make the Oprah Winfrey interview interesting to an international audience, she needed to create a narrative – a unique story – distinguished by sensational revelations. Over the past year, she had pondered about her ‘truth’ – what to exaggerate and what to labour. To please her fans, especially in America, her palpable anger and desire to shame the Royal Family would be disguised behind a serene face, alternately smiling and hurt.

As a self-styled progressive feminist, Meghan would have known that the sensitive touchpoints were bullying and racism. In the culture born in California, the self-declared victims were rarely doubted. Those who questioned the victim’s assertions as unproven allegations were damned. The peak of sensitivity was any revelation of attempted suicide. Few dared to doubt those confessions. Just as she had been urged by the Palace to remain silent – ‘Never complain, never explain’ was their motto – the Palace would not contest her truth after the broadcast.

On Tuesday 16th February 2021, Meghan sat in a sunlit Santa Barbara garden with Oprah Winfrey. With an actor’s ability to remember her lines, Meghan had rehearsed her replies and, most importantly, the appropriate movement of her hands, head and even eyes as she chose to speak in the dramatic whisper of a damaged angel. Presenting herself as a helpless innocent when she got engaged, she would deliver a performance worthy of Hollywood. Her make-up had taken nearly three hours to complete.

Of her successive accusations against the Royal Family, the most damaging was her weaponisation of race. Her unborn son, she whispered, was to be denied protection and a title as prince. ‘Concerns,’ she said ‘and conversations about how dark his skin might be when he’s born.’ Meghan could not be clearer. The Royal Family had denied the unborn Archie a title and protection because his mother was not white: the first member of colour in this family not to be titled in the same way that other grandchildren would be.

Oprah Winfrey asked, ‘They were concerned that if he were too brown, that would be a problem?’

Meghan replied, ‘If that’s the assumption you are making, I think that feels like a pretty safe one.’

Oprah: ‘What? Who is having that conversation with you?’

Meghan: ‘There were several conversations about it which took place in those months when I was pregnant.’ Meghan refused to identify the culprit: ‘I think that would be very damaging to them.’

For Oprah Winfrey, Meghan was clearly a martyr, a symbol of the revolution for social justice. Together they were victims who had become survivors in their self-created ‘safe harbour’. What Meghan would also call a ‘modern fairytale’.

Harry was introduced into the edited interview in the last third of the broadcast. He felt obliged to appear in the programme. Faced with a choice of ‘life and death’ where he was abandoned without protection to be ‘destroyed’ at the mercy of would-be murderers anxious to kill him and his family, he believed ‘being silent wasn’t working. We felt we had no choice . . . My wife and I were in peril.’ Telling their truth on American TV was, Harry said, no different than Palace spokesmen ‘planting stories’ and the Palace’s co-operation with many authors of books, especially Charles’s interviews with Jonathan Dimbleby for his ‘crypto-autobiography’ in 1994.[169] Oprah Winfrey did not pay for the interview but shortly afterwards, Harry would receive over $500,000 for a keynote speech to J.P.Morgan bankers in Miami.[170]

With stark honesty, or perhaps thoughtlessly, Harry contradicted Meghan’s description of his family’s racism. There was only one conversation about a future child, he said, ‘right at the beginning’ of their relationship, ‘before we even got married’. Meghan was not present, he said. There was no mention of titles or protection. The conversation was about, ‘What will the kids look like? At the time, it was awkward. I was a bit shocked.’ He would never, he said, identify the family members.

In fact, the conversation was over tea at Clarence House with Charles and Camilla. Harry had been gushing about finding the love of his life. After describing his girlfriend’s background, all three laughed about what their child might look like. Oprah Winfrey failed – or refused – to highlight the fundamental discrepancies between Meghan’s version and Harry’s.

Meghan’s inaccuracies were not unfortunate errors. Clearly well rehearsed for the interview, she netted her prize. Across the globe, the headlines called the Royal Family ‘racist’. The second headline was about Meghan’s suicidal feelings during her pregnancy in January 2019. The cause, she told Oprah Winfrey, was ‘bullying and abuse’ on social media. ‘I just didn’t want to be alive any more.’[171] Even worse, she claimed, she was not believed or protected by Palace officials.

‘I went to the institution,’ Meghan told Oprah Winfrey, referring to Palace officials, ‘and I said that I needed to go somewhere to get help. I said that “I’ve never felt this way before, and I need to go somewhere,” and I was told that I couldn’t, that it wouldn’t be good for the institution.’ Pressed to identify that ‘most senior’ person, Meghan replied, ‘I went to human resources and I said, “I just really – I need help.” Because in my old job, there was a union and they would protect me. And I remember this conversation like it was yesterday.’[172]

After the Oprah Winfrey interview, Meghan offered another version of the events following Harry finding his wife sobbing in Kensington Palace. Harry, she said in one of her podcasts, had ‘found a referral for me to call’. The psychiatrist, she continued, answered her call while standing at a supermarket checkout.[173] The episode was called, ‘Crazy or hysterical, nuts, insane, out of your mind, completely irrational.’ One year later, Meghan would add more detail: ‘I could hear the little beep-beep, and I was like, Hi, and I’m introducing myself and she’s literally going, “Wait, Sorry. I’m just . . . Who is this?” Um, and I’m saying I need help. And she could hear the dire state that I was in.’[174] Meghan failed to disclose what happened thereafter.

No one who had seen Meghan on that January evening at the Royal Albert Hall with Harry could have imagined that just hours earlier she was seriously contemplating suicide. Either way, as an actor, she knew how to perform.

In the aftermath, some doubted Meghan’s near-suicide. Robustly she replied, ‘I haven’t really scraped the surface of my experience . . . I would never want someone else to be making those sorts of plans. And I would never want someone else to not be believed.’[175] She added, ‘I don’t want anyone to feel alone.’[176]

However, Meghan’s previous female advisors in Kensington Palace, alias ‘the Sussex Survivors Club’, judged their employer to be a ‘narcissistic sociopath’.[177] More proof, they claimed, was Meghan’s assertion to Oprah Winfrey that the marriage service in Windsor was a fraud. The couple, she said, had been married days earlier in a private ceremony by the Archbishop of Canterbury. Indeed, eyewitnesses had seen the Archbishop in the garden outside Nottingham Cottage with Meghan and Harry. Dogs were barking near the huddle during what Meghan knew was – at her request – a short blessing, but it was not a marriage ceremony.

One week before the Oprah Winfrey programme was broadcast, the Palace discovered the contents from a trusted source at ITV in London. The station had bought the rights from CBS. The Palace decided to retaliate first. On 3rd March 2021, four days before the broadcast, Prince William apparently authorised the leaking of the Knauf memorandum about Meghan’s alleged bullying of her staff to The Times. The newspaper revealed that Meghan’s behaviour had driven two personal assistants to resign and a third, suffering a loss of self-confidence, to say, ‘I can’t stop shaking.’ None of those involved were identified. All claimed they had been operating in a ‘climate of fear’ where employees were routinely ‘humiliated’ by both Meghan and Harry in front of their peers and repeatedly subjected to ‘unreasonable demands’. One aide told The Times, it felt ‘more like emotional cruelty and manipulation, which I guess could also be called bullying’.[178]

In the furore that followed The Times’s revelations, Buckingham Palace was accused by Meghan’s supporters of ‘shameless, obscene, racist-inspired malice’ against an innocent woman whose ‘kindness, goodwill runs in her bones’.[179]

On the eve of the broadcast, Meghan was in bed in Montecito crying. Not because she felt any remorse for her shattering allegations against the Royal Family, but because The Firm had orchestrated a ‘smear’ about her alleged bullying. Only William’s senior staff would have possessed Knauf’s memorandum to pass to The Times.

‘It was a great mistake and a great shame that Knauf’s complaint was leaked,’ a senior Buckingham Palace official would later say. ‘Leaking it to The Times gave it credibility. It caused so many problems.’[180] Buckingham Palace did not approve of the tactics chosen by William in Kensington Palace.

The leak, Meghan believed, vindicated her telling Oprah Winfrey that the Palace could not expect them to ‘be silent if there is an active role that The Firm is playing in perpetuating falsehoods about us’. Her next sound bite sounded rehearsed: ‘They were willing to lie to protect other members of the family. They weren’t willing to tell the truth to protect me and my husband.’ And, as if on cue, she quietly brushed aside some tears.[181] She had been brave. She stood on the right side.

Harry naturally supported his wife, despite earlier insisting that she never read anything about herself on the internet. ‘I held her,’ said Harry. ‘We talked, she cried and cried and cried.’[182]

As she cried, Meghan probably failed to recall her own homily: ‘If you live knowing the truth, regardless of what anyone says, you’ll be able to go to sleep with a clear conscience.’ [183]

Certain they had spoken the ‘truth in the most compassionate way possible’ to Oprah, Harry nevertheless spoke about leaving ‘an opening for reconciliation and healing’. That sentiment was grasped by a Buckingham Palace spokesman. On Saturday night, he predicted that the interview would be a quickly forgotten sideshow – ‘lost in the mists of time’. The Palace did not understand Harry’s terms for reconciliation. Drawn from his therapist handbook, he meant: ‘We collectively can heal together if we share our stories.’[184] Few in the Palace comprehended that kind of language.

The interview, CBS announced, was watched by 49 million people. The Sussexes’ courage was welcomed by President Biden, Hillary Clinton and the Obamas. The Sussexes’ critics were vitriolic. The interview was dubbed ‘a very Californian exercise in grievance’, a ‘tedious, narcissistic wallow’ and ‘a one-sided PR effort’.[185]

The most trenchant allegation about the Sussexes’ dishonesty referred to one of their original explanations for their flight from Britain – their demand for privacy. In Meghan’s definition, it transpired that privacy meant her unquestioned freedom to say what she liked, while criticism of her was unacceptable.

After the broadcast, the Palace realised its misjudgement. Reeling from the worldwide condemnation of the racist royals, the best the Palace could reply was the Queen’s comment that ‘recollections may vary’.[186]

Days later, Charles wrote to Meghan expressing his disappointment that the Sussexes had given the interview and denying his family’s racism. In reply, Meghan identified the person who made the racist comment. Her text has never been published but many did presume Charles personally of being the culprit. Two years later, while disclosing that private exchange, Meghan’s spokeswoman suggested that she had in fact referred to ‘unconscious bias’, a clearly intentional dilution of her accusations of racism to Oprah Winfrey.[187]

Amid the tumult, the Sussexes’ spokesman announced that the interview would be the ‘last word’’ about their rift with the Royal Family. Having ‘needed to have their say’, they now considered the matter closed and wanted to ‘move on’.[188] Though even while making that announcement, the spokesman knew that, fresh from demolishing the Royal Family with Oprah Winfrey, the Sussexes were preparing Netflix’s six-part series.

CHAPTER 12

‘The Me You Can’t See’

Liz Garbus picked her filming crew carefully. Each prospective technician and production assistant was vetted to ascertain that they were not anti-Sussex. After scrutinising their social media posts, each was questioned about loyalty and discretion. Those selected in November 2021 were required to sign a draconian non-disclosure agreement (NDA). Each member of the four-man filming crew was ordered never to speak to the Sussexes unless they were directly addressed by the couple. Under no circumstances were they to refer to them by their names. In internal documents they were called H and M. In any rare personal contact, Meghan was to be addressed as ‘Ma’am’ and Harry as ‘Sir’. Filming was to start in December.

Garbus recorded her interviews in a rented house over ten days, each session lasting eight hours. To make the interviews more intimate, the camera crew was occasionally concealed behind black fabric screens. Not only to create a better atmosphere, but also so that the crew could not see – except on the monitors – the relationship between Garbus and the Sussexes. No Archewell employee came on to the set.

To prevent any leaks about disagreements and retakes, Garbus discussed each question with the Sussexes before entering the room. Carefully, the Sussexes never commented in front of the crew during or after a session about the interviews. Those sensitive conversations were delayed until they had returned to the production area and could not be overheard. There, Archewell’s executive producer Ben Browning, after watching it ‘live’ on a monitor, gave his judgement. No hint of displeasure seeped from his room. When he or the Sussexes decided that a question should be reshot, their decision would not be flagged in front of the crew or any other members of the production team. Everything was agreed in private. Inevitably, the crew identified some reshoots, especially the emotional scenes. ‘Garbus left it to Meghan to know how to perform spontaneously at the required moment,’ recalled a member of the crew. Carefully, Garbus never hinted that Meghan’s on-camera suffering was staged.

By then, the Sussexes had handed Garbus over twenty hours of video filmed by them and their staff. Among the rushes was the morning after Meghan and Harry’s splashy interview with Oprah in March 2021. The grainy, unlit sequence showed the couple sitting side by side at their home when Meghan exclaimed: ‘Beyoncé’s just texted!’

Harry pulled a mock-surprised face and theatrically threw his hands up.

‘Shut up,’ said Meghan.

‘Just checking in, just casual,’ replied Harry.

Meghan laughed: ‘I still can’t believe she knows who I am. She said she wants me to feel safe and protected.’ Harry nodded.

Next, Meghan delivered a perfect sound bite: ‘She admires and respects my bravery and vulnerability and says I was selected to break generational curses that need to be healed.’

If that exchange smelt of re-enactment, the call Meghan took from Tyler Perry seemed even less authentic than what followed.

Harry interrupted Meghan’s discussion about the Queen’s ‘recollections may vary’ statement. Sticking his mobile in front of Meghan’s face, she allegedly read a text from William.

‘Wow!’ Meghan said.

‘I wish I knew what to do,’ Harry sighed, appearing distressed.

‘I know,’ Meghan replied – and they theatrically embrace. Pause, and then Meghan suggests, ‘Let’s take a breather, get some air and then decide.’ Cut!

* * *

In parallel, Harry was deeply engaged with Moehringer for his autobiography. Shared among an increasing number of Random House’s editors, Moehringer’s draft chapters reflected Harry’s mental health challenges and vitriolic recriminations about his family. In their discussions, some experienced editors spotted that Moehringer seemed to be unaware of Harry’s hypocrisy. Playing the eternal victim, he said he wanted an ordinary life but at the same time demanded all the privileges of royalty. Angry that he was the ‘spare’, the self-confessed delinquent without a purpose in life was venting his fury that nearly every member of his family failed to appreciate his special needs. Moehringer’s drafts recorded the one-sided complaint of appalling treatment. Eager to serve his client, Moehringer embellished the lucrative soap opera. After all, the ghostwriter was a republican who cared ‘less than nothing’[189] for a thousand years of British history. Harry’s failure to understand the uncompromising nature of the British constitution was irrelevant to the ghostwriter. Even though Harry had said, ‘Many of my family aren’t able to work and live together,’[190] Moehringer inserted no reflective comment when voicing Harry’s need for a family and not a monarchy.

All those accusations had been recorded before Prince Philip died on 9th April 2021. Although his grandfather’s death had been anticipated, family sentiments had not deterred Harry from his onslaught.

What could be seen as Harry’s own betrayal of his family had not abated when he arrived at Windsor’s St George’s Chapel on 17th April for Prince Philip’s funeral. In his parallel state, he had been initially ‘afraid’ to return for the funeral because it would ‘trigger’ a trauma.[191] But while he could not avoid the funeral, he knew that Meghan would be unwelcome. After her appearance on Oprah Winfrey, she would not have dared to return to Britain. ‘Thank goodness Meghan’s not coming,’ the 94-year-old Queen said in a clear voice to her trusted aide as she prepared for the service that morning.[192]

Harry suffered no remorse. Charles and William, he knew, had clearly been thrown by the Oprah Winfrey interview. The enormous damage caused by his accusation that the Royal Family was racist was not beyond his comprehension.

Inside the chapel, the Queen, wearing a black Covid mask, sat in dignified isolation. That image generated huge sympathy around the world. Covid restrictions had sharply limited the number of mourners. Harry and Prince Andrew – both stripped of the honour of wearing their service uniforms – wore morning suits, as did the other mourners.

Anguish filled Charles’s face. William looked tense. Harry’s bland expression defied a charitable description. Outside the chapel afterwards, as he impatiently flapped the order of service on his thigh, he knew that the accusations about Oprah Winfrey were just a foretaste of much worse to come. Nevertheless, he agreed to Kate’s suggestion that he walk with William from the chapel back towards the castle. The TV commentators instantly cast Kate as the broker of reconciliation.

‘They’re filming us,’ William warned Harry. Their expressionless faces as they marched up the hill encouraged commentators to wild speculation. None realised that Harry expected a ‘genuine apology’ and ‘genuine accountability’ from Charles and William. In Harry’s terms, reconciliation was only possible if his family begged forgiveness from him and Meghan.

That hurdle became clear when Charles and his sons met after the funeral beyond Frogmore’s gardens. Harry claimed the meeting was his idea ‘to find a way out’ of the ‘months the Windsors had been at war’.[193] As he waited, he conjured the impression that he had spotted snipers across the rooftops outside St George’s Chapel. Their presence, he would claim, was because of an ‘unprecedented number of threats’ against him.[194] In reality, snipers were always deployed. On that day there were no unusual threats. His paranoia was in overdrive.

During his conversations with Moehringer, Harry had castigated his father for behaving with cold indifference in his bedroom after giving him the news of Diana’s death. His emotionally negligent father had failed to hug him. Twenty-four years later in Windsor, Harry seemingly had no sense that his father was suffering his own traumatic loss. As Charles and William approached him after the funeral, he observed only that neither smiled at him.[195]

‘They’d come ready for a fight,’ complained Harry, blaming the breakdown of relations on his father’s request that he stop his legal campaign against the tabloids. Moehringer articulated Harry’s fury towards Fleet Street as ‘the dreadful mob of dweebs and crones and cutrate criminals and clinically diagnosed sadists’ who earned their profits ‘by tormenting one very large, very ancient, very dysfunctional family’.[196]

Just two hours after the funeral, Harry accused his father and brother of being collaborators with the tabloids against him and Meghan: ‘You helped them against us.’

‘You’re delusional, Harry,’ said William. The Palace, added Charles, ‘can’t just tell the media what to do’.

Harry scoffed. By now, persuaded by Meghan, he believed that celebrities could control the media – just as William had fed The Times ‘their lie’ that Meghan was a bully. And, thought Harry, no one displayed more vanity towards the media than his father: ‘Deprived of love as a boy, bullied by schoolmates, he was dangerously, compulsively drawn to the elixir [newspapers] offered him.’[197] The two men, he deemed, were ‘lost’. In his anger near the graveyard, Harry accused his father and brother of allowing the tabloids to damage ‘our love and our bond’. ‘I’ll soon prove,’ he insisted, ‘that the press were more than liars. They were lawbreakers. I’m going to see some of them thrown into jail.’

Exasperated by Harry’s fantasies and lack of remorse, Charles and William realised that any communication with him was hopeless. Therapy had taught him a language his family didn’t understand. Every question they asked was misunderstood. Under Meghan’s influence he had moved into another world. ‘We have made it to the other side,’ Harry told his father.[198] In Moehringer ‘s version, Harry spewed out his recriminations without fear of contradiction. Moehringer, it appeared to one editor, was uncertain whether Harry understood himself.

That afternoon, neither Charles nor William grasped that in Harry’s new world, deception was acceptable. Harry’s subversion extended to his description of that very encounter in Windsor.

Lacking any sympathy for his family, Harry’s adrenaline was pumping as he flew back to Los Angeles. He did not reconsider withdrawing any of his condemnatory comments to Moehringer. On the contrary. On his return, Harry depicted his father to Moehringer as a worn-out, powerless wreck. Instead of feeling compassion for Charles – a son burying his father and witnessing his solitary, grieving mother – Harry lampooned Charles for appealing to his arguing sons during their confrontation, ‘Please, boys – don’t make my final years a misery.’ Distraught, Charles was portrayed as clueless about how to deal with the crisis he had partly created.

To bring their Windsor summit to a dramatic climax, Moehringer depicted Harry burdened by a ‘death cult’ generated by his family and the atmosphere in the chapel. Bravely, Harry ‘spoke’ how alone, he would ‘break free and live . . . I had changed to the point where I had outgrown my environment.’[199]

The Windsor meeting had deepened the three men’s distrust. The opportunity for reconciliation was lost. Harry had become fixated by hatred. Meghan and Moehringer stoked his wrath.

One month later, Harry delivered another blow against his family. An Apple TV series called The Me You Can’t See about his mental health, produced with Oprah Winfrey, was launched on 21st May 2021. The programmes focused on his mental torment. All his family, Harry believed, were ‘on the spectrum and we slide up and down’. The barrier to their relationship, he concluded, was his dysfunctional father’s and brother’s inability to ‘speak his new language’.[200] Mental health became his battering ram against his family. He even criticised the Queen and Philip as neglectful, unloving parents to Charles. Breathlessly he linked Charles’s ‘genetic pain’ to his own childhood misery. The rest of his family, especially William, were equally blamed for his ‘cycles of suffering’ and ‘unresolved anger’.

A scriptwriter provided the line to compare his life as ‘a mixture between The Truman Show and being in a zoo’ to introduce the monarchy: ‘I’ve seen behind the curtain. I’ve seen the business model. I know how this operation runs . . . I don’t want to be part of this.’

One particular trigger for his dudgeon, he said, was the ‘combined effort of The Firm and the media to smear Meghan’ while she was suicidal. ‘She was going to end her life. It shouldn’t have to get to that,’ and he added, ‘That was one of the biggest reasons to leave, feeling trapped and feeling controlled through fear, both by the media and by the system itself. I was ashamed to go to my family. Because I know that I’m not going to get from my family what I need.’

Cast by Buckingham Palace, according to Harry, as ‘villains’, he melodramatically ramped up the earlier accusations he had aired in the Oprah Winfrey interview. He described how he and ‘struggling’ Meghan had felt ‘bullied into silence’.[201] In his terms, the Palace’s own silence – the official refusal to ‘protect’ them – was ‘betrayal’.[202] Even while they negotiated their departure – ‘hunted and helpless’ in London – there were ‘forces working against us’. Harry never named those family members who ignored his pleas.

Persuaded by his therapist that his problems were caused by his family, Harry was certain that thanks to ayahuasca, a class-A psychedelic hallucinogen, his mental health had stabilised. Drugs had ‘helped me deal with the trauma of my past’. He could ‘open up’, he said. Like so many users of therapy, once he felt cured, Harry believed he possessed unique insight.[203]

Harry had first publicly revealed his mental health problems in 2017. Speaking on Bryony Gordon’s Mad World podcast, he described being ‘very close to a complete breakdown on numerous occasions’ and saved by ‘a shrink’. His therapy had started, he told Gordon, ‘three years ago’. The initiative in 2014, he repeated, was William’s: ‘Bless him, he was a huge support to me,’ he told Gordon. At that time, William was credited with urging him to get help after his breakdown related to Diana’s death and his service in Afghanistan. And by his own account, Harry emerged cured.

In 2021, Harry changed his narrative. On Oprah Winfrey’s show, Harry cut William out of the plot. He also buried his co-operation with William and Kate to launch jointly in 2016 the HeadsTogether campaign, a charity helping mental health sufferers. Then he changed his story again.

In the revised version as told to Moehringer, he needed to liberate himself from being ‘trapped’ within his uncaring family and the institution. ‘No one around me could really help,’ he said. The Royal Family, he now complained, gave him no support after his breakdown, and it was only after he met Meghan in 2016 that he was ‘inspired to pursue therapy’. Misleadingly, he added, ‘I knew that if I didn’t fix myself that I was going to lose this woman . . . That was the start of the learning journey for me.’ In this version, far from suggesting it, William had pointed to Meghan’s suggestion of therapy as the cause of Harry’s ‘brainwashing’.[204]

Into that confused mix, Harry added the accusation that the uncaring Royal Family had suppressed any discussion about Meghan’s mental health. ‘Every single ask, request, warning,’ Harry said, ‘just got met with total silence or total neglect.’ Accordingly, the Royal Family was blamed for Meghan being suicidal.

Inevitably, the public was not microscopically examining Harry’s inconsistent versions. But his accounts ranged from not telling his family about Meghan’s brush with suicide to asserting the opposite – that for more than one year he had discussed Meghan’s unhappiness with his family and outlined their dramatic solution. Namely, that they would leave Britain.[205]

Meghan was similarly responsible for contradictions. She had disclosed that her search for help while considering suicide was unsuccessful on two occasions. First, she was spurned by Buckingham Palace’s HR department and secondly, she was palmed off after telephoning a psychoanalyst. But she never suggested that she had spoken to members of the Royal Family. Her inconsistencies challenged Harry’s final version in Spare.

In the Apple TV series on his mental health, Harry thanked Meghan for telling him to seek a therapist. But if Harry found a therapist in 2016, why could the same therapist not be consulted for Meghan in 2019?

Harry’s versions, embellished by Meghan’s ‘truth’, would be seized on by Piers Morgan. ‘I wouldn’t believe Meghan Markle if she gave me a weather report,’ he claimed.[206] Morgan’s riposte was endorsed by her critics but was scorned by her admirers. In doing so, her critics concluded that Meghan’s suicidal feelings were a performance to persuade Harry to move to California.

The Apple series was a ratings success. Many were impressed by Harry, especially men who shared his reticence about discussing their mental health issues. Only a few had no sympathy for a multi-millionaire prince pleading for pity. For those, Harry posing as the public’s healer but only speaking about himself was simply too rich. The downsides caused no damage to Harry but Meghan sensed a problem.

CHAPTER 13

Security

Brand Sussexes’ image was critical to Meghan’s fortunes. Americans, she knew, resented scroungers or ‘grifters’. Meghan’s absence of humility – flaunting her celebrity lifestyle in Montecito – risked striking a bad note. Her critics carped that she was famous but not relevant. Meghan needed to twist the narrative to establish the Sussexes’ USP, their unique selling point. While Harry’s previous life would make him oblivious to commercial imperatives, she knew that the negative headlines from Britain’s media, about an elitist family aggressively protecting their privacy from within their closeted Montecito fortress, clashed with the public’s admiration of hard-working achievers who fulfilled the American Dream.

Wrestling with reality, Meghan’s business advisors and in-house publicist were faced with a conundrum. For many, she was an enigma. Standing in the spotlight, she somehow lacked the charisma and mysterious charm of a Hollywood star. Moreover, Hollywood’s celebrities often illustrated their backstories with tales of tough childhoods, climbing the ladder and finally landing the big break. But Meghan’s big break was marriage. While Harry remained irrefutably the prince, Meghan’s exceptional achievement was acting as a royal while complaining about his family. Complicating her publicists’ task, the Sussexes would not tolerate any criticism. On her publicists’ advice, Meghan changed her story.

Meghan had told Oprah Winfrey, ‘I grew up with that farm-to-table dining before it was sweeping the nation.’ She added, ‘I do think there’s some value to really throwing yourself into food and embracing where it comes from.’ [207] That truth was abandoned. Meghan’s revised version portrayed herself as a ‘latch-key kid’ surviving on junk Jack-in-the-box TV dinners [208] and a $4.99 salad bar at Sizzlers, and as a schoolgirl working at weekends at a local Humphrey Yogart shop.[209] ‘Lies and lies,’ Thomas Markle would retort. ‘She always ate the best food, often in the best restaurants.’[210] Meghan, he said, never had a weekend job and, if he was working late, she would either stay with her school friends or was brought to the studio in a chauffeured car. Most Americans preferred not to believe Thomas Markle. Attracted by the publicists’ new image of the Sussexes as charitable philanthropists escaping from a racist Royal Family, the majority warmed to the couple trading as the Duke and Duchess.

By now, Meghan was heavily pregnant with her second child. To reinforce their invaluable royal connection, the Sussexes decided to name their unborn daughter Lilibet, the Queen’s nickname used only by her closest family members. A Lilibet website – lilibetdiana.com – was even registered before the birth.[211]

Harry’s daughter was born at Santa Barbara’s Cottage Hospital on 4th June 2021, with an all-female medical team. After the birth, but before the public announcement, Harry called the Queen. He told his grandmother about the birth and their decision to call their daughter Lilibet. Harry claimed that the Queen approved the name.

Hours later, the Palace briefed the BBC that the Queen was ‘never asked’ for permission for the use of her name. In his telephone call, Harry was ‘telling’ the Queen, not asking her permission. Once the BBC broadcast that negative report, the Sussexes’ ‘truth’ machine was activated. ‘Had she not been supportive,’ said Toya Holness, their spokeswoman, ‘they would not have used the name.’ The Sussexes’ legal firm, Schillings, announced that unless the BBC apologised, the Sussexes would sue for defamation. Pitching Harry against the Queen was an extreme tactic to control the Sussexes’ image. The Palace, though, supported the BBC. Royal correspondent Robert Hardman would quote a senior Palace official that the Queen was ‘as angry as I’d ever seen her’ that she had agreed with Harry’s suggestion.[212] Faced with the factual truth, the Sussexes retreated. Schillings’s threat evaporated. The Sussexes’ ‘truth’ was defeated. Buckingham Palace’s refusal to support his truth outraged Harry. His old enemies in the Palace, he decided, especially Edward Young, were deliberately diminishing his status in Britain.

At the end of June, Harry and Meghan arrived at Heathrow. For the first time, no armed police protection officers were waiting. Convinced that his status and safety required armed guards, Harry was incandescent. Ever since his birth he was accustomed to being surrounded by protection officers. On all his excursions he was comforted by tough men prepared to die to ensure his safety. As a drunken teenager, he had been saved by them from disaster repeatedly. Before the Sandringham summit, he had not anticipated that the Royal Family would deprive him of their services.

The reality struck him on 30th June 2021. Early that evening, he and Meghan were driven out of London’s Kew Gardens after a WellChild function. Eager paparazzi came close to his car. Convinced that he and Meghan were a ‘sitting duck’ to be murdered by fanatics, he complained to Edward Young. Not only as fifth in line to the throne and a ‘prince of the realm’ was he entitled to protection, but also because of his ‘particular and unusual position’ after military service. He feared that ‘one lone actor’, motivated by right-wing hatred or racism, could attack Meghan with a knife or acid: ‘These are things that are genuine concerns for me.’[213]

Asking Young for help must have been irritating. Described in Moehringer’s script as ‘oval-faced and fuzzy appearance’ with a tendency to ‘glide around with great equanimity and poise as if he was a boon to all living things’, Harry disliked the Palace official.

Edward Young passed Harry’s complaint to Scotland Yard. The police agreed that the ‘ambush’ created an ‘unsatisfactory and dangerous’ situation, but while the paparazzi were a nuisance, there was no evidence that Harry and Meghan were threatened by a potential assassin.[214] Only that danger, replied Scotland Yard, would justify permanent police bodyguards around the Sussexes.

Harry’s rage revived after returning to Heathrow on 1st July for the unveiling of a statue to Diana. Again, no protection officers were waiting for him. Throughout his visit, photographers were not held back by the police. That, he decided, was intolerable.[215]

Harry’s rage had escalated since ‘Megxit’ in 2020. During the initial Sandringham summit, Harry had been told that the Royal Family would support his request for security but, he was cautioned, the decision would be made by a government committee called Ravec. The Royal and VIP Executive Committee was dedicated to assessing threats to the Royal Family and others.

Ravec, Harry knew, was part of the network of government committees filled with Establishment personalities, not least Clive Alderton, Charles’s private secretary. He believed that his father was pulling the strings. If Charles made a request to the committee to provide armed protection for Harry or asked the Home Office ‘for more help and greater flexibility’,[216] it was inconceivable that this would be denied. Harry had called his father but Charles refused to take his telephone calls. He agreed with suspicious Palace officials that his son’s constant demands for money and protection reflected Meghan’s influence. They concluded the demand for armed bodyguards reflected a desire to enhance their status.

To ensure Harry understood, Edward Young had sent him on 11th January – eighteen months before the incident at Heathrow – a detailed message emphasising that Ravec and not Buckingham Palace would decide whether he needed armed protection.

Ravec’s chairman was Richard Mottram, the former head of the defence ministry and ex-head of Whitehall’s joint intelligence committee. For three days after the Sandringham summit, Mottram considered whether Harry and his family should be protected. The cost would be about £10,000 a day. Back-up cars cost extra. By then, Mottram believed from Harry’s conversations with his family and friends from Vancouver that the Sussexes were breaking off from the Royal Family. Few believed the Sussexes’ pledge to ‘start a new life in Canada’ or Harry’s assertion that ‘the UK is my home’. Indeed, Whitehall’s officials had already heard from confidential sources that the Sussexes intended to move permanently to California. The Cabinet Secretary, Mark Sedwill, called Harry in Canada. Police protection, said Sedwill, was provided to working royals to prevent violent attacks, not to guard celebrities irritated by the public. And Harry, as a non-working royal living abroad, could not expect British taxpayers to fund his security. He would need to pay for private bodyguards. Unexpectedly, Sedwill discovered Harry’s unwillingness to accept that he was responsible for his own fate.

At that time in 2020, Harry called Edward Young. He expected the Queen, he said, to overrule Mottram’s decision. Young replied that Mottram refused to budge. Not least because the intelligence agencies had not discovered any evidence that Harry or his family were exposed to an identifiable risk. Critically, Mottram did not ask the government’s Risk Management Board (RMB) to evaluate the risk Harry faced. The reason, Mottram later explained, was that Harry’s new circumstances as a non-working royal were unprecedented. A special ‘flexible and tailored’ approach would be necessary.

Harry’s fury grew. How, he demanded, could these decisions be made without anyone consulting him? He was leaving Britain because his family was at risk. That reason should justify protection. He and Meghan alone would decide whether he was in danger. Not a government official. As usual, Harry was inconsistent. Previously, Harry had justified his departure from Britain by highlighting the Palace’s refusal to protect him and Meghan from the media. Now he claimed that he had been compelled to escape from the risk of an assassin. No one bothered to tell Harry that he had shifted his ground.

Unaccustomed to being rebuffed, Harry demanded the name of the government official who was willing to put the Sussexes in a position of extreme vulnerability ‘as some form of punishment for protecting my family and putting them first’. Even twenty-three years earlier, raged Harry, when the risks were lower, the government did not expose ‘my mother’ to that risk. That was inaccurate. Fearing they were spying on her, Diana had actually dispensed with police bodyguards rather than had them taken away.

Over the next few days, Whitehall’s most senior officials were inundated with a flow of Harry’s emails demanding the identity of the official ‘comfortable taking accountability for what could happen’. Officials could not decide whether ‘Meghan’s self-important quest for status was feeding Harry’s paranoia’.[217] After all, Princess Anne travelled without protection unless on some royal duties and she had already been the target of an attempted kidnap.

Harry next called the Queen. At her request, on 6th February 2020, Young told Sedwill what had been agreed between Harry and the Queen at Sandringham. ‘You will understand,’ Young wrote, ‘that ensuring the Duke and Duchess of Sussex remain safe is of paramount importance to Her Majesty and her family.’ Mindful of Diana’s ‘tragic’ death and the Sussexes being targets of extremists, Young continued, ‘it is imperative that the family continues to be provided with effective security.’[218] Young appealed to Sedwill to reassure Harry that his protection was being considered as requested by the sovereign, but government officials and not the Royal Family made the decision. Young’s email about the Queen’s request for his protection was, in Harry’s opinion, window dressing. In what he’d called a palace of lies he could imagine that moments after Young’s email was sent, Young telephoned Sedwill to say that the message was simply for the records and should be ignored. In their vipers’ nest, that sort of manoeuvre was apparently normal.

Harry accused Edward Young of obstruction. Because of ‘significant tensions’ between himself and the Queen’s private secretary, explained Harry, he doubted that Young had ‘fully communicated’ his offer of paying for protection to Ravec. Harry also accused Young of negatively influencing Ravec’s decision to axe his taxpayer-funded police bodyguards.[219]

Harry made the same accusations against Mark Sedwill, the Cabinet Secretary. Harry claimed that in January and in April 2020, he told Sedwill personally he would pay for his own protection but that his offers were not passed on to Ravec. Government lawyers denied that Harry made an offer to anyone before he started legal proceedings against the government in September 2021. Harry’s veracity was undermined by the government’s records.[220] There was no record of Harry offering to pay for his protection at the Sandringham summit.

On 28th February 2020, Mottram formally told Harry that Ravec had withdrawn the Sussexes’ permanent police protection. The taxpayer would not pay for his protection abroad. In future, before each visit to Britain, Ravec would monitor the risks and decide whether Harry needed protection. Mottram also told Harry that he could not pay for police protection. The reason was irrefutable: police bodyguards were expected to risk their lives to protect their principal because the state had decided that it was in the public interest. To permit Harry to pay would be an unacceptable precedent allowing others also to buy life-or-death protection.[221]

Harry’s sustained fury on this matter on his return to Heathrow in July 2021 must have been wonderful news for his lawyers. By then, Schillings were fighting two cases on Harry’s behalf against the tabloids (the Mirror Group and News UK) and considering two more cases. Harry was a lucrative client – ‘a goldmine’ said one critic – guaranteeing the lawyers millions of pounds if they won or lost.

Jenny Afia, the solicitor who had at this time just won Meghan’s case against the Mail on Sunday, encouraged Harry to believe that Mottram’s decision could be overruled by the High Court. The lawyers’ confidence of victory and their promise to dispatch acrimonious complaints to government officials fell on fertile ground.

In Harry’s opinion, going over the top was justified. Going into battle to show that he was the victim of his family raised his self-confidence. Embarrassing his father and brother had seemingly become a worthwhile quest. His security, he said, had only been withdrawn to apply pressure ‘to keep us under the roof’ and ‘knowing that risk would force us to come back [to Britain]’.[222]

In Harry’s world, since everything he believed was the truth, he was certain of victory. In his reasoning he could not imagine that a judge considering the merits between himself and government officials would not support a prince. During his conversations with Moehringer, his conviction that he was the victim of conspiracies had been reinforced. He expected to swing public opinion in his favour. Eventually he believed he would win.

In September 2021, Harry instructed his lawyers to issue a High Court claim – for a judicial review against the Home Office. In particular, Harry complained that Mottram’s decision subjected him to ‘unlawful and unfair treatment’. In secrecy, Ravec had failed to offer ‘a clear and full explanation’ of how they came to the decision to treat him uniquely ‘less favourably’ than others.[223] Not only was Ravec’s failure to commission a RMB report unlawful, he said, but Ravec’s denial of 24-hour armed guards was illegal.

Edward Young was flummoxed. Harry’s action was unprecedented. A member of the Royal Family suing the Queen’s government in the Queen’s court embarrassed the monarchy. The Queen’s private secretary, noted one observer, was ‘puzzled’ about who had encouraged Harry to ‘take to the courts’, and Young was also ‘terrified’ that Harry was suing two newspapers. In one case, he had employed four barristers.[224] In the end, they blamed Meghan.

Harry’s claim against the Home Office was unknown to the public. His lawyers asked the judge to keep the proceedings secret. The Home Office opposed the denial of ‘open justice’ and awaited a judge’s decision.

Excited by firing off on so many fronts, Harry and Meghan arrived in New York later that month for a high-profile visit. Just crowned by Time magazine as number one among America’s 100 most influential people, the couple had reached the zenith of their fame and popularity. Without any problems, the Sussexes’ staff had persuaded the city’s mayor and police to provide the maximum security necessary for the Queen’s grandson.

Bursting with enthusiasm, the Sussexes had every reason to believe they were privileged royals. Although Meghan had told Vanity Fair, ‘I’ve never defined myself by my relationship,’ she always introduced herself as the Duchess of Sussex, not least as a nascent politician in telephone calls to two Republican senators to promote paid parental leave.

Every move in Manhattan was carefully planned to satisfy the Sussexes’ narrative – their importance as members of the Royal Family. Their tour included visits to the site of the Twin Towers, the United Nations and the headquarters of the World Health Organization, all ideal photo opportunities for the Netflix cameraman given access for chosen sequences.

In preparing for the Sussexes’ visit to the Mahalia Jackson elementary school in Harlem, spokeswoman Toya Holness told the school’s head that Meghan would be filmed reading her new book, The Bench, to a class of children. To perfect the image, Holness had arranged to have the classroom transformed to make it look ‘more appealing’. The room’s walls were painted, attractive cushions were strategically placed and the lighting improved. In advance, the city’s media spokeswoman Danielle Filson sent Holness her draft press release. Holness objected to Filson’s description of Meghan ‘reading aloud’. She wanted a ‘more substantial’ description of Meghan contributing to ‘community support’. Filson replied that the release should not be ‘promotiony’ – exactly what the Sussexes did want.[225] Holness won that battle.

To control their image, Meghan demanded that everyone involved, including city officials, sign NDAs and not make any ‘negative’ comments about the couple.[226] The result was media reports about her carping demands. Since journalists were excluded from the school, their reports ridiculed the appropriateness of Meghan’s $15,000 outfit, including a Loro Piana cashmere coat. They also questioned how her happy family book was relevant to the deprived children she was meeting and whether the Sussexes could promote a fictional father’s relationship with his child considering that they were both estranged from their own fathers. Those jibes were ignored. The Sussexes’ quest for public approval in America remained secure, just as their reputations in Britain became more precarious.

At the same time, Jason Knauf had signed a statement that Meghan had not told the truth in her Mail on Sunday case. Her statement that she had not consulted Knauf about her letter to her father and her denial of any co-operation with Omid Scobie, said Knauf, was untrue. Not only had he been consulted about the letter but on Meghan’s orders, he had given Omid Scobie a copy of Meghan’s letter to her father. Clearly, Meghan had expected her ‘private’ letter would be published.

Schillings communicated this to Meghan. Clearly shocked by Knauf’s version of events, Meghan composed herself. In adversity, she took advice and fought back. She carefully arranged for herself and Harry to be filmed as if reading that message from Schillings for the first time, flying on a private jet to New York. ‘How do we deal with that?’ she asked Harry. She then accused William of authorising Knauf’s statement to be leaked to The Times: ‘It’s your brother,’ she said on camera. Harry agreed: ‘They’ll try and cover it up.’[227] In the context of Knauf accusing Meghan of lying, the Sussexes’ sound bites were nonsensical. But in their battle to damage William’s reputation and that of the monarchy, their contrived exchange – all filmed for their Netflix documentary – was perfect. Especially after what followed in New York and London.

The Mail on Sunday appealed against Meghan’s victory. Seven weeks before the appeal was to be heard in London, in November 2021, Harry was on the stage at a RE:WIRED conference in New York denouncing the media. Recently, he had called the First Amendment – America’s constitutional cornerstone to protect the media from state censorship – as ‘bonkers’ and ‘vulgar’. The media, he told the conference, had no interest in publishing the truth: ‘Misinformation is a global humanitarian crisis.’ Inaccurate journalists were damned by Harry as ‘the pirates with press cards who have hijacked the most powerful industry in the world’. He asked, ‘If the news media is supposed to be holding us to account, who is holding them to account? I would love to see a movement to expose the unethical, the immoral and dishonest amongst them.’ Emotionally, he attacked the British media for ‘creating news with a vested interest’ to provoke Meghan’s untimely death.

Just as Harry delivered that condemnation, Meghan, acting on her lawyer’s advice, admitted Knauf’s allegations. Indeed, she admitted that she had signed an inaccurate statement. She apologised to the judges. In normal legal cases, Meghan would have been vulnerable to merciless cross-examination during a trial, weakening her case against the Mail on Sunday. But despite her mistake, Schillings were confident of victory. England’s judges, the lawyers knew, were prejudiced against the media and historically always supported the Royal Family. The lawyers’ prediction was accurate. Three judges accepted Meghan’s apology, blaming an ‘unfortunate lapse of memory’. A proper trial, they declared, was unnecessary. They ruled in her favour.

The Sussexes were euphoric. ‘This is a victory not just for me but for anyone who has ever felt scared to stand up for what’s right,’ said Meghan, damning the Mail and other tabloids. ‘In the nearly three years since this began, I have been patient in the face of deception, intimidation and calculated attacks.’[228]

Meghan and Harry had every reason to believe they were a protected golden couple with the world at their feet. Neither would be familiar with the witch’s warning at the opening of Macbeth: ‘Shall he dwindle, peak and pine.’ Those at the top rarely have the foresight to imagine their irreversible decline.

CHAPTER 14

Spare

‘The editing process was chaotic,’ recalls an editor at Penguin Random House describing the scene in Manhattan in early 2022. Drafts of chapters sent by Moehringer were distributed among several editors at all levels of seniority. Each editor rewrote the draft and returned their own versions. Adding to the confusion, the editors’ revised chapters became redundant because Moehringer had rewritten his original draft chapter and then had reworked it again after Harry and Moehringer’s wife, Shannon Welch, had also added comments. ‘Moehringer introduced chaos,’ observed an editor. ‘I discovered that we were working from several drafts of the same chapters.’

One origin of the problem was a disagreement between Moehringer and Harry about the book’s core theme – the Prince himself. To under-stand Harry, the British class system and the aristocracy, Moehringer was encouraged to visit Harry’s friends in Britain. Moehringer would write: ‘I interviewed the socks off . . . all the people in Harry’s inner circle, a vital phase in every ghosting job.’[229] The friends he visited described not only Harry’s drinking, drugs and nightclubbing, but also his problems at school and with his parents. None of the interviews made the final version. Only Guy Pelly, among Harry’s many friends, merited a brief mention, while his polo friend Nacho Figueras was consigned to the acknowledgements.

Multiple pages written by Moehringer arrived at Penguin Random House with intimate details about Harry’s life in Britain, but without any context of the Prince living in a gilded cage. The editors never had the sense that Moehringer understood Harry’s life as a wayward multi-millionaire without a care about money, homelessness or unemployment. Instead, Moehringer focused on magnifying trifling incidents, such as his complaint about insufficient natural light into his basement home at Kensington Palace and arguments about a parking space. Harry condemned William for having a bigger bedroom as a child, cursed him for ignoring him at Eton and was plainly angry that William did not trust him to make a best man speech at his wedding dinner.

The gold dust for Moehringer and the editors was Harry’s graphic descriptions of successive shouting matches with Charles and William. The pages describing their fractured relationship sprang to life. Not least William ‘lunging’ at Harry’s shirt during their confrontation after Prince Philip’s funeral. Similarly, the editors were enthusiastic about Harry’s descriptions of his father as emotionally damaged and indecisive. To disparage the future king, Harry told Moehringer that Charles usually travelled with his childhood teddy bear, did yoga in his undershorts to cure his back pain and forever smelt things. ‘He must have been a bloodhound in another life,’ Moehringer inserted. The climax to Harry’s damnation of Charles, as told to Moehringer, was his father’s fear of being ‘overshadowed’ by Meghan, who was inevitably destined to ‘take centre stage’.

No one questioned Harry’s inaccurate assertion that Charles did not financially support him or William. Charles’s rebuke to Harry –‘I’m not made of money’ – rang true but ignored Harry’s request for even more than his annual £1 million allowance plus his living expenses.

Moehringer appears to have rarely checked Harry’s version of events. Simple mistakes were unquestioningly included. ‘Now you’ve given me an heir and a “spare”,’ Charles allegedly told Diana in hospital after Harry’s birth, ‘my work is done.’ His father, recounted Harry, had then ‘gone off to meet his girlfriend’. But Diana told Andrew Morton, the most trustworthy reporter of Diana’s sentiments, that Charles had said, ‘Oh, it’s a boy and he’s even got rusty hair.’ Charles, according to Diana, left the hospital to play polo. Diana later told Richard Kay, another trusted journalist, that Harry’s birth marked the happiest period of their marriage. Charles’s relationship with Camilla resumed more than one year after Harry’s birth.[230]

Among Harry’s other ‘vivid’ memories was the Queen Mother’s death in March 2002. The news, Harry said, was delivered to him by a courtier on ‘a bright and warm Easter’ at Eton: ‘Your Highness, the Queen Mother has died.’ In reality, Harry was skiing in Klosters in Switzerland. On an overcast day, Charles gave him the news. They immediately returned to London.

Harry’s more important ‘mistake’ was his reason to publish the book: to rebut ‘every lie published about him’.[231] Newspapers, he told Moehringer, had accused him of ‘cheating in A-level art’. The media’s source was the admission by Harry’s art teacher at Eton that she had improved his exam answer. In Harry’s version, his demand that the Palace issue a denial for publication was refused by ‘cold-hearted’ officials. Harry was wrong. On that same day, newspapers published Clarence House’s and Eton’s official denials of the teacher’s confession as ‘untrue’ and ‘absurd’. The Palace’s dishonesty was not unusual. On Harry’s orders, Palace officials repeatedly lied to protect him, not least about his teenage usage of drugs.

Scrutinising Harry’s version of events was initially hampered by the difficulty of conducting interviews on Zoom. Once the Covid restrictions were abandoned, Moehringer headed to Montecito for intensive face-to-face conversations, where he would watch Harry assert that newspapers called him a ‘coward’ by ‘faking’ a knee injury on the eve of going into the army. Moehringer recorded the false accusation, but no newspaper published that claim. On the contrary, newspapers described ‘courageous’ Harry’s misery about missing his deployment because of the ‘unfortunate’ injury.

Similarly, Harry spoke at length about the media’s responsibility for causing the suicide of television presenter Caroline Flack, who took her own life in February 2020. The death of his friend, Harry told Moehringer, was rooted in ‘the relentless abuse at the hands of the press, year after year’.[232] That was untrue. The coroner found that Flack killed herself because she was to be prosecuted for assaulting a boy-friend in the midst of an unhappy relationship. Her family did not in fact directly blame the media for her suicide.

As Harry recounted these false stories to Moehringer, his real agenda appeared to be proving how the racist media had persecuted Meghan, forcing him to flee the country. The harassment, he said, had started in 2016 – at the outset of their relationship. Meghan had walked from Kensington Palace to shop at the local Whole Foods shop. In Harry’s description, as she queued at the checkout she saw rows and rows of magazines and newspapers, all with shocking and disgusting headlines about her. Other shoppers noticed her, looked at the newspapers and shared ‘a horrible smile’ with the cashiers.[233] In fact, Whole Foods didn’t even stock newspapers or magazines. And in 2016, their relationship was still mysterious. The only person who spotted Meghan – because she was still unknown in London – was the Daily Mail’s diarist Richard Kay, who was by chance on Kensington High Street during an unplanned break from his nearby office. And that day Meghan did not feature on a single front page.

Among his complaints against the newspaper, Harry told Moehringer that Meghan’s legal claim against the Mail on Sunday was subject to a media blackout. ‘In fact, it was barely covered at all,’ Harry said.[234] In truth, every newspaper devoted huge coverage to the case, especially the Mail.

* * *

In January 2022, Harry’s antagonism towards the Mail propelled him to take a risk. In the early stages of his court case against the Home Office to secure police protection, a judge ruled that the case would not be heard in secret. Soon after, the Mail on Sunday proposed to publish a story headlined ‘Harry: Give Back My Bodyguards’.[235] The newspaper reported that Harry had sued the government three months earlier, in September 2021, to restore his taxpayer-funded 24-hour protection. ‘Why,’ asked the Mail on Sunday’s commentator Sarah Vine, ‘should the British people continue to pay for two people who bad-mouth their previous employer all over town?’[236]

On Saturday night, shortly before the newspaper began printing, Schillings briefed the Press Association news agency to ‘set the facts straight’. Harry, according to Schillings, had offered to pay for his protection at the Sandringham summit. ‘That offer was dismissed,’ said Schillings, voicing Harry’s version. Schillings added an important proviso: Harry was still prepared to pay to protect his family when they visited Britain and he would sue the Home Office for refusing to allow him to pay personally for police protection.[237]

Days later, Harry’s version about offering to pay for protection began to unravel. Edward Young recalled again that Harry had not made that offer at Sandringham. In fact, Young remembered the opposite. In an email, Harry had said that he didn’t have the money to pay for protection.[238] For those weary of Harry’s sermons against ‘online misinformation’, his ‘error’ was damning.

Harry’s position was also inconsistent. In the secret September 2021 court hearing of his case, Harry did not mention paying for his protection. He demanded that the Home Office reinstate his taxpayer-funded police protection. The confusion had been sown by Harry’s solicitors’ briefing to the Press Association.

The Mail on Sunday’s headline was blunt: ‘How Prince Harry tried to keep his legal fight with the government over police bodyguards a secret . . . then just minutes after the story broke, his PR machine tried to put a positive spin on the dispute.’[239] Harry’s honesty was publicly challenged.

Yet Harry’s vendetta dropped on to the Palace at a difficult time, just a few days after officials had received bad news from America. A judge had ruled that the sex abuse case launched by Virginia Giuffre – a victim of the convicted paedophile Jeffrey Epstein – against Prince Andrew would be heard in court. Days later, the Queen stripped Andrew of his military honours, patronages and his title as His Royal Highness. To save the jubilee celebrations, Andrew had been cast into the wilderness and ordered to settle the case with Giuffre. Outsiders speculated that the settlement cost the Royal Family £12 million.

Embarrassingly, Charles was also embroiled in scandal. On the same day that Andrew became a private citizen, Scotland Yard announced it would investigate the offer of a knighthood and British citizenship to Mahfouz Marei Mubarak bin Mahfouz, a Saudi donor to Charles’s charity project, Dumfries House in Scotland. The offer had been made by Michael Fawcett, the trusted manager of Charles’s money-raising efforts for over twenty years.

Charles’s relationship with the Saudi businessman was awkward. Not least because in a secret and photographed ceremony in Buckingham Palace in 2016, Charles had awarded Mubarak a CBE. After the matter was exposed in November 2021, Charles denied any knowledge of Fawcett’s alleged offer of an honour for cash.[240] Fawcett was forced to resign from Charles’s foundation and conveniently found lucrative employment with a Lebanese businessman living in Knightsbridge. Without explanation, the police ended their investigation. If Fawcett had been prosecuted, the monarchy’s reputation would have been damaged.

To further embarrass Charles, during the uproar, Harry’s publicist revealed that Harry had received £50,000 from Mubarak in 2013 for Sentebale, a charity for children with HIV which Harry had created in 2006 in Botswana and Lesotho, a landlocked country in southern Africa.[241] But unlike Charles, Harry had cut off relations with Mubarak in 2015, despite the offer of £1 million for his charity. Mubarak’s condition was that Harry would first meet the businessman in Saudi Arabia and then receive the money. The donation appeared to be tainted by ‘cash for access’ – the precise charge Charles had faced over many years.[242]

Then the publicity got even worse. The Sunday Times reported that Charles had accepted €3 million from the Qatari prime minister between 2011 and 2015. At private meetings, the millions were said to have been handed over to Charles in plastic shopping bags filled with banknotes.[243] Already infamous for accepting millions of pounds from rich donors for his charities over the previous twenty-five years,[244] the story made Charles look grubby. Charles suspected that the latest exposés were linked to Harry’s legal warfare. Harry had fallen further under the influence of his lawyers, but both Harry and Schillings were beyond the Palace’s control.

Furious about the Mail’s accusation that, in Harry’s interpretation, he had ‘lied in his initial public statements’ about his offer to pay for police protection, Harry sued the newspaper for defamation. The Mail, complained Harry, had caused him ‘substantial harm, embarrassment and distress which is continuing’. The Mail’s report, added Harry, was an ‘attack on his honesty and integrity’.[245]

Harry’s misfortune was that the judge assigned to his case, Matthew Nicklin, was more supportive of the media than the four judges who had ruled in Meghan’s favour. At the first hurdle, Nicklin rejected Harry’s allegation that the Mail had accused him of lying. The newspaper’s lawyers, said the judge, had carefully avoided that pitfall. But Nicklin agreed that the article damaged Harry’s reputation by accusing him of intending ‘to mislead the public’. He later refused to resolve the case in Harry’s favour without a trial, speculating that the statements issued on Harry’s behalf could at a trial be described as ‘a masterclass in the art of spinning’ and in ‘misleading’ the public.[246] By slipping into a swamp of litigation, Harry was no longer the master of his own destiny.

At the heart of all four cases, against the Home Office and against the Mail on Sunday, was Harry’s conviction that Palace officials were targeting him. By July 2022, Harry’s case against the government had cost taxpayers over £100,000. His own costs were over £200,000.[247]

Money was of no concern to Harry. He was on a roll, convinced that he would slay all the dragons.

* * *

At Penguin Random House’s Manhattan headquarters in summer 2022, still no one questioned Harry’s version of events. As Moehringer’s redrafts arrived to be edited, more errors were creeping into the script – for example, the assertion that the Queen’s corgis were descended from Queen Victoria’s reign, whereas they were introduced to the Royal Family in 1933. To weed out the slapdash, Sabele Editorial were hired as fact-checkers. Their owner, Hilary McClellen, would be thanked by Harry for ‘superb fact-checking’. The corgi fable would be published in the book.

Harry’s petulance had also crept into the script. Few Palace employees were more odious to Harry than Paul Burrell, Diana’s long-standing valet. Harry did not tell Moehringer how Burrell’s criminal trial for allegedly stealing a vast trove of Diana’s personal possessions had dramatically ended shortly before Burrell was about to give evidence in his own defence. Burrell’s testimony about ‘safeguarding’ Diana’s secret tape recordings of a former Palace valet’s allegations would have shattered the monarchy, endangering Prince Charles’s succession.[248] Months later, Burrell earned millions of pounds from his bestselling ghosted memoir filled with revelations about Diana’s love life. Harry damned Burrell’s book as ‘merely one man’s self-justifying, self-centring version of events’. Harry never considered that his own book would attract the same criticism.

By then, a senior rewriter under Ben Greenberg, Random House’s editor-in-chief, witnessed repeated clashes between Harry and Greenberg. ‘Harry was considered to be a difficult author,’ recalls the editor. Irritatingly, Harry had rejected a dozen cover pictures taken by Ramona Rosales, fuelling Greenberg’s complaint about Harry being ‘argumentative’ and ‘missing deadlines’.

Part of the problem, as one editor observed, was the ‘haphazard’ management of Moehringer. In his narrative, the playboy Prince appeared to be a beleaguered, insecure weakling. Every damnation he uttered would make a headline, but some editors believed that Moehringer’s drafts had not fully grasped Harry’s resentment of being the ‘spare’, not the heir. Seeking attention and love, he was breaking the bond of trust with his brother. Humiliatingly, Harry revealed that his ‘arch nemesis’, the future king, suffered ‘alarming baldness’ and had probably been circumcised.[249] Most pointedly, he revealed their brutal argument about Meghan in Nottingham Cottage’s kitchen, which resulted in Harry falling and breaking a pottery dog bowl and his necklace being ripped off. Photographs of the same kitchen showed a metal dog bowl.

‘There’s overkill,’ the editors agreed. ‘Too much about the tensions and disagreements between Harry and his brother and father. Harry’s saying the same thing again and again.’ Some of his explicit criticisms of other members of the Royal Family, including the Queen and Prince Philip, were too raw, a senior editor decided. The publishers’ motive was not to protect the Royal Family but to make the book readable.

To Harry’s great annoyance, Moehringer was told to cut out a number of the arguments. Harry apparently reported his fury to Meghan who, by then, had read so many versions that her interest was evaporating. As her involvement waned, Harry’s indignation increased. Occasionally, as he read an edited version of a bitter dispute, Harry demanded a deletion. Moehringer was angry and explained that those passages were the heart of his story – of Harry battling against a dysfunctional family. Sometimes Moehringer won, sometimes Harry. And then Harry changed his mind, somersaulting in every direction on deletion and inclusion.

Caught between his editors and Harry, Moehringer became ‘exasperated’: ‘My head was pounding, my jaw was clenched, and I was starting to raise my voice,’ wrote Moehringer. He explained to Harry, ‘Strange as it may seem, a memoir isn’t about you. It’s a story carved from your life, a particular series of events chosen because they have the greatest resonance for the widest range of people.’[250] Harry was probably mystified.

‘But is it all true?’ an editor asked. ‘Factual errors,’ replied Moehringer, ‘can’t exist in an autobiography.’ Harry’s memory, Moehringer knew, was self-serving and faulty. Not least because he had learned from therapy that facts don’t matter. Only Harry’s version of the truth counted. In his mind, subjective belief cancelled out irrefutable facts.

The customary demands of publishing only provable facts went out of the window. The pretence was at best irrelevant and at worst unachievable. To give Harry his voice, regardless of the truth, they agreed with Moehringer to adopt what is known as Gonzo journalism. Made famous by the American writer Hunter S. Thompson in the 1970s, Gonzo journalism focuses on the author’s personal experiences and emotions. Any suggestion of objectivity is buried. Instead of the real truth, the author’s ‘voice’ is exaggerated and sarcasm is heightened.

Gonzo journalism empowered Moehringer’s text to overflow with Harry’s self-pity about abuse, traumas and neglect, topped by his refusal to take responsibility for his own behaviour. In Moehringer’s words, Harry was oblivious of the real worldly challenges facing the Royal Family to survive and remain relevant. Instead, reflecting his deep unhappiness as the wretched ‘spare’, Moehringer cast Harry as the victim of the Palace and the press, bursting to stand out as a genuine hero, the soldier who cold-bloodedly killed twenty-five Taliban fighters – or, in Moehringer’s prose, ‘chess pieces’. That heroism justified the victim to wreak vengeance on his family.

To illuminate his Gonzo journalism, Moehringer inserted famous men’s thoughts into the text. In Andre Agassi’s autobiography Open, Moehringer had quoted Freud, Jung and mythology to explain the tennis champion’s tortured psyche. To bestow credibility to Harry’s ‘voice’, Moehringer cited the French philosopher/writer Jean-Paul Sartre and the novelist William Faulkner, both likely unknown to Harry but according to Meghan, among her favourites. Probably one of the few famous Frenchmen Harry could name was Charles de Gaulle. To justify the inaccuracies, Moehringer composed an unusual explanation for Harry: ‘There’s just as much truth in what I remember and how I remember it as there is in so-called objective facts.’ He added a quotation, ‘The line between memory and fact is blurry, between interpretation and fact.’

Neither Moehringer nor the editors appear to have reconciled Harry’s campaign against journalists’ falsehoods with his own justification for publishing fantasies about his family: ‘We often record emotion alone, all detail blurred into unreadable smear.’

The final arguments followed the lawyers’ demands. To avoid legal recrimination, the names of paparazzi photographers and some tabloid editors were removed. But two British newspaper editors particularly disliked by Harry were named: the Mirror’s Piers Morgan and the Sun’s Rebekah Brooks. Nicknamed by Moehringer as ‘Rehabber Kooks’, Brooks was described as ‘the main villain in the phone-hacking scandal’ – except that at the end of a criminal trial in 2014, she had been acquitted by a jury, to Harry’s ‘incredulity’. He was allowed by Penguin Random House’s lawyers to include as fair comment, ‘My faith in the whole system took a serious hit when that woman got off scot-free. They were letting this woman walk? And there was no furore from the public?’[251]

One issue discussed by Random House’s senior editors was Meghan’s allegations about the Royal Family’s racism. In the aftermath of the Oprah Winfrey interview, Harry had come under enormous pressure, not only from Charles and William, but also from his aunt Anne and other family members. Knowing that Meghan’s description to Oprah Winfrey of the ‘conversations’ before Archie’s birth about his skin colour was untrue, Harry shifted her accusation to ‘unconscious bias’. That waffle made no sense to the editors. Amid a lot of argument, Harry agreed to remove all mention of the Royal Family’s alleged racism.

In June 2022, the editors assumed that the manuscript was nearly complete. The original 800 pages had been reduced to 400 pages. Among the deletions was Harry’s 25-page report to the Palace refuting the allegations of Meghan bullying her staff. Only the phrase that he had ‘demonstrated their lie’ remained.

To achieve simultaneous global publication in the late autumn, the manuscript would need to be translated into fifteen languages for both the book and the audio versions. The sales team at Penguin Random House reported advance orders suggesting that the book would be ‘big’. Some final details in the manuscript would be completed after Harry’s return from London to celebrate the Queen’s jubilee in June 2022, her seventieth year as monarch.

CHAPTER 15

Jubilee

Harry had not yet agreed that he would be in London with Meghan and his children for the jubilee celebrations. Although his absence would be an unforgivable insult and damage his image, he didn’t appear to mind.

Stung by Harry’s criticisms, Edward Young was suspicious of Harry. Not only because of the Sussexes’ anti-royal publicity blitz but for his conduct after visiting the Queen in Windsor in April 2022. He had been on his way from Los Angeles to Holland for the Invictus Games. By any measure, the Games were one of Harry’s few achievements. Launched in London in 2014, they were staged to encourage injured servicemen to take up sport to help recover from their wounds. In the first competition, four hundred men and women from thirteen countries contested ten sports over four days. A quarter of the competitors were British. The highlight of the second Games in Orlando in 2016 was the visit of Barack and Michelle Obama.

In 2022, the Games were supported by President Biden’s wife, Jill, and other political leaders. Harry had met Jill Biden in 2013 in Colorado where he was visiting the Warrior Games, the inspiration for Invictus Games. She attended the 2014 Invictus Games in London and the 2016 Games in Orlando, Florida.[252] On his way to the fifth Games in The Hague, Harry could expect an ecstatic welcome. But not when he arrived in London.

The Queen was still critical of Harry’s decision to move to California. ‘Turning one’s back on duty,’ recalled the Queen’s friend Lady Elizabeth Anson, ‘is completely alien to the Queen and she has been very hurt by it all.’[253] Contrary to Harry’s version, the Queen was also critical of the Sussexes before their wedding. ‘The Queen,’ Anson said, ‘was very upset by how Harry behaved and some of his demands. I remember her being rather upset by how beastly Harry was being. Their relationship was quite badly damaged by it all . . . He was rude to her for ten minutes.’[254]

Their relationship further deteriorated after Harry’s appearance on the Oprah Winfrey special. And there was the prospect of more denunciations to come. Harry, the Queen feared, was destroying the mystique of the Crown with his repeated media performances. The cool reception of the Sussexes by the Queen’s courtiers in Windsor Castle in April 2022 reflected the family’s suspicions.

For his part, Harry publicly denied any acrimony. But he sensed he was being ranked as an outsider. To reassert his importance, arriving in The Hague, Harry unexpectedly agreed to be interviewed by America’s NBC TV. His timing appeared calculated to overshadow the Queen’s ninety-sixth birthday and the publication of a new photograph of the monarch. In case his interview failed to dominate the news, his publicist Toya Holness also arranged a photocall of him with Meghan. The Duchess, briefed her publicist, was wearing jewellery worth £300,000, including a Cartier watch owned by Diana.[255] That was all froth compared to Harry’s comments to NBC about his grandmother’s sentiments during their private meeting: ‘We have a really special relationship; we talk about things she can’t talk about with anybody else.’ With a jibe at Edward Young, he added: ‘I’m just making sure that she’s, you know, protected and got the right people around her.’

‘Harry’s Game,’ commented The Times about the NBC interview, showed that the exile had ‘descended into self-pity and hypocrisy’. His appearance, the newspaper concluded, was ‘narcissistic’. The Sussexes had ‘sought to manipulate and profit from the media coverage they profess to despise. He’s fond of milking his connections when it suits. The emerging consensus about this once highly popular royal is that California is welcome to him.’[256]

After embarrassing the Queen, it appeared that Harry also targeted the Cambridges. Just after Kate and William met Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelensky, the Sussexes announced their contribution to a Ukrainian food charity.[257]

Harry and Meghan evidently believed they were winning the family war and dangled the prospect that they would not come to London in June for the jubilee because of ‘security issues’.[258] Palace officials feared Harry would repeat his refusal to attend the memorial service for Prince Philip at Westminster Abbey on 29th March because there was no armed protection. Harry was ‘unable to return home’, Schillings had told the Home Office, because it was ‘too dangerous’.[259] To placate Harry for the jubilee, Ravec agreed to provide special cars and protection. The Royal Family contributed about £160,000 for the Sussexes, their children, bodyguards and staff to fly on a twelve-seater Bombardier Global Express jet to Farnborough, thirty-five miles from London.

Agreeing the details of the Sussexes’ locations during the four days of celebration was also challenging. On the Queen’s orders, Harry was told to keep a ‘low profile’. Inevitably, he would not meet his brother. Nor could he wear a uniform. The Queen had also decided that he and Meghan would sit apart from the Royal Family for the Thanksgiving service in St Paul’s Cathedral – on the other side of the aisle, in the second row beside his cousins Beatrice and Eugenie. They would be invited to the reception in Guildhall afterwards, but Harry was told that the family would prefer they did not come. By ‘family’, Harry assumed William and Kate had objected.

During Trooping the Colour on Horse Guards Parade, Harry would be located with thirty minor royals in the Duke of Wellington’s office and could watch from a window. Afterwards, he would be invited for lunch at Buckingham Palace but again he was not expected to come. If he did, he would not stand on the balcony in view of the public.

In exchange, he and his family would meet the Queen in Windsor, a short drive from their home, Frogmore. For Harry, being with his grandmother was the prize he sought in order to reassert his credibility for both his book and the Netflix series.

London was lit by sunshine on Thursday 2nd June, the first day of the jubilee celebrations. Harry and Meghan showed no remorse as they came face to face with those they were to defame in the yet-still-unseen Netflix series and his book. Focused on promoting strife, regardless of the casualties, the couple appeared determined to destroy the magic of the Royal Family and sabotage William’s inheritance, the prospect of revenge and money suffocating any loyalties. ‘Frosty’ was one eyewitness’s recollection of the atmosphere between the Sussexes and their family.

Enabling herself to be seen by photographers during Trooping the Colour, Meghan pushed herself close to a tiny window. Hours later, the ailing Queen, suffering ‘mobility problems’, stood smiling on Buckingham Palace’s balcony surrounded by the Cambridges and their children, looking down on an adoring multitude along the Mall. The media was captivated by the Queen’s four-year-old great-grandson Louis clasping his hands over his ears as RAF jets swooped over the Palace. By then, the Sussexes were back in Frogmore. The image on the balcony of the monarchy’s secure succession for the next three generations would likely have been particularly irksome.

Sidelined, the Sussexes were ignored by the Royal Family the following day in St Paul’s Cathedral. The incapacitated Queen had stayed in Windsor. Visiting the monarch afterwards was the climax of the Sussexes’ visit. Harry needed photographs of himself and Lilibet with his grandmother. They would be gold dust for his book and TV series. But just as he was about to enter the room, a lady-in-waiting told Harry that ‘at Her Majesty’s request’ no photographs would be allowed. At the same time, several members of his family left the room. The chill remained until the Sussexes departed and drove back to Frogmore. After discreetly holding a birthday party for Lilibet, they returned to California.

Reconciliation had not been discussed. Few believed the Sussexes’ spokeswoman’s whisper that the Queen had invited the Sussexes to Balmoral in the summer.[260] More believed a family member’s warning. If Harry’s book was published during the Queen’s lifetime, there would be ‘no way back’. Nor, he was told, would he be forgiven if Netflix used any footage of the jubilee celebrations.

Members of the family also mentioned that the Archbishop of Canterbury, Justin Welby, had visited Frogmore. An insider reported that the Archbishop had said to Harry, ‘Sir, this is a difficult time for you and for them.’ After listening to Harry complain about unequal and unfair treatment, the cleric reported back to the family that both sides were ‘talking past each other’. Charles was not surprised. ‘There was a lot of anger thrashing around,’ said an advisor. Charles agreed: ‘It’s impossible to have a rational discussion with Harry.’

On his return to America, Harry called Moehringer. He said that despite his previous insistence, some poisonous exchanges between himself and Charles and William should be removed after all. ‘The hard bit was taking things out,’ Harry would later admit. ‘There are some things that have happened, especially between me and my brother, and to some extent between me and my father, that I just don’t want the world to know. Because I don’t think they would ever forgive me.’[261] Random House’s editors were irritated. There was no talk of the book being cancelled. Publication was set for the eve of Christmas.

CHAPTER 16

Archetypes

Returning to Montecito in an unforgiving mood, the Sussexes watched Liz Garbus’s latest edit of the six-part Netflix series – now simply titled, unoriginally, Harry & Meghan, which was scheduled to be released on 8th December 2022. Proud to be ‘woke’, Meghan had expected Garbus to portray her courageous ambition to champion injustices in society. Taking her cue from ‘Meghan the Warrior’, Garbus told the story of an innocent, loyal couple loved by the public but utterly traduced by white monarchists.

Garbus cast Meghan as the champion of human rights, egalitarianism, feminism and gender equality – her conviction that boyhood is ‘fluid’ and that boys should challenge masculinity. Above all, Garbus characterised Meghan as a leader of identity politics – against racism and exposing the oppression of black people [262] – and was encouraged to blame the Royal Family’s deep-rooted racial prejudice for the Sussexes’ flight from Britain. In Garbus’s version, Meghan’s racial background had influenced the Royal Family and Palace officials to deny her protection.

Posing as guilt-ridden – by his white skin and his racist family – Harry played into the hands of critics anxious to undermine Britain. To emphasise the Queen’s racism – as a direct descendant of racist slave traders – Harry did not object to Garbus ignoring the lifelong dedication of the Queen and Charles to embrace Britain’s minority races and the Commonwealth subjects as equals. Unaware of the circumstances, Harry allowed Garbus to prejudicially edit his grandmother’s pledge to the Empire and Commonwealth on becoming Queen in 1947 about dedicating ‘my life . . . to your service’.[263]

To boost the Sussexes’ arguments about the Royal Family’s racism, the Netflix producers recorded interviews with a black historian, Kehinde Andrews, and a mixed-race one, David Olusoga, and the anti-royalist, left-wing journalist Afua Hirsch. Hirsch had advocated the destruction of Nelson’s Column because the admiral was a white supremacist.[264] As an outright supporter of Black Lives Matter, Olusoga urged the demolition of all statues deemed to be tainted by slavery. In his Empire series for BBC TV, Olusoga presented a particularly negative opinion of British history. Aspects of Olusoga’s description of the British anti-Mau Mau campaign in Kenya during the 1950s was condemned in the Daily Telegraph as ‘untrue’, ‘ignores or falsifies basic truths’ and offering ‘a truly distorted account of the history’.[265] Similarly, Andrews believed, ‘The Royal Family is perhaps the most identifiable symbol of whiteness in the world’[266] and damned the Queen and her family for continuing to represent imperialism because the murals and statues in the royal palaces reeked of the profits from slavery.

According to Kehinde Andrews, the Queen was ‘the world’s number one symbol of white supremacy’.[267] ‘Nothing has changed’ since the end of the British Empire, said Andrews in the Netflix series, apart from the Royal Family’s ‘better PR’. ‘If you look at the black people in the Commonwealth,’ he said, ‘their conditions are almost just as bad as they were fifty and one hundred years ago.’[268]

In the minds of these historians whom the Sussexes had recruited, the Queen’s proudest achievement – the Commonwealth – was Britain’s secret ‘privilege club’ to protect its commercial interests. Their ‘independence’, granted in the 1960s, was a fallacy. Andrews highlighted a direct line from the slave trade to the Commonwealth. Renamed by him as ‘Empire.2’, it was supposedly a fig leaf for exploiting all black countries. Andrews ignored the inconvenient fact that the majority of the Commonwealth’s two and a half billion citizens are not black and that India’s economy has grown exponentially since 1948. Although every country is free to leave the Commonwealth, more nations have joined it, including Gabon and Mozambique, than chosen to opt out of it.

Harry could not understand that distortion is a familiar weapon, but Meghan did consciously support Andrews’s anti-whiteness. Archewell’s Black History Month, which she supervised, even suggested that her followers should read the philosophy of the controversial American Marxist Malcolm X.[269]

Andrews massaged the suggestion that every grievance suffered by Meghan could be blamed on her skin colour. All Britain’s media, said Andrews, were united against Meghan as ‘an angry black woman trope’.[270] The tabloids – or the ‘vultures’, according to Doria Ragland, Meghan’s mother – had driven Meghan to depression and suicide. But Andrews and Garbus failed to illustrate their assertion with a single article on a tabloid page. The newspaper reports about bullying her staff were not mentioned, nor was their accuracy disputed.

To reflect Meghan’s denunciations of the racist Royal Family, Afua Hirsch decried white royals as ‘awkward’ visitors to black countries. Her proof was the Cambridges’ visit to Jamaica in March 2022, during a Caribbean tour to celebrate the Queen’s jubilee, organised by Jamaica’s anti-monarchist government. The Cambridges were driven through the capital, Kingston, standing in an open-topped Land Rover. Wearing a white bemedalled uniform, William’s colonial image was inappropriate. According to the Jamaican government’s plan, their vehicle stopped near a field filled with children. Initially, the Cambridges walked over to shake children’s hands outstretched through a mesh fence. The optics indicated imperial privilege and racist Britain. After they realised the mistake, the Cambridges walked to the other side of the fence to meet the welcoming children. Perhaps unsurprisingly, Garbus didn’t use those shots of the Cambridges. Instead, to reflect Harry’s agenda to harm William as a modern monarch, Netflix included the cringe-making televised dressing-down of the Cambridges by Jamaica’s prime minister Andrew Holness. Jamaica, Holness told William, would vote to become a republic. Juxtaposing those images reflected the producers’ delight in hammering home Meghan’s condemnation of the Royal Family.

The climax was Meghan recounting her unexpected first meeting with the Queen during a drive in 2016 towards Windsor’s Royal Lodge. In the car, Harry had said that Meghan would need to curtsy. To dramatise her story to the camera, Meghan exaggerated her curtsy to the Queen as if both had featured in a medieval drama. Harry silently watched his wife mock his grandmother. ‘It was surreal,’ said Meghan with a mischievous glint. ‘I just thought it was a joke. I didn’t know what I was doing.’

In that sequence, she revealed her anti-monarchism, ridiculing any respect towards the Royal Family. One member of the Netflix film crew had wondered whether Harry would request the scene to be reshot to protect his grandmother. Another speculated that it would be entirely dropped. Neither happened. Instead, Harry commented in the film: ‘There’s a hierarchy of the family.’ Then, in rehearsed lines, he articulated a revelatory explanation about Meghan: ‘She sacrificed everything she ever knew. The freedom she had, to join me in my world. [In return] I sacrificed everything to join her in her world.’

For Meghan, one highlight of the series was the twenty hours of private videos given to Garbus. Whether those sequences were genuinely contemporaneous, the best of several reshoots or staged much later was impossible for viewers to know. A key sequence was allegedly filmed while Harry was at the Sandringham summit in 2020. Meghan had flown to her home on Vancouver Island two days before. ‘H is in London and I’m here,’ she said tearfully to the camera. ‘I don’t know where to begin.’ After adding that Harry was negotiating their options for leaving the family at Sandringham, she was next shown with a towel wrapped around her hair: ‘I just really want to get to the other side of this.’ There was a dramatic pause. Sitting motionless, she added emotionally, ‘I don’t know what to say any more.’ Filmed by an unnamed professional, its authenticity was questionable.

To sceptics, so much of their self-produced film was uncertain, not least their own judgement of credibility. To verify their complaint about persecution by the paparazzi, the Sussexes were shown nervously looking through the rear window of their moving car while being driven in California. Sitting in the back of a limousine, both were breathlessly narrating their escape from a paparazzo who was apparently pursuing them. Except, as Meghan eventually admitted, no one was chasing them. So much of their story proved to be self-invention.

‘People see me as a real-life princess,’ Meghan pronounced during the summer of 2022.[271] As the Sussexes conducted their assault on the Royal Family with the filming of their imminent Netflix series and Harry’s autobiography was being completed, Meghan continued her quest to establish herself as a global brand. Denied video footage of herself with the Queen, she seemed to want to be compared to Diana – relevant, revered and heroic.

‘So much of what Meghan is and how she is,’ said Harry supportively, ‘is so similar to my mum.’ Mentioning Diana usually silenced the critics. When Harry spoke about a photo of Diana with Nelson Mandela given to him by Archbishop Tutu or drew a comparison of the treatment of Meghan and Diana by the media and the Royal Family, he would say Meghan ‘shared’ his mother’s fate.[272]

Bizarrely, Harry said that he had believed, at one time, that Diana faked her death to escape the media. He spoke about an encounter with a leopard in Botswana as a ‘signal’ from Diana. He had also asked a psychic to contact his mother who reported Diana’s riposte, ‘I’m with Harry right now.’ Her son was ‘living the life she couldn’t’.[273] He introduced Meghan to his mother at her grave at Althorp, the Spencer family home, and he left Meghan to seek ‘clarity’ and ‘guidance’ by touching the gravestone. On Meghan’s insistence, Garbus included a sequence of Meghan showing Lilibet a photograph of ‘your grandmother’. Pertinently, she didn’t do the same with Archie.

After sober reflection, most dismissed the similarity between Diana and Meghan. Diana, a nineteen-year-old virginal aristocrat, was deceived by the prospect of blissful marriage and had once, after discovering the reality, genuinely attempted suicide by falling down a staircase. Even the aristocratic Diana Spencer felt isolated among the Windsors. Whereas Meghan, a 36-year-old divorcee, would have been able to calculate, after countless relationships, precisely the advantages of marrying a world-famous prince. Meghan’s forlorn attempt to equal Diana crumbled. Without Diana’s natural nobility, electric presence and genuine humanity, Meghan’s ambitions were even sparking descriptions of her as an imposter.

Without Diana’s natural advantages, Meghan needed to forge her own celebrity. Personal success, she knew, depended on separating her brand from Harry’s. Although she delivered the carefully rehearsed line that she and Harry were ‘like salt and pepper – we always move together,’ she planned in future to generate publicity focused on herself. The Netflix series would be their last joint media production. She would only appear with Harry at public events if it made sense for her own brand. Or as a walk-on part to reinforce her royalty. ‘You wanna come and say “Hi”?’ she had laughed at Harry during her fortieth birthday broadcast. Outside a window, the jester husband was seen juggling balls. And nothing more.

Launched in August 2022, Meghan’s first solo breakthrough was a twelve-part Spotify series called Archetypes, alias ‘Labels that try to hold women back’. By identifying the disparaging words attached to women, Meghan promised she would trace the origins of how stereotypes ‘shaped the narratives’ of women’s lives. She expected the series to persuade the world to recognise her worth. It was planned as a defining moment, establishing Meghan’s brand in the media as a brave, powerful, sophisticated, incisive heroic feminist. To those who told her she was ‘lucky [Harry] chose you’, Meghan retorted: ‘That’s a typical gendered archetype and stereotype’ – because ‘he was lucky I chose him’.

Keen to be ‘understood and seen’, she told Variety magazine during a promotional interview that her series broke down the ‘harmful’ labels attached to her. Listeners would reassess her as ‘a real person’ and easily recognise how she ‘laughs and asks questions and approaches things with curiosity’. The arduously rewritten template for Archetypes revealed her imagination: ‘I loved digging deep for intelligent, meaningful conversations with my diverse and inspiring guests, laughing and learning with them. It has been such a labour of love.’

But the enthusiastic team of women hired by Spotify and Archewell to produce the shows discovered the opposite. Four months into the project, the production team wilted. Weeks had been spent discussing with Meghan ‘a big theme that would explain the world’. Gradually they discovered that Meghan ‘backtracked on ideas’, ‘watered them down’ and then ‘had no ideas’.[274] As deadlines approached, eighteen months after signing the contract, Meghan panicked. Many celebrities she approached with handwritten invitations, including Taylor Swift, rejected the opportunity to star alongside her.

The team discovered that the actress ‘couldn’t turn the mic on and talk’. She was not a natural probing interviewer able to elicit revelations and headlines. Like most actors, Meghan could only deliver the lines written for her. During interviews, she focused on herself, unintentionally highlighting her disinclination for self-mockery. Believing that her fame transformed her into a world leader, she equated her marriage to a prince as an achievement as high as Serena Williams winning twenty-three Grand Slam singles titles. She was ill-equipped to discuss serious issues with genuine stars.

During the first eleven minutes of her first interview with Serena Williams, Meghan expounded on the challenges faced by a rich and successful woman. Female ambition, she complained, was equated with pushiness. Yet she was talking about criticism of herself rather than the great tennis champion.[275]

In Buckingham Palace, Meghan explained, ‘ambition is a terrible, terrible thing’. Williams patiently listened to Meghan blame the Royal Family for stifling her talents and potential. In her jargon – ‘that’s dimensionality’ – she explained the hardship of life as a duchess. Why, she asked rhetorically, should she have met the public during official duties without extra pay? Unpaid service was clearly not seen as a proper reward for years of struggle on the fringes of Hollywood.

To illustrate the perceived horror of Palace life, Meghan described how four-month-old Archie narrowly missed a nursery blaze caused by a malfunctioning heater during their 2019 tour of South Africa. ‘Everyone’s in tears, everyone’s shaken,’ recounted Meghan. And to her disgust, after the fire, she was forced by her staff ‘to leave Archie’ to complete the day’s visits. ‘This doesn’t make sense,’ she said.

In reality, Archie was nowhere near the room, was never in danger and there was no panic.[276] Her protest sat oddly with her self-description in the series of being ‘a working mom’. In the working tour of South Africa, a phoney alarm was not a reason to disappoint her hosts.

Her producers found Meghan’s pronouncements baffling, soon realising she had nothing original to say. There was no deep meaning to Meghan, they concluded. ‘It’s labels and no substance,’ complained one producer. Frustrated by her shortcomings, Meghan lashed out at her team. ‘She could be really, really awful,’ one producer told Vanity Fair. If ‘things didn’t go her way, some employees felt mistreated’. One employee disappeared for ‘long-term therapy’ and others took extended breaks. Their complaints were identical to those voiced by her Kensington Palace staff four years earlier – and vehemently denied by Meghan as a ‘calculated smear campaign on someone who has been the target of bullying herself’. Harry had cast the criticism as a Palace plot to depict his wife as a ‘tyrant’.[277] At the time, Meghan’s battles with the Spotify team were suppressed by non-disclosure agreements. Her employees feared the ultra-litigious Sussexes would ruin their careers.

The Sussexes’ threats were laced with contradictions. Meghan launched one Archetypes interview with a fulsome description of ‘her morning rush’ – how she got her children up, made breakfast and sent the children to school while also feeding ‘all three of the dogs’. Posing as the stereotypical American mother, she said repeatedly, ‘I love doing it.’ Then she read out a crafted observation: ‘How crushing the guilt of expectations can become.’

Hadley Freeman, the Sunday Times columnist, summarised the Duchess’s dilemma: ‘Meghan actually wants to be a celebrity without any sense of irony, given how much her own success exceeded her talents . . . Meghan is a product of her own era, in that she has the entitlement of a celebrity but the talents of a nobody . . . Against the odds she found her way to the royals, the perfect pedestal for a narcissist.’[278]

To fix Meghan’s brand, her publicist organised a series of interviews. The first was with Allison Davis, an African-American writing for The Cut, a New York magazine. Meghan assumed that the cover story, to be published on the twenty-fifth anniversary of Diana’s death, would be sympathetic. Despite telling Davis, ‘I don’t read any press,’ Meghan had carefully rehearsed her statements.

Before her marriage, Meghan had unsuccessfully tried to create an image of herself as a serious philanthropist. But in her groundbreaking interview in 2017 with Sam Kashner for Vanity Fair’s cover story, ‘Wild About Harry’, the writer had profiled an opportunistic actress. Meghan complained to the magazine’s editor. ‘I felt manipulated and betrayed,’ Kashner said afterwards.[279] Yet now, Davis’s treatment of Meghan was even more critical than Kashner’s. ‘At one point in our conversation,’ Davis wrote, ‘instead of answering a question she will suggest how I might transcribe the noises she’s making.’ Without the right words for her feelings, she was making ‘guttural sounds’ or ‘just moaning’.

During the interview, Meghan asked whether the journalist wanted ‘to know a secret’. Glancing around to ensure that no one would overhear this privileged information, Meghan revealed, ‘I’m getting back on Instagram.’ Davis derided Meghan for having ‘delivered a nothing with such gravitas’.[280]

Race might have united the two women, especially Meghan’s accusation that Britain’s tabloids were ‘calling my children the n-word’. Undoubtedly aware of the impact such a statement would have, Meghan alleged that she was treated as a ‘black woman’ for the first time after she began dating Harry. Until then, she had been treated as mixed race. Upping the stakes, she characterised herself to Davis as the hero of black women. Her wedding, she fantasised, had stirred the same ‘rejoicing in South Africa’s streets as when Mandela was released from prison’ in 1990.

Two years after leaving Britain, she revealed that her anger towards the Royal Family had not subsided. ‘Still healing’ from causing an ‘upset to the hierarchy’, she and Harry agreed that his family should ask for forgiveness. ‘I think forgiveness is really important,’ said Meghan. ‘It takes a lot more energy to not forgive. But it takes a lot of effort to forgive,’ she continued. The Royal Family faced a blood-curdling threat: ‘I’ve never had to sign anything that restricts me from talking. I can say anything.’ Revealing that she had kept a diary during her years in London, she gave a warning about her own autobiography: ‘I have a lot to say until I don’t. Sometimes, as they say, the silent part is still part of the song.’

Three weeks later, Meghan must have been flummoxed by Davis’s disobliging article, and why Davis did not respond to her appeal to the sentiment of two black women fighting the same cause? Her flattery had been wasted. Davis had laughed in the face of Meghan’s self-importance.

Meghan fired another shot. A few weeks before the launch of the Netflix series, Variety magazine’s cover story ‘Power of Women’ featured the Duchess. The high point would be her appearance at a Variety gala in Los Angeles. A hyped-up Meghan met the interviewer Matt Donnelly at the San Ysidro ranch, an expensive Montecito resort overlooking the Pacific owned by Ty Warner, a billionaire toy manufacturer, and somewhere Meghan had enjoyed eating before. Her bodyguards sat at a separate table. In her best performing style, Meghan patiently modelled a succession of outfits while charming Donnelly. Tasked to write positively about Meghan, Donnelly highlighted her ‘softness, playfulness, laughter and silliness’ and never questioned whether the relaxed, chatty actress was playing him as she ‘revealed’ her lifestyle. Of her family life she confessed: ‘We do feel joyful.’ As for so many Californians, ‘joy’ had become Meghan’s buzzword.[281]

Meghan’s ‘chapter of joy’ explained her new purpose in life. Invented by Meghan’s new hero, the bestselling Texan self-help author Brené Brown, the expression had been introduced to Meghan by the actress Mindy Kaling, who was close to Kamala Harris, the Californian lawyer and Democrat politician.[282] ‘Joy’ would also become the 2024 election campaign slogan of Vice President Harris, alias the ‘President of Joy’.‘Let us choose jooooy,’ screeched Oprah Winfrey at Harris’s election rally to show that the politics of joy underscored Harris’s authenticity – and Meghan’s.[283] ‘I think if you try to manufacture something like joy,’ said a Harris campaign manager, ‘it can go wrong because it’s fake. I think the reason why it’s resonating with people is because it’s authentic.’

The word ‘authenticity’, like ‘joy’, was often uttered by Meghan. The result was not always positive. In the London Times, Trevor Phillips wrote, ‘Today neither Meghan nor Harry can utter a word without provoking derision.’[284] An increasing number of Americans began to echo the British broadcaster’s scepticism.

Most Americans had accepted Meghan’s account to Oprah Winfrey about her rejection by a racist Royal Family. But one year later, the mood had changed. Meghan’s high expectations for her Spotify series and The Cut article had misfired. Among Americans who respected the Queen, Meghan’s star was waning. Singer Mariah Carey gently mocked Meghan as a ‘diva’.[285] A New York Post headline was unfriendly: ‘Toddler and Tiara: Spoiled Princess Meghan Still Whining about Royal Family’.[286] Kamala Harris’s campaign managers rejected Meghan’s offer of help, fearing a backlash.[287]

* * *

Harry hoped to reverse the increasingly disenchanted image of the Sussexes as an unending grievance machine. Appearing at the United Nations in New York on Nelson Mandela Day, there was so much for Harry to say. Spurred on by Meghan to generate global publicity, he linked Diana to South Africa’s statesman. Harry’s theme was Africa paying the price for decisions made by rich white countries. ‘Our world is on fire again,’ said Harry. ‘Our world needs to save humanity. How many of us feel battered, helpless in the face of the seemingly endless stream of disasters and devastation?’ With humanity allegedly on the verge of catastrophe, Harry directed his assault against the media. For ‘the few were weaponising lies and disinformation at the expense of many’.

Harry found an appreciative audience, but then the mask slipped. He equated the invasion of Ukraine with the recent US Supreme Court decision reversing Roe v Wade, the ‘constitutional right’ to abortion. Dressed in Givenchy in the front row, Meghan smiled as Harry attacked the Supreme Court judges for their ‘global assault on democracy and freedom’. Though indeed controversial, in reality the judges had ruled that instead of Congress in Washington DC, each state should individually decide its own abortion laws.

Hours later at a gala dinner in Rome, Samuel Alito, the American Supreme Court judge who wrote the abortion judgement, mocked Harry. How, asked the famous judge, could anyone connect his ruling with the Russian invasion of Ukraine? The answer, said the judge, was obvious. Only a multi-millionaire enjoying a remarkably privileged life could invent a link between abortion and the media. In Alito’s opinion, only a prince divorced from reality could similarly imagine that all Africans believed life was a burden.[288]

Oblivious to Alito’s criticism, Harry was pleased with his performance. After all, Meghan would have surely reassured him that the applause was genuine. It’s clear how badly Harry reacted to rejection. He was still bewildered why Spotify had declined his most recent proposal to interview global leaders deemed to be sociopaths. His proposed list of guests included Vladimir Putin about his ‘childhood traumas’, Donald Trump about his childhood, Pope Francis about fatherhood and Mark Zuckerberg about his life. Harry justified his proposal: ‘I have a very bad childhood trauma. Obviously. My mother was murdered. What is it about me that didn’t make me one of these bad guys?’[289]

The real mystery was why Harry imagined that Putin would agree to be interviewed, or whether Harry had even heard Trump’s description of him as ‘whipped’ and ‘an embarrassment’. Or did Harry recall Meghan damning Trump as ‘divisive’ and a ‘misogynist’? Rather than understand that only hard graft would land access to those personalities, Harry imagined that the world would comply with his wishes.[290] After disgruntled employees revealed Harry’s fantasies, his spokesman was ordered to ‘vehemently deny that Harry had ever made those proposals to Spotify’.[291] Insiders, though, were not surprised by Harry’s attitude towards the truth.

Anticipating the imminent Netflix series and the appearance of his book, Harry appeared to harbour no doubts about his righteousness. Streaming and publication would happen during the Queen’s life, despite the inevitable grief to be heaped on his 96-year-old grandmother. Harry’s disloyalty to his flesh and blood did not occur to him. Even during that week he warned a Los Angeles audience about a ‘sickness in politics’. As he described the selfishness of ‘service to others being sacrificed for personal gain’, he seemed unaware of his own culpability.[292]

In early September, the Sussexes flew to Britain for Meghan’s appearance at the One Young World conference in Manchester, followed by their dash to Düsseldorf for the Invictus Games. Then a brief stay in Frogmore before returning to California. Out of the Buckingham Palace loop, Harry had no idea about his family’s unfolding drama.

CHAPTER 17

The Funeral

Early on the morning of 8th September 2022, Charles was at Dumfries House in Ayrshire in Scotland, waiting for an American TV crew to set up their cameras for an interview he was doing on his expensive restoration project. A call told him that his mother was seriously ill. At 9.30am, he took off by helicopter towards Balmoral. Landing at his Birkhall home, which he had inherited from the Queen Mother, Charles drove across the Balmoral estate to the Queen’s bedside. Despite the graveness of the situation, Charles was satisfied that his mother was stable, so he returned to Birkhall.

Charles telephoned William and Harry with the news. He told both to head immediately to Northolt airport in west London. A jet would be waiting to take off for Scotland at 2.30pm. Just after 2pm, William was in the plane. Harry was still in Frogmore, arguing on the phone with his father.

Events in Frogmore after Charles’s first phone call followed a now predictable pattern. Both Harry and Meghan dithered. Meghan was unable to decide what to pack as suitable clothes to wear for Balmoral. Despite the confusion, she had managed to contact Sunshine Sachs’s Keleigh Thomas Morgan – in the middle of the night in Los Angeles – to organise a flash note to the media that both Sussexes were flying to Scotland. When Charles heard that Meghan intended to come, he called Harry. That was unacceptable, said Charles.

Harry, Charles recognised, was beyond his control. Not only as a free agent publicly rampaging against his family, but also risking millions of pounds in his court battles against the government and the tabloids. Harry’s explanations for his attacks were beyond Charles’s comprehension. Underlying Charles’s anger that fateful morning was his mother’s disappointment that the Sussexes had attacked the very institution which gave them so much. Since Meghan had refused the Queen’s invitations to Balmoral in the Queen’s lifetime, she was unwelcome at her death. Sharing his grief with Meghan, who maligned the monarchy, was unthinkable, said Charles. He believed that, to her dying day, his mother was shocked by Harry’s disloyalty.[293]

‘I will not tolerate it!’ Harry shouted at his father. ‘Don’t even think of talking like that about my wife.’[294]

Twenty-five years after Diana’s death, in the absence of any divided loyalties, his father’s trauma failed to tug any kindred emotions. Instead, Harry was preoccupied with Meghan’s insistence that she fly to Balmoral. At the family’s grief-stricken moment, on the eve of his grandmother being lifted into a coffin, Harry thought it was appropriate for Meghan to be welcomed by the people she had caricatured as medieval. Harry was outraged by Charles’s reaction: ‘He started to tell me his reasons but they didn’t make any sense at all. And it was disrespectful as well.’[295] Charles ended their argument by revealing that Kate would not be coming, so Meghan had not been picked on. Still fuming, Harry discovered that William, who was unwilling to wait any longer, had ordered the plane to take off.

Days later, Harry told a senior official that the plane’s departure ‘was not a cock-up but a deliberate snub’.[296] He claimed that his messages to William elicited no reply. William’s staff insisted that Harry had never contacted them.[297]

While picking mushrooms in the woods, Charles was alerted that, faster than the doctor had anticipated, the Queen was dying. He was still driving to Balmoral Castle when Edward Young called to deliver the news that the Queen had died at 3.10pm, signalling the end of a seventy-year reign.

William’s plane landed in Aberdeen at 3.50pm. Ninety minutes later, Harry took off in his own chartered jet to Aberdeen. As he flew north, his anger towards William mounted. Not only had his brother not waited, but as the new Prince of Wales he would receive £23 million every year from the Duchy of Cornwall and was a step closer to becoming the king. Then, Kate would be crowned queen, while Meghan remained a duchess.

The Queen’s death was announced to the world at 6.30pm. Harry received the news while in the air. On arriving at Balmoral, he heard that Charles, Camilla and William had gone to Birkhall for dinner and to sleep.On William’s insistence, Harry was not invited. He could not be trusted.[298] Princess Anne took Harry to see his grandmother’s body. Later, the two had dinner with his two uncles, Andrew and Edward. Early the following morning, Harry returned to London on a commercial flight. Asked about those circumstances four months later, Harry told CBS’s Anderson Cooper that he had not been given the first plane’s flight details. ‘I was not invited,’ he would tell American viewers.

The state funeral was set for 19th September. The Sussexes dithered and then decided to wait ten days in Frogmore. The image of them leaving – even temporarily – would have been damaging.

The nation’s grieving was interrupted three days later when William and Kate decided to meet the mourners gathered outside Windsor laying flowers. At the last moment, for the monarchy’s sake, William invited Harry and Meghan. With their feud being repeatedly mentioned by the media, he wanted to avoid any blame for excluding the couple. Meghan demanded time for her make-up, hair and to dress. Meeting in the castle, the two couples drove for three minutes together in silence to the gates. As they emerged, they barely looked at each other.

The crowd was ecstatic. The two couples split, each one engaging with people on one side of the road. Everyone focused on Harry and Meghan. Both performed to perfection, except when Meghan was seen to impatiently rebuff an aide trying to help with bunches of flowers. As they drove off after forty minutes, some speculated about a reconciliation, portraying the emotional scenes as ‘bringing Harry back in’ to re-bond with his devastated father. Another wrote that William and Harry ‘came together to close the gap’ in a ‘show of unity’ that they were ‘there for each other’.[299]

Those speculating about reconciliation would have had little knowledge of the true nature and impact of Harry’s and Meghan’s impending Netflix series and Harry’s book, so would have failed to grasp Harry’s and Meghan’s delight that the funeral added further authenticity to both projects. Nevertheless, as they drove back to Frogmore, Harry and Meghan were fuming. They had not been greeted by William and Kate on the terms they expected. Neither had embraced Meghan nor shown her sufficient respect. Kate had been cold. His family, Harry complained, showed ‘absolutely no willingness to reconcile’. They had been victims of ‘really horrible’ treatment.[300] Reportedly, Kate had told a senior royal that the walkabout was ‘one of the hardest things she’d ever had to do’.[301]

Over the following week, as the vast majority of Britons were emotionally struck by the dignity and honour of Britain’s traditions, endless tributes were paid to the flawless monarch who had devoted herself to serve her country and the Commonwealth. Detailed plans for the funeral were adjusted for the new circumstances, including Harry’s position and dress during the meticulous pageantry. In the course of repeated conversations with Palace officials, Harry agreed that he would not wear a uniform as he walked with William and their cousin Peter Phillips behind the team of horses pulling the Queen’s coffin on a gun carriage from Buckingham Palace to Westminster Hall for the lying-in-state. Military bands playing their haunting marching rhythms silenced those questioning Harry’s loyalty to an institution he was committed to injure, and whose fate now rested on his father, the new King.

Uniforms were important in Harry’s life. After more discussions, the Palace agreed that he could wear his while standing vigil for the lying-in-state in Westminster Abbey. On the same terms, he assumed, as the disgraced Andrew. Once the uniform was delivered, he discovered that the Queen’s cipher insignia – EIIR – had been removed from the shoulder. He protested. The reason was irrefutable: Harry was no longer a working royal. On arriving at Westminster Hall, he spotted that Andrew’s uniform still bore the insignia. He protested again. The answer was ready: whereas Harry had been ordered to return ‘all honorary military appointments’, at that time Andrew had returned only his ‘military affiliations’ but retained his appointment as the monarch’s aide-de-camp.

The new King resisted the temptation to strip the couple of their titles and declare Harry an outcast. His mother would not have approved. But he did disinvite the Sussexes from a Buckingham Palace reception before the funeral for heads of state and their representatives, a thousand guests. ‘Only for working royals,’ Harry was told.[302] Originally, the term had been invented to exclude the disgraced Prince Andrew from Buckingham Palace’s balcony. During the next few days, Charles sidelined his son’s insistence that he sign the letters patent – official, legal documents – to formally create his children, Archie and Lilibet Mountbatten-Windsor, as Their Royal Highnesses Prince and Princess. Charles also planned to amend the Regency Act, removing Harry’s status as a counsellor of state empowered to step in if the King was incapacitated. Without a British home, Harry would automatically lose his counsellor status.

While Harry fussed about his relations with his family, from Frogmore, Meghan reorganised her public relations set-up. Sunshine Sachs’s Keleigh Thomas Morgan resigned, along with Toya Holness. Neither could cope with Meghan’s demands. Christine Schirmer, an experienced communications advisor, was appointed Archewell’s media supremo.

Variety magazine agreed to delay publishing an interview they’d done with Meghan until after the Queen’s funeral. The magazine also approved an insertion into Matt Donnelly’s article. Originally, Meghan had not mentioned the Queen, just as she had ignored her when she was the guest editor of Vogue. Marrying into the Royal Family, Meghan believed, had been just a ‘chapter’ in her life.[303] Belatedly, though, she paid lip service to the Royal Family, having told Donnelly that the Queen was a ‘shining example of female leadership and I continue to be proud to have had a nice warmth with the matriarch of the family’.

Indignation was etched on Harry’s face as he entered the Abbey for the funeral service on 19th September. In Harry’s tribute to the Queen, whom he dubbed his ‘guiding compass’, the Prince quoted the Queen’s words after Philip’s death: ‘Life, of course, consists of final partings as well as first meetings.’ He concluded, ‘We now honour my father, in his new role as King Charles III.’[304]

Meghan drove to the funeral in Westminster Abbey with Sophie, the Countess of Wessex. The silent tension between the two women, both married to Windsors in the line of succession, reflected their mutual antagonism. In Meghan’s eyes, demure Sophie fitted the mould, seamlessly blending into the Royal Family. While Meghan, in Sophie’s opinion, always drew attention to herself by refusing to play any part other than one in her own script. But there was a twist. After launching her attacks, Meghan had not anticipated that the Royal Family would fight back.

In the abbey, the cameras’ view of Meghan was obscured by Vice-Admiral Sir Timothy Laurence, Princess Anne’s husband, and a giant candle. Similarly, no camera could show Harry and William in one shot or even with a pan. They were kept separate. Nothing happened by accident. Throughout the morning, Meghan blamed the family’s racism for the coolness towards her. Victimhood was Meghan’s religion, the justification for her aggression.

Seated in the second row, Harry was carefully scrutinised for clues about his state of mind. One reporter wrote that Harry had the ‘air of a tormented man’, albeit ‘without malign intent’, who finally realised his sacrifice for La La Land. ‘It looks as if he misses us, as we miss him,’ she concluded.[305] Another observed that grievance was etched on Harry’s face.[306] A few journalists noted that Harry failed to sing the national anthem with gusto. He sang through gritted teeth and completely stopped at ‘God Save the King’.[307] Nevertheless, in the aftermath, ‘sources’ hinted to newspapers that the King saw ‘tremendous flickers of hope’ for reconciliation.[308] All that speculation would prove to be mistaken. By the end of the month, the Sussexes had been ‘demoted’ to the bottom of the Royal Family’s website, below Princess Alexandra, a cousin of the Queen ranking fifty-sixth in the line of succession.[309]

After two weeks in Britain, the Sussexes left London without reconciliation. Neither heard the King’s first address to the nation: ‘I want also to express my love for Harry and Meghan as they continue to build their lives overseas.’ Typically, Charles shied away from confrontation.

The Sussexes flew to Los Angeles on a commercial flight after seeking a lift with Jill Biden on Air Force One. To avoid offending the Royal Family, the White House rejected their request. For the same reason, Jill Biden had also rejected Harry’s invitation to attend the Invictus Games in Holland.[310] Despite the snubs, the Sussexes could not risk damaging their relationship with the Biden family. So much of their fate in America depended on the Democrat support. Meghan assumed that Joe Biden’s dislike of British colonialism would cement their relationship.

Back in Montecito, Meghan contemplated the curtain-raiser to the Netflix series. ‘I learned so much about myself,’ Meghan disclosed, by not being ‘heard and understood’. Reacting to the Royal Family ignoring her during the funeral, she quoted a Greek poet Dinos Christianopoulos, ‘What didn’t you do to bury me? But you forgot that I was a seed.’[311]

Christine Schirmer was directed to resume the Sussexes’ plan of action. Shortly after Buckingham Palace released an official photograph of the new Royal Family – the King, Queen and the new Prince and Princess of Wales – the Sussexes released an official photo of themselves. Taken at the One Young World Summit in Manchester, it showed Meghan, dressed in red, staring sharply into the lens while Harry appeared somewhat awkward. No one in London misunderstood the message. No doubt intended, the battle of the photographs eclipsed Kate’s first public engagement in Scotland.[312] Relentlessly, Schirmer was told that the focus should be on the Sussexes.

Incensed by his treatment in London, Harry was more determined than ever to cause chaos. Contrary to media reports, he had no intention of approving any further cuts from his book. All sixteen language editions were ready for printing, and the audio and Kindle versions were under way. Billed in the advance publicity as ‘raw, unflinching honesty’, Spare’s publication had been planned while the Queen was alive. Potentially, her death reduced the book’s power of embarrassment. Either way, Harry appeared unconcerned by the effect it would have had on her reputation, even so soon after her death. ‘Hard-won wisdom about the eternal power of love over grief,’ was Harry’s promotional quote, reflecting his alleged professions of affection for his grandmother.[313]

CHAPTER 18

Protection

While the Queen lay in state in Westminster Hall, Harry had approved the details of his claim against Associated Newspapers, the owner of the Mail group.

Over the previous months, David Sherborne had been recruiting celebrities and other high-profile people to join the Prince in a joint action against the Mail for hiring private investigators to collect information illegally. Sherborne’s biggest catch was Baroness Doreen Lawrence, the grieving mother of Stephen, an 18-year-old black student brutally murdered in 1993 in south-east London by a gang of local white thugs. For four years, the murderers had been protected by corrupt and prejudiced members of London’s Metropolitan Police Service. The stalemate was broken in 1997 by the Daily Mail. In a bold front page, the newspaper named five men, each with a photograph, as the murderers. The floodgates opened. London’s police force was damned by an official inquiry and in 2012, two men were convicted of the murder. Doreen Lawrence became a Labour peer and, it seemed, was grateful to the Mail.

In January 2022, Harry sent Doreen Lawrence a text message saying there was ‘information’ she ‘would want to know about’. Days later, at Harry’s suggestion, she met Sherborne. Lawrence was told by the lawyer that two private investigators hired by the Mail had been ‘instructed to target Lawrence for “internal security”’. Sherborne showed Lawrence a statement allegedly signed by Gavin Burrows, a private investigator, in which Burrows admitted that he had been paid by the Mail group to illegally intercept her voicemail messages, itemised telephone bills and medical records. ‘I must have done hundreds of jobs between 2000 and 2005 for [a journalist] whilst he was at the Mail on Sunday,’ attested Burrows. In detail, he admitted to phone tapping and bugging cars and homes, including those of Harry, Doreen Lawrence, the actor Hugh Grant and other celebrities.

Sherborne showed Lawrence another statement signed by Harry: ‘I was told that Mr Burrows had been regularly commissioned by the Mail on Sunday to unlawfully obtain my private information by methods such as hacking telephones, obtaining credit card bills, tapping landlines, including my friend Guy Pelly’s.’[314]

The revelation, Lawrence said, had left her feeling ‘numb with anger’. She had suffered ‘a new trauma and injustice’.[315] On the basis of Harry’s endorsement of Burrows’s statement, Lawrence was persuaded by Sherborne that she could accuse the Mail of being ‘in bed with corruption and abhorrent criminal behaviour’ that had prevented all her son’s killers being jailed. Any doubts she might have harboured would have been quashed by Sherborne’s disclosure that she would be joining not only Prince Harry in the claim but also Elton John, and actors Elizabeth Hurley, Sadie Frost and Hugh Grant.[316] Burrows apparently admitted that those ‘were just a small handful of my targets’ for the Mail.

‘Appalling and utterly groundless’ and ‘preposterous’, thundered Associated Newspapers, the owner of the Mail group, in reply to Burrows’s claims. Harry and the others, said Associated, were relying on a self-confessed phone hacker. Burrows, continued Associated, had been recruited to Harry’s case by Jonathan Rees, a hacker convicted of attempting to pervert the course of justice and sentenced to seven years’ imprisonment, and by Graham Johnson, also convicted of phone hacking.

Harry and Lawrence were surprised by the next move. Associated presented them with a statement signed by the same Gavin Burrows denying that the statement flourished by Sherborne to Harry and Lawrence was authentic. Explicitly, Burrows denied that he had ever been employed by the Mail to gather information illegally against the claimants. Despite the fact the claimants’ team had insisted Burrows had signed the statement and understood its purpose, the ‘Burrows statement’ flourished by Sherborne was allegedly bogus.

Harry had become embroiled in unusually contentious litigation. Independent lawyers were appointed by Harry’s solicitors to sift through millions of pages in Associated’s commercial archives looking for evidence of payments to Burrows. Without a ‘money trail’, Harry’s case was difficult to prove. The projected cost of the trial was £38 million. Even before the first court hearing, Harry’s messages to Lawrence went ‘missing’ from both mobile phones. But that did not hamper their claims. Sherborne was certain that he could produce direct links between the Mail’s stories about the claimants and the Mail ’s payments for unlawful activities to private investigators. A total of £3 million, he claimed, was paid by the Mail group to private investigators. In Harry’s case, Sherborne produced fourteen articles in the Mail on Sunday offering intimate details about Harry in the Bouji nightclub and his relationship with Chelsy Davy. He claimed they were illegally sourced using bribes to BA employees when Davey would fly into London, and others. Denying that allegation, the Mail countered that their journalists mixed with Harry and his friends in the club, knew the club’s staff well and used legal, professional methods to get information from reliable sources.

Critics would say that Harry’s self-confidence had been exploited by his lawyers, pocketing millions of pounds in legal fees from successful claimants. Their activities, funded by Harry, re-emerged in a complaint to IPSO, the press standards watchdog.

Then Harry complained about a Mail on Sunday exposé of his alleged dishonesty relating to a series of wildlife photographs posted on Instagram. Those photos, reported the Mail, showed Harry standing bravely close to untethered elephants. But the Instagram photos were untruthful. They had been cropped to conceal restraining ropes around the elephants’ legs.[317] Harry’s hopeless complaint reflected his questionable judgement in pursuit of the media. It was rejected.

One defeat, though, did not dent Harry’s commitment. On the eve of the court hearings of his claims against the Mirror and Sun newspapers for their illegal activities, he was still confident of victory. After sifting through copies of the Mirror and Sun back to the mid-1990s, his lawyers had shown him over a hundred articles. Most he was reading for the first time. The more he read, the more annoyed he became. Even in the absence of any direct evidence, Harry’s lawyers claimed that any report which embarrassed Harry was obtained illegally. In Harry’s opinion, the media’s hostility justified his book and the Netflix series.

In California, Netflix chief Ted Sarandos knew he was on to a winner. The Sussexes are ‘great at getting attention’, he would chirrup.‘You may love them or hate them, but you’re watching.’ Naturally, Netflix had made elaborate plans for promoting the series in the run-up to December 2022. When the company’s publicists had checked on the future arrangements of William and Kate they had discovered a heavenly gift. The couple were due to be in Boston on 30th November for a three-day visit to launch The Earthshot Prize, their annual £1 million prize for green visionaries and environmentalists. President Biden was among the guests listed to greet the couple in the home town of the Kennedys, America’s own royalty. The Sussexes planned a rival tour in New York.

William’s staff wearily anticipated the Sussexes’ sabotage. Harry and Meghan had attacked the Royal Family on ITV in 2019, just as William and Kate undertook a sensitive visit to Pakistan. Subsequently, most official announcements of any event involving the Cambridges were followed within hours by a counter from Montecito. But no publicist in New York and Los Angeles anticipated the bonus presented in London on 30th November.

At a Buckingham Palace reception for victims of sexual violence hosted by Queen Camilla, Lady Susan Hussey, an 83-year-old lady-in-waiting for the previous sixty-two years had as usual welcomed the guests, discovered their background and decided whether to steer Camilla towards the visitor.

In the crowded, noisy room, the hard-of-hearing widow approached 61-year-old Ngozi Fulani. Looking at the woman dressed in a flamboyant, colourful African national costume, Hussey asked, ‘Where do you come from?’ Over the previous decade, Hussey had asked the same question countless times. Unable to understand or possibly hear Fulani’s answer, Hussey moved her hair to read the name badge. Eventually, Fulani explained she was originally from north London and had been born as Marlene Headley. Clearly puzzled, Hussey again asked, ‘Where do you really come from?’ Fulani did not mention that she had travelled to Buckingham Palace by train from Peckham in south London. Nothing more was said until the early hours of the following day.

On Twitter, Fulani accused Hussey of racism. By asking ‘Where are you really from?’, wrote Fulani, Hussey was guilty of a ‘form of abuse’. Moving her hair had aggravated the insult. ‘I think it is essential to acknowledge that trauma has occurred,’ she tweeted. Before daybreak, Fulani had embarked on a mass-media tour without any journalist questioning her version of events. Hussey’s racism was not doubted. Rather than wondering whether Hussey had been set up, the media frenzy endlessly rebroadcast Fulani’s suggestion, ‘Why don’t we re-educate [Hussey]?’

Buckingham Palace was gripped by panic. The epitome of ‘white privilege’ – the royal household – had been categorised by a self-proclaimed victim as prejudiced and guilty.[318] Just as he was leaving for Boston, William was told about the furore. He was alarmed. The public would assume that Harry’s and Meghan’s accusation about institutional racism within the Royal Family was true.

Instead of either Edward Young or Clive Alderton summoning a meeting to agree a riposte lamenting a devoted, deaf, elderly woman misunderstanding an esteemed guest, they remained paralysed. None of William’s advisors questioned Ngozi Fulani nor considered that Hussey regularly attended a Southwark church where the majority of the congregation was black. Instead of supporting Hussey, his godmother who was beloved by King Charles, William bowed to the Sussexes’ scenario. If the Palace failed to issue an immediate grovelling apology, he calculated, his visit would be endangered. Five hours after Fulani’s first broadcast, Hussey was fired. Sixty-two years of loyal service was ignored. ‘Racism has no place in our society,’ said William’s spokesman.

Two days later, on a bitterly cold day, the Waleses hosted a glittering reception in Boston’s MGM Music Hall. Presented as ‘powerbrokers’ and ‘changemakers’, the Waleses were welcomed by large crowds. But even the presence of President Biden, the former Secretary of State John Kerry, the Republican senator Mitt Romney, plus Annie Lennox, Ellie Goulding and the surprise arrival of David Beckham, could not drown the impact of Netflix’s trailer to the six-part series, expertly timed for release just after the Waleses’ grand entrance.

‘It’s about hatred; it’s about race,’ said Netflix’s narrator – Prince Harry – with undisguised aggression. Over shots of hard-faced William, scowling Kate and saintly Meghan in Westminster Abbey in 2019, Harry issued a declaration of war: ‘No one sees what’s happening behind closed doors.’ Cut to Meghan: ‘Unfortunately, in us standing for something, they are destroying us.’ Over a burst of piano music, Harry added with menace, ‘This isn’t just about our story. This has always been so much bigger than us. No one knows the full truth. We know the full truth.’

Cut to Meghan in an armchair apparently crying. On the eve of her wedding, she was already a victim of racism: ‘Truth be told, no matter how hard I tried, no matter how good I was, no matter what I did, they were still going to find a way to destroy me.’ Standing beside a £2,000 Hermes blanket, Meghan sobbed. ‘I had to do everything to protect my family,’ continued Harry over shots of the Royal Family. To ‘destroy’ Meghan, he said, Buckingham Palace had planted ‘salacious stories’ in the media. The ‘dirty game’ was confirmed by Schillings’ lawyer Jenny Afia: ‘There was a war against Meghan to suit other people’s agendas.’ The accusation was repeated by an American entrepreneur, Christopher Bouzy: ‘It’s about hatred, it’s about race.’

Cut to Meghan: ‘When the stakes are this high, doesn’t it make sense to hear our story from us?’

The core of the Sussexes’ complaints was the sequence illustrating Harry’s obsession with a ‘conspiracy’ to destroy Meghan headlined, ‘Exploitation and Bribery Between our Family and the Media’. The Sussexes accused the media of publishing poisonous falsehoods. Garbus and Netflix had ordered picture researchers to scour the newspaper and film archives for dramatic proof of the media’s malicious dishonesty towards the Sussexes. The result was a trailer created from sequences of misrepresentations.[319] Shots purporting to be Harry and Meghan pursued by the paparazzi were actually cameramen filming the British model and media personality Katie Price at Crawley Magistrates Court a year after the Sussexes had left Britain.[320] Harry’s voice accusing British newspapers of ‘outright racism’ was illustrated by a newspaper headline ‘Princess in Crisis’ lifted from the National Enquirer’s false claim in 2010 that Kate Middleton was an alcoholic.[321] The images of jostling photographers persecuting the Sussexes was actually footage taken at a 2011 Harry Potter film premiere before the Sussexes had met. Garbus’s illustration of the Sussexes suffering the media’s persecution was images of chaos shot in May 2019 outside the house of Michael Cohen, Donald Trump’s former lawyer, as he was about to leave for prison.[322] Without offering any evidence, Meghan’s friend Lucy Fraser, posing as a PR consultant, denounced the media for ‘going through rubbish bins’ and Harry’s and Meghan’s bank accounts.

In one genuine sequence of Harry leading Meghan away from popping flashbulbs, Harry spoke of the ‘pain and suffering of women marrying into this institution . . . I don’t want history to repeat itself.’ The video was recorded in 2018 at the peak of ‘Meghan Mania’. The American was surrounded by loving crowds.

In a promotional statement, the Sussexes said, ‘We hope [the series] helps others to heal, and to feel inspired.’ Curiously, though, despite all this, Meghan had told Variety magazine that the series was ‘not the way we would have told it’.[323]

Liz Garbus appears to have performed one more favour for the Sussexes. Her professional partner, Rory Kennedy, was the sister of Kerry Kennedy. Both were the daughters of Robert F. Kennedy, the Attorney General assassinated in 1968 and the brother of President John F. Kennedy. Every year, Kerry Kennedy, a human rights activist, hosted a gala in New York to announce the Robert F. Kennedy Ripple Award, recognising an ‘exemplary leader’ demonstrating an unwavering commitment to ‘protect and advance equity, justice and human rights’. Previous winners included Archbishop Desmond Tutu and the Clintons. The winners in 2022, besides the Ukrainian leader Volodymyr Zelensky, were the Sussexes. Kerry Kennedy explained that after watching the Oprah Winfrey interview, she wanted to reward the Sussexes for challenging the Royal Family’s ‘power structure’ and branding the Royal Family’s institution as endemic with ‘structural racism’.[324]

Conveniently, the New York gala at the midtown Hilton would be held just two days after The Earthshot Prize and two days before the Netflix series was streamed on 6th December. Hosting the ceremony would be Alec Baldwin, the Hollywood actor and director recently charged with accidentally shooting dead a female cinematographer.

As a five-year-old, Meghan had told her father about her ambition to walk on the red carpet. She wanted to make her mark. Her appearance at the Kennedys’ New York gala would be another opportunity to relaunch herself. Harry had Invictus and Sentebale, and Netflix had commissioned a series on polo. She had not yet come up with anything new. The Ripple Award was her opportunity to be anointed as a civil rights hero by the Democrats’ own royal family.

Arriving in New York on a private jet funded by the charity, the long process of selecting her clothes had produced a stunning effect. Meghan wore an ivory off-the-shoulder dress with long sleeves and a skirt with a front split custom-made for her by Nicolas Ghesquière. It was strikingly similar to Kate’s gown, worn days earlier in Boston. Her jewellery was capped by shimmering diamond drop earrings and an aquamarine cocktail ring owned by Princess Diana. Over a hundred journalists and a slew of cameramen were waiting in the rain as Meghan emerged from the limousine in mid-Manhattan. Harry instantly made the news by opening an umbrella as he nervously escorted the star towards the entrance.

‘What do you think about destroying the Royal Family, Meghan?’ shouted a heckler. ‘Are you putting money before family?’ yelled a journalist.

Ignoring the sour notes, the couple entered a small room to parade for the journalists and photographers. Eyes beaming with every hair in place and her dress perfectly hung, Meghan held her rictus smile for four minutes then swept out. Unlike many stars who disappoint in real life, both behaved like royals. Their charisma was genuine.

Inside the ballroom, over 75 Kennedys and about 1,500 guests paying a minimum of $2,500 a ticket were awaiting the Sussexes. Those guests with guaranteed access to the couple had paid $410,000 for the privilege. Among the eager diners was Robert Couri Hay, a celebrity gossip columnist. ‘It was a hot ticket,’ he burbled. ‘A sell-out. Harry and Meghan were hot and fresh in America. They reinvigorated the gala – created quite a stir. It was an electric atmosphere and Harry and Meghan milked it for all its worth.’[325]

On stage, Kerry Kennedy introduced the prize winners as ‘heroes’ for leaving Britain: ‘They embody moral courage. They went to the oldest institution in UK history and told them what they were doing wrong. They couldn’t have structural racism in the institution. They knew that there would be consequences, that they would be ostracised, they would lose their families, their position and that people would blame them for it. They did it because they believed that they couldn’t live with themselves if they didn’t question this authority.’

Referring to Bobby Kennedy, she praised the Sussexes’ ‘moral courage – the one essential, vital quality’, according to her father ‘for those who seek to change a world that yields most painfully to change’.

Harry was allowed the first words: ‘We don’t get out much these days because our kids are small and young, so this is quite unexpected. I’ll be honest with you, Kerry – I thought we were just going on a date night, so I found it quite weird that we’re sharing the room with 1,500 people.’ Amid the laughter, he smartly moved to the side. Centre stage was Meghan, the star of the show. As Meghan took the microphone, the slick actress proved herself a master of presentation. ‘Harry looked at Meghan like she was ice-cream,’ noted Hay. ‘He was awestruck by her.’

Meghan’s audience was similarly gripped as she spoke about the horror of the Royal Family’s racism: ‘I just didn’t want to be alive any more.’ That night, racism was the cause of her attempted suicide. Huge applause followed her denunciation. She was revealing her misery, she continued, ‘because I don’t want anyone to feel alone’.

In her feminist mode, Meghan announced the Archewell Foundation award for activist film-makers promoting gender equity. Thunderous applause, and the Sussexes circulated amid unquestioning admirers.

After they left the hall, Baldwin was asked whether he thought the Royal Family was racist. ‘No, no, no, no,’ he replied.[326] A few Americans were equally dubious about the award. ‘I find it somewhere between sublimely ridiculous and blatantly ludicrous,’ said Professor David Nasaw, a biographer of Joseph Kennedy. ‘It’s absurd.’ Another critic wrote: ‘You’ve turned the award and the organisation into a farce and laughing stock. Your father will be turning in his grave with this misuse of his name.’[327] Those critics were the exception. Like Robert Couri Hay, most were ecstatic.

Two days later, the Netflix series aired and broke all records for first-day audiences: 2.4 million people watched it in Britain while globally, the audience was eventually estimated at 49 million. The Sussexes were delighted. The Royal Family had been torpedoed.

Inevitably, some commentators carped about the ‘Spoiled Princess’, the ‘Petulant Princess’ and the ‘Montecito Malevolents’.[328] Others noted that no major stars like Oprah Winfrey, Elton John or the Obamas supported the Sussexes in the series. ‘They left the UK to be their authentic selves,’ observed the Daily Mail. ‘And true to themselves, the Netflix series is a performance. They want to remain in the spotlight.’[329] On CNN, Peggy Drexler identified the Sussexes’ ‘fatal flaw’ as ‘thinking they can control how others see them’. There was, she thought, ‘little to change people’s minds about them. It’s self-promotional, self-aggrandising and, frankly, a little boring. They do not come off as more likeable. Notably, it’s perhaps the first time that much of the dislike is directed towards Harry, instead of just Meghan.’[330] The journalist Barbara Amiel noticed how Harry ‘pouts that he hates media attention’ but the six-part series was only about ‘earning millions of dollars’ by standing in the spotlight.[331] The result, said Piers Morgan, was ‘greedy, ruthless, two-faced nonsense’.[332] Variety joined the negative camp. Under the headline ‘It’s Well Past Time for Harry and Meghan 2.0’, the media analyst Andrew Wallenstein wrote, ‘There can only be so many revelations left to share with the public. Given that they’ve beaten this horse to death, perhaps this one-trick pony is due for the glue factory.’[333]

In London, officials had organised a show of force. In Buckingham Palace, Charles and Camilla hosted a glittering reception for the diplomatic corps. Earlier on the same day, Charles had been sitting cross-legged at a Sikh temple promoting the importance of religious and racial unity. Days later, twenty members of the Royal Family paraded into Westminster Abbey for a service of thanksgiving of the late Queen’s life with a congregation of 1,800 voluntary workers. In his sermon for his Christmas Concert, also in the abbey, William praised the ‘spirit of togetherness’. Christ, he said, was born ‘to serve, not to be served’.[334] William was undoubtedly smarting from Harry’s accusation in a TV interview that ‘without question’ William had approved the release of Knauf’s memo to The Times. Single-handedly, said Harry, William had broken their ‘pact’.[335]

The Netflix series did not improve the Sussexes’ reputation in Britain. Only 17 per cent of those polled sided with Meghan and Harry, while 44 per cent were sympathetic to William and Kate. A mere 11 per cent thought the Sussexes had been forced out of Britain and 19 per cent thought they deserved an apology.[336] Clutching at those straws, Buckingham Palace dismissed the Netflix series as ‘not as damaging as we feared’ because the Sussexes had ‘overplayed their hand quite badly’. But tellingly, 26 per cent of Britons agreed that the Royal Family was racist, while 51 per cent thought the Sussexes should be invited to the coronation.[337]

Constitutionally, Charles needed Harry in Westminster. The Royal Family could not be seen as fractured. Despite William’s fears that Harry and Meghan would stage an attention-seeking stunt, the Sussexes were informally invited.[338] Harry refused to commit himself. The demands that he appear in civilian clothes, stripped of his uniform and medals and play no part in the ceremony, he told the Palace emissary, were unacceptable.

More important to Harry was his family issuing a ‘formal apology or taking responsibility or accountability’. Before committing to the coronation, his spokesman continued, the Sussexes wanted to ‘sit down with the Royal Family’ and ‘address’ their issues. In Harry’s ultimatum, ‘the ball is in the Palace’s court.’[339] Neither of the Sussexes believed they owed an apology for anything. Both assumed they would dictate events.

‘My wife and I, we’re moving on,’ said Harry. ‘We’re focused on what’s coming next.’[340] But the Sussexes were not ‘moving on’. To boost sales of Spare, due to be published in January, Harry had agreed to four TV interviews. One more blast, he calculated, and then his family would seek forgiveness.

Christmas Day in Montecito was quiet. With their children and Meghan’s mother Doria, the Sussexes entertained a neighbouring couple for lunch. By contrast, Charles hosted a party of over forty members of the family at Sandringham, including for the first time Camilla’s children, Sarah, the Duchess of York, with her daughters and Andrew, plus his sister Anne and brother Edward, his cousins, their children and their grandchildren. In a display of unity to the world, Charles sought to confound Harry’s jibe that the Windsors were dysfunctional. Unlike his mother, Charles spared no expense to offer good food and wine. Charles’s recorded TV Christmas message praised health workers, highlighted the good work by William and Kate, and didn’t mention Harry.

CHAPTER 19

Publication

The publication party for Spare in Santa Barbara was unusually low key. Hosted by ‘friends’ of the Sussexes, very few of the Random House staff dedicated to the book’s editing and production in Manhattan were invited. Most were not even aware of the party until after the event.

Amid all the arguments and delays, the mood was not particularly celebratory for a book which on its first day sold 1.43 million copies and would sell 3.2 million in the first week. Penguin Random House had expected the book to be ‘big’, but not for it to be ranked as history’s fastest selling non-fiction book. Although it was not what the editors had originally imagined, no one could dispute the book’s essential qualities: a gripping page-turner packed with a global celebrity’s intimate revelations.

At the party, no one suggested Harry write a second book. Moehringer in particular did not volunteer for another round. However, no one could accuse Harry of not reading his own book – a credible truth about many ghosted autobiographies. Harry slowly read his book’s audio version, lasting fifteen hours and thirty-seven minutes. The listener heard the multitude of slurs against his family in his own voice.

Among the surprises at the party was Meghan’s reticence. Months earlier, she had disappeared during Harry’s promotional tour. In the early stages of resurrecting her commercial brand, she had accepted advice that she must shed the image of a sour duchess. Partly on the advice of Adam Lilling, the founder of Plus Capital, a ‘partner to the world’s top influencers’, she planned her resurrection as a positive-thinking Californian entrepreneur. Her ambition was for huge wealth and, with that, presumably to stop appearing to be scrounging for rides on private jets. Therefore, she could no longer be associated with Harry’s attack on the Royal Family.

To unveil her money-making spectaculars, she filed an application to revive The Tig, her old blog, a ‘hub for the discerning palate’ targeting those with ‘a hunger for food, travel, fashion and beauty’.[341] She would negotiate with Netflix to produce ‘fictional, scripted content’, especially light-hearted romcoms. And documentaries too, like the Obamas’ award-winning American Factory, a searing account about a Chinese-owned factory in a depressed Ohio town. Planning a feminist spin-off of Charles Dickens’ Great Expectations, she would announce the hiring of Tracy Ryerson as head of scripted content supported by Nishika Kumble.

One blip was familiar. Mandana Dayani, Archewell’s chief of staff, resigned after only eighteen months, followed by Rebecca Sananes, who had been in charge of Meghan’s podcasts. Unable to find replacements, Meghan declared that the Sussexes would take a ‘leadership role’ though she would remain ‘invisible’.[342] To remedy the latest twist, the Archewell Foundation paid £90,000 to Katie McCormick Lelyveld’s PR company[343] for ‘strategic support for social impact PR’. Lelyveld had worked for Michelle Obama as press chief from 2007 to 2011 and previously for Hillary Clinton.[344]

Random House assigned a team of publicists to accompany Harry to the TV interviews. Guided by those advisors, he focused on his moral ambition. ‘This is not about trying to collapse the monarchy,’ he said. ‘This is about trying to save them from themselves.’ His cause, he would repeat, was to reform the monarchy for the sake of his brother’s children. Like him, two would be ‘spares’ – ‘And that hurts. It worries me.’ Quite how describing his frozen penis, sex with a woman in a field and making faces at a hapless school assistant would help Charlotte and Louis was not explained.[345] The book, Harry was briefed to say, was important for ‘historical fact and significance’.

However, everyone recognised Harry’s limitations, not least that many of his accusations would be contested.[346] In anticipation of a challenge to his credibility, Moehringer had inserted into the text Harry’s thanks to his ghostwriter for speaking ‘so often and with such deep conviction about the beauty (and sacred obligation) of memoir’. To add heft, Moehringer had quoted an American essayist Mary Karr: ‘The line between memory and fact is blurry, between interpretation and fact.’ In Moehringer’s words, Harry’s fantasy was just as credible as the truth, just as Harry had said: ‘My memory is my memory and there’s just as much truth in what I remember and how I remember it as there is in so-called objective facts.’ Personal memories and past events could be revised to suit his purpose. Neither Moehringer nor Harry apparently acknowledged the existence of the irrefutable truth.

Forgetting how he blamed the Palace for failing to protect Meghan from media distortion, Harry narrated a promotional video of Spare featuring shots of Nelson Mandela. The South African, claimed Harry, inspired the Netflix series and his own autobiography. Instantly, Mandela’s granddaughter Nikola criticised Harry and the publishers for having ‘stolen my grandfather’s quotes and legacy because they know his name sells’.[347] Harry, his publicists noticed, was puzzled by her criticism. Surely, he said, Mandela would approve of his performance?

During the week of publication, two interviews were arranged at the San Ysidro Ranch in Montecito. Anderson Cooper would put the questions for CBS (secured thanks to Meghan’s relationship with Oprah Winfrey) and ITV’s Tom Bradby arrived from London.

There was a genuine warmth when Harry and Bradby met. Even before the camera began recording, there was a certainty about Harry’s conviction. He had waited years for the moment to turn the tables on the media. Newspapers, he demanded, should depict him approvingly on his own terms. For his part, Bradby knew that his own credibility depended on asking some tough questions.

Among the most important issues was Harry’s and Meghan’s revelation to Oprah Winfrey about the Royal Family’s anticipation of the colour of Archie’s skin. In the filmed interview with Bradby, Harry bluntly denied that he or Meghan had accused the Royal Family of racism. ‘The press said that,’ he told Bradby. Asked again whether he had accused family members of racism, Harry replied: ‘No, I didn’t.’ At worst, he said, the Sussexes had accused his family of ‘unconscious bias’. Viewers recalling Meghan’s detailed answers to Oprah Winfrey would be puzzled whether Harry genuinely believed his version. After all, the previous week in New York, he had heard Meghan utter exactly the same accusation of the Royal Family’s racism. His only consistency was refusing to name the family members who had raised the subject.

Fired up, Harry turned the tables. He accused the British media of racism – proven by their ‘absolutely horrendous’ reports about Susan Hussey whom ‘Meghan and I love’ (though Meghan’s Kensington Palace staff recalled the Duchess’s dislike of Hussey). And William, said Harry, had ‘thrown her under a bus’.[348] Harry forgot that Ngozi Fulani had started the campaign against Hussey on Instagram.

William’s sin, said Harry, was to authorise his staff to deliberately ‘trash’ his and Meghan’s reputations. Along with Buckingham Palace, his brother and father fed the tabloids with lies to ‘create as much conflict as possible’. His family was ‘complicit’ in causing the ‘pain and suffering’ inflicted on Meghan. He explained, he had ‘written’ the book as a tool to ‘protect’ himself.

After announcing his willingness to forgive, he told Bradby that he was amazed how his family ‘feel as though it’s better to keep us somehow as the villains . . . They’ve shown absolutely no willingness to reconcile. They haven’t said a single thing.’ His family, he complained, had not admitted their mistakes. Once his family felt accountable, they should apologise to him and Meghan and ask for ‘forgiveness’ – which was ‘a 100 per cent possibility’.[349] He added mournfully, ‘It never needed to be this way. I would like to get my father back. I would like to have my brother back.’

Displaying a lack of self-awareness, Harry was asked by Bradby what he would say to William. ‘What I have to say to them will be in private,’ Harry replied without any irony. ‘None of this is done with the intention of hurting any of my family.’ He had written nothing that was ‘scathing’.[350] Harry clearly suffered no guilt about his betrayal.

Towards the end of his interview, Bradby told Harry that many Britons wished he would ‘shut up and stop talking’. Harry looked puzzled: ‘Stop talking about what?’ he asked.

Besides his damning accusations against Charles, William and Kate, Harry targeted Camilla. In his book, Harry accused Camilla of leaking to the media her first meeting with William.[351] Moehringer or his fact-checker could easily have discovered that Harry’s accusation was untrue. Camilla’s assistant had indiscreetly told her husband, a Times journalist, about the meeting and resigned in embarrassment. More accurately, Harry accused his father of hiring a skilled publicist to cultivate the public image of Camilla as his future wife.

Most of his bile about Camilla had been removed from the manuscript, except how he had begged his father not to marry Camilla.[352] But in his interview with Anderson Cooper, Harry could not resist. Camilla, he said with relish, was ‘dangerous. She was the villain. She was the third person in the marriage.’ Ruthlessly, he said she had pursued Charles and the Crown. To rehabilitate her image, said Harry, Camilla had gone to ‘bed with the devil’ – she ‘traded information’ with the tabloids and ‘bodies were left in the street’.[353] The principal ‘body’, he believed, was himself. Harry was firing at sitting ducks. Whatever he said, he knew that neither Camilla nor the other royals would retaliate. For the good of the monarchy, they believed, silence was their only option.[354]

Asked by Cooper why, given the animosity, the Sussexes didn’t renounce their titles, Harry replied, ‘And what difference would that make?’

Even then, the Prince had not grasped his wife’s strategy of commercially exploiting her royal status. To those who suggested that Meghan’s soul was bent on fame and fortune, Harry snapped, ‘That’s a distorted narrative.’[355] Their move to California, Harry said with certainty to CBS, was not motivated by making money: ‘We were dedicated to a life of service, as is proven by everything that we’re doing now with the work that we do.’ Although Harry knew that Meghan was setting up websites as the ‘Duchess of Sussex’ to sell food and clothes, he remained reassured that their lives were dedicated to philanthropy.

The morning after Cooper’s interview was broadcast, Harry reappeared on CBS’s Good Morning America. Overnight, Harry had been persuaded that attacking Camilla was an error. Despite her being a marriage wrecker, he told the morning’s audience, ‘I have a huge amount of compassion for Camilla. I don’t look at her as an evil stepmother.’ But, he admitted, they had not spoken for a ‘long time’.

‘Nothing that I’ve done in this book,’ Harry said with a straight face, ‘has ever been with any intention to harm or hurt [the Royal Family].’ Echoing Archewell’s website, he was ‘leading the way with compassion’.[356] Whether Harry genuinely believed those sentiments was impossible for the viewer to decide. He gave no hint of love for any member of his family. Asked to justify publishing his memoir, he replied with certainty: ‘I have thought about it long and hard and as far as I can see it, the divide couldn’t be greater before this book.’

In a hitch to the carefully managed publication plan, Spare had been prematurely released in Spain. Working their translators at breakneck speed, the British tabloids filled up to ten pages every day with Harry’s accusations and revelations. Among the most sensational was his description of killing twenty-five members of the Taliban like ‘chess pieces’ or ‘Bads taken away before they could kill Goods’. His revelation was denounced in Britain. ‘This is not how we behave in the army,’ said Colonel Tim Collins, famous for his inspirational speech on the eve of the 2003 invasion of Iraq. ‘It’s not how we think. He has badly let the side down.’ Harry’s revelations, Collins told Forces News, were ‘clearly a tragic money-making scam to fund the lifestyle he can’t afford and someone else has chosen’. Collins went further. Harry was accused of not only being racist but ‘has now turned against the other family – the military – that once embraced him, having trashed his birth family’.[357]

The senior officer’s criticism stung Harry. He had not anticipated any repercussions. His reaction was familiar. In reporting his own words, he told his TV interviewer, the media had perpetuated ‘the most dangerous lie they ever told’. His revelation of killing twenty-five Taliban had been twisted, he said. The British press, he continued, was guilty of endangering his family by exposing the Sussexes to Islamic terror.[358] In Harry’s world, he could never do wrong. Even accurately repeating his own words was proof of the media’s bad intentions.

Twenty-four hours after Spare was published, Harry received a message from Buckingham Palace that on King Charles’s orders he was expelled from Frogmore. His description of Camilla as ‘evil’ was arguably the final straw. The eviction remained a secret. Incandescent, Harry called his father urging that the expulsion be revoked. Having failed to speak to his father, he was told that the £2.4 million for renovations would be repaid to the Sussexes.[359] On 29th June 2023, Harry changed his primary residence to Montecito.

The day after he lost Frogmore, Harry arrived at The Late Show presenter Stephen Colbert’s TV studio in New York with a bevy of bodyguards visibly carrying Glock firearms. Clearly filled with adrenaline, Harry admitted, ‘Once the book came out, I felt incredibly free. A huge weight off my chest.’ After five minutes describing his frostbite to ‘my man piece, my Johnson, my Wilson, my Todger, my Willy’ necessitating his use of a ‘cock cushion’, Harry’s aggression resurfaced. William was his target: his brother’s ‘scowl’, his ‘alarming baldness’ and his jealousy.[360]

Sales of Spare soared. The reaction in Britain was not favourable. The book, concluded The Times, was ‘deeply unedifying’, revenge with ‘tacky stuff’ by ‘mining the same depths of his despair’. The newspaper advised Harry, ‘Don’t come to the Coronation. Live quietly and privately in America. Please, not here.’[361] ‘Every time he opens his mouth,’ wrote Sarah Vine in the Daily Mail, ‘or puts pen to paper, he vomits another hairball from his past, coated in bile.’[362]

America’s reaction was mixed. New York Magazine observed: ‘Their lack of self-awareness can make even their legitimate complaints seem grating.’ The Wall Street Journal was acidic: ‘What may gall the reader the most is the hypocrisy.’ The National Review criticised his ‘betrayal of family, of country’. Even Don Lemon, a Sussex supporter, asked: ‘What exactly is he achieving by airing family dirty laundry?’[363] But the Anglophobic New York Times published a series of eulogies of Harry and damnation of British media and the Royal Family.

Columnist Pamela Paul praised Harry and Meghan as ‘martyrs, revolutionaries or simply change-makers’ for seeing America as a ‘haven’ from Britain – cursed as ‘anti-immigrant, overrun with racists and burdened by the legacy of colonialism’. Paul aligned with Meghan: ‘America loves a melodrama, an against-all-odds story, an Us versus Them. America loves an almost happily-ever-after and any gossip that keeps on giving. As is now abundantly clear, Harry and Meghan are giving their all to give America all of that.’[364]

The vitriol of columnist Zeynep Tufekci was pitiless. Piers Morgan, she wrote in the New York Times, led the ‘swamp of commentators of Britain’s atrocious but politically influential tabloids’. Guilty of ‘whipping hatred and spreading lies’, Harry stood against them alone: ‘My impression from his memoir is that Harry wants to make a crusade of applying sunlight to corrupt media practices and his family’s participation in them. If he succeeds in fighting the vile forces that he feels contributed to his mother’s death and imperilled his newfound love, he might bring a greater sense of decency in Britain, and maybe even curtail the power of the worst practices in media. Good luck to him.’[365]

America and Britain were divided. The Sussexes’ popularity in Britain had slumped to around 20 per cent. Newsweek polls showed Harry’s ratings had fallen from December to January by 45 points to minus 7, while Meghan’s fell from plus 36 to minus 13. In America, around 50 per cent of those polled supported the Sussexes.

The division in America and Britain was racially split too. Three-quarters of black Britons and nearly half of Asians polled believed that Meghan was a victim of racist bias. While white Britons polled voted by a majority of 40 per cent to keep the monarchy, a majority of Asian and black people condemned the monarchy as an irrelevant, exclusive institution reflecting Britain’s prejudice and intolerance. The monarchy, they believed, should be abolished.[366]

Buckingham Palace was paralysed. The sharp conflict of public opinion made finding an obvious solution near impossible. An Ipsos poll showed that Harry’s book had damaged the Royal Family. Their support fell from 54 per cent to 46 per cent. William’s own popularity rating fell from 74 per cent to 63 per cent and only half those polled said they thought Charles would make a good king.[367] Playing down the harm, one senior official puffed that ‘The book did not cause real damage.’[368] Another Palace insider claimed that ‘It is exhausting, it is exasperating, but it is not distracting. It will burn itself out.’[369] The Sussexes hoped he was wrong.

J. R. Moehringer hated the criticism, especially when British news-papers, illustrating Harry’s dishonesty, catalogued the book’s factual errors. For some, Moehringer’s worst mistake was to damn the tabloids’ description of Meghan’s first public engagement with the Queen in Chester as an ‘unmitigated disaster’. In reality, every newspaper had hailed it a huge success. Except, they noted, that Meghan got into a car before the Queen – at the monarch’s request. In Harry’s mind, the media’s failure to hail Meghan as perfect proved its malice. Moehringer agreed. On Twitter, he retorted that the tabloids’ ‘corrupt media ecology’ had fuelled the racist pursuit of Meghan.[370]

Still incensed, Moehringer wrote a damnation of Britain’s newspapers in the New Yorker magazine. His conspiracy theory linked the media’s criticism of Harry with Brexit.[371] ‘He’s lost the plot,’ sighed one senior Random House editor. ‘A belligerent response,’ said another editor. ‘He should have been calmer and more collected.’ Asked about the probability of another book from Harry, UK publisher Transworld’s managing director Larry Finlay was distinctly cool about repeating the experience.

Sensitive to the criticism, Harry called his old friends in Britain. To his surprise, the shires had erupted. They felt betrayed. For years, his friends and their parents had remained silent about the drugs, girls and Harry’s escapades. ‘I’m staggered by your disloyalty,’ emailed one of his oldest friends. ‘You’re cruel and cowardly,’ wrote another. The father of one close friend also emailed his dismay to Harry. Harry’s self-justifying replies fell on stony ground.[372]

In his fourth TV interview, Harry threatened that within the four hundred pages deleted from the final manuscript was ‘a shit ton of dirt about my family’, especially ‘things that have happened’ with William and Charles, ‘that I just don’t want the world to know. Because I don’t think they would ever forgive me.’ He was still waiting for Charles or William to call with an apology. Exasperated by their silence he finally snapped: ‘They will never forgive me anyway.’[373]

* * *

Guests at a private dinner hosted by Charles and Camilla at Clarence House during that week were surprised by the King’s reluctance to confront Harry openly. Surely, they assumed, he would not tolerate Harry’s criticism of Camilla. ‘Of course it bothers her; of course it hurts,’ her friend Fiona Shelburne (Lady Lansdowne) confided, ‘but she doesn’t let it get to her.’[374] No one knew that Harry had been evicted from Frogmore but everyone recognised Charles’s natural preference to shy away from arguments. He was clearly torn. With Charles fearing that his reign would be wrecked by Harry and Meghan, there was half-hearted talk of reconciliation before the coronation.

Harry’s mention of reconciliation had appealed to some Palace officials but others, especially those close to William and Kate, suspected that some media reports had been invented by Harry’s publicists to justify his complaints. In any event, reconciliation required an honest broker and there wasn’t one. Perhaps, some suggested, the Archbishop of Canterbury, Justin Welby, could act as a mediator, but that idea was discarded. Reconciliation, Palace officials were told, was ‘a long journey and could only start by both sides refraining from saying nasty things. They can disagree but without attacking each other.’[375] Another insider advised that the Windsors should remember that they are a family. But emotions were too raw. With Harry intent on continuing his public destabilisation of the Royal Family, and both William and Kate outraged by Harry’s betrayal, each side’s demand for the other’s unconditional surrender perpetuated the family’s anger. The Palace chose silence as its only option while planning the coronation.

Even so, William could not resist replying to an onlooker’s call during a visit to Liverpool: ‘Keep going, Will. Scousers love you!’

‘I will do,’ William replied.

The Waleses’ suspicion of Harry was only trumped by their distrust of Meghan. Homing in on human weakness was her speciality. The number of her victims – her father, ex-husband, countless friends and former staff – seemingly confirmed her habit of exacting vengeance against anyone deemed to be dispensable. Her presence at the coronation would encourage a circus. The Waleses’ opposition to Charles’s surrender to Harry was matched by the King’s fear of public criticism if he openly pursued for peace. Deep down he assumed that Harry would come, not least to boost Meghan’s commercial ambitions.[376] But the Palace’s suspicions were fuelled by Harry’s refusal to commit. He was seen to be playing games.

‘The door is always open,’ Harry told CBS. ‘The ball is in their court. There’s a lot to be discussed and I really hope that they’re willing to sit down and talk about it.’[377] Harry knew that his constitutional status depended on attending. While hoping to reverse his demotion, Harry must have also known that Meghan would never return to London to face the Royal Family she had mocked and deceived. Reassured by Camilla that Harry could not ruin the ceremony, Charles relieved the tension by calling him. He encouraged his son to attend the coronation. Perhaps inevitably, the Sussexes leaked the conversation.[378] The formal invitation to the Sussexes was issued at the beginning of February 2023.[379]

Two weeks later, a widely publicised South Park episode entitled ‘The Worldwide Privacy Tour’ depicted the Prince and Princess of Canada –‘a dumb prince and his stupid wife’ – as irritating hypocrites. ‘We just want to be normal people,’ moaned the cartoon prince, demanding privacy. ‘This attention is so hard.’ Holding a placard saying ‘We Want Privacy’ and ‘Stop Looking At Us’, the Princess shouted through a megaphone: ‘We are here because privacy is a basic human right.’ At the end of a meaningless conversation, the prince opened his wife’s head and found it empty. The satirists had illustrated the truth that beyond complaining, the Sussexes had nothing original to say. In the satirists’ eyes, they had been perfect fodder for the Royal Family – waving, smiling and greeting. The couple’s threat to sue the production house for defamation was quickly abandoned.[380]

The ridicule failed to dent the next stage of the marketing of Harry’s book – and embarrassing his family. As always, nothing was left to chance. For the first time that year, Harry and Meghan were ‘seen’ at San Vicente Bungalows, a Hollywood restaurant. That was the publicists’ curtain-raiser to a confected interview of Harry by 79-year-old Dr Gabor Maté, a Hungarian-born expert on addiction living in Canada. Under the heading ‘Living with Loss and Personal Healing’, Maté advertised himself as a specialist on the impact of childhood trauma.

By now, to many it looked as if Harry had monetised his interest in mental health. As a coach for BetterUp, a Californian corporation offering to improve happiness and productivity through counselling and behavioural psychology, Harry was paid about $1 million to speak about his own ‘burn-out’ and four years of therapy in order to help other sufferers to ‘find their flow’ and ‘unlock potential and opportunity’. Benefiting from ‘sound advice to heal myself from the past’ and ‘a fresh perspective’, Harry advertised himself as cured. ‘I am not a person with a disorder,’ said the BetterUp salesman.[381]

At that time, BetterUp and other mental health corporations had gained advantage from the Covid pandemic. Across Europe and America, countless people were self-diagnosing as new sufferers. Millions of Britons, especially those under thirty, were identifying new mental health problems. Declaring their inability to work, many demanded state benefits. In Britain, welfare claims had surged by 40 per cent over the past year. Britain’s Access to Work scheme was paying some self-diagnosed ADHD sufferers nearly £70,000 a year tax-free for support.[382]

Among the critics of Harry’s encouragement of self-diagnosing mental health difficulties was the psychotherapist Julia Samuel, the trusted friend of Diana. ‘Banging on with promiscuous honesty, telling everyone everything, doesn’t help any of us,’ she wrote. ‘The endless repetition of perceived injustices to anyone who will listen won’t relieve problems.’[383]

Harry ignored Samuel’s advice. ‘Self-compassion has to be the priority,’ said Harry. He was ‘turning my pain into purpose’. The solution to mental health problems, he said, was making a break or leaving one’s job. ‘Resignations aren’t all bad’ was his motto, even for those without his privilege and money.[384] His televised ‘intimate conversation’ with Gabor Maté was advertised to his followers as ‘a continuation of my mental health journey’.[385]

Choosing Maté as an interviewer cast another shadow over Harry’s judgement. Not only because of Maté’s advocacy of decriminalising every drug, but because Maté had praised the Palestinian terrorist group Hamas as ‘heroes’. Maté also denied that Jeremy Corbyn was antisemitic, even though the former Labour Party leader had been expelled from his party over allegations of antisemitism.[386]

Watching Harry and Maté’s livestream conversation on 4th March 2023 cost Britons £19, which included a copy of Spare. On the eve of the broadcast, Buckingham Palace leaked the news of Harry’s eviction from Frogmore. That decision baited Harry.

In a gloomy wood-panelled room partially lit by a roaring fire, Harry leant forward nervously in his armchair to tell Maté about Charles’s responsibility for his ‘broken home upbringing’. Abandoned by his family, said Harry, he had endured ‘an incredibly painful childhood’, starved of affection, especially hugs. Only thanks to therapy and illegal drugs had his quest to find his ‘authentic true self’ succeeded.

‘You can be wounded by not having your needs met as a young child,’ agreed Maté.

‘I started to go slightly off the rails,’ continued Harry, ‘and dealt with it through drinking and drugs.’ Maté endorsed Harry’s use of hallucinogenic drugs as Harry added, ‘If you are suffering from a huge amount of loss, grief or trauma, then these things have a way of working as a medicine.’

‘It was a story of deprivation,’ agreed Maté. As the wizened therapist spouted out a list of Harry’s mental illnesses, the privileged Prince rolled over in agreement, seemingly delighting at being the centre of attention, a sucker for Maté’s psycho-babble. Drug addiction could soothe the trauma, agreed Maté. Harry nodded. When Maté rebuked him for fighting in Afghanistan, Harry forgot his loyalties. Instead, Harry told the Hamas supporter how his fellow British soldiers were society’s victims and had actually opposed the war. His pride in killing twenty-five Taliban fighters – as written in his memoir – was forgotten.

The conversation lasted eighty-six minutes. In retrospect, Maté cursed himself for taking part. The British media’s negative and dismissive reaction to the ‘merchant of pain’, admitted Maté, ‘really got to me and put me in a very negative state of mind.’ Harry was also, by now, feeling dissatisfied. ‘I’m feeling more and more distant from my loved ones and my family,’ Harry lamented. ‘This is a problem.’[387]

Once the spotlight had been turned off, Harry reverted to his daily routine. Exercise in the gym, playing with Archie, an occasional cycle ride, smoking cannabis in his garden and walking the dogs along the beach. Other than sporadic calls about the Invictus Games due in September in Düsseldorf, he was preoccupied with the five legal cases he was fighting in London’s High Court. Three were against British media groups and two separate cases were against the Home Office. His courtroom battle against the Home Office had so far cost the taxpayer over £300,000 in legal fees. His own costs were higher.[388]

Harry called his London lawyers, sometimes late at night, to discuss technicalities and then sought out a single British friend to confide in. ‘He’ll still regularly talk to me about obscure journalists and stuff done to his mother,’ recalled one friend. Harry repeated his determination to challenge Rupert Murdoch and to ‘fight this battle to the bitter end’. Because only his insurers risked millions of pounds if he lost, he said boldly: ‘Murdoch has offered me over £1 million to settle but I won’t.’[389]

Meghan said nothing meaningful in the aftermath of the publicity splurge. Harry was on his own.

CHAPTER 20

High Court

Billed as ‘The Duchess of Sussex’, six weeks after Harry’s book tour, Meghan starred in a video promoting Clevr Blends coffee.[390] She owned a stake in the company that sold powdered drinks containing ‘calming’ additives for sleep, wellness and to treat anxiety. Meghan described Clevr as a woman-only corporation, although the co-founder was male.

For a fee, the Duchess also promoted latte powders, luxury Tatcha skincare products and Eberjey bathrobes. On Amazon’s website, Eberjey cost about ten times more than similar robes.[391]

Meghan had wielded spectacular influence during her first outing with Harry to Nottingham in 2017. The £545 Strathberry bag she carried was an instant sell-out. Undoubtedly keen to capitalise on the commercial value of her fashion choices, she had been surprised to be struck down by Buckingham Palace’s veto. The dispute came to a head with her decision to quit Britain. If she could not profit from her fame, she would take the highway. Five years later, Meghan was photographed with a Cesta bag on a dinner date with Cameron Diaz and Gwyneth Paltrow. Hours later, Cesta’s founders, Erin Ryder and Courtney Weinblatt Fasciano, discovered the Meghan effect: ‘All of a sudden, this one style that had been a little bit sleepy was totally sold through. We had more sales in one day than we’ve ever had.’[392]

By 2023, Meghan’s portfolio included more than five brands. ‘Investing in them has helped me line up for this chapter where I’m investing in myself,’ Meghan said.[393] Several other products were under consideration for her endorsement.

The tabloids’ lies which drove us out of Britain,’ according to Harry, were describing their move to California as motivated to make money.[394] But this was another lie, said Harry, and the truth, he told Tom Bradby, was so different: ‘We were dedicated to a life of service, as is proven by everything that we’re doing now with the work that we do.’ Earning cash was irrelevant, Harry insisted. Outsiders wondered whether Harry was the victim of self-deception or Meghan’s deception – or was he just an outright liar. Harry, it appeared, was unaware that his wife’s ambition was dedicated to becoming a celebrity billionaire. Performing for charity emerged as Meghan’s means to promote her brand. Amid her publicist’s patter of brand separation from Harry, abandoning the victim narrative and neutralising the toxicity of Netflix and Spare, Meghan was presented as a fun, powerful, optimistic woman leading with love.

To earn her fortune, she signed up with Ari Emanuel at the William Morris Endeavor talent agency. Emanuel’s agency also represented Oprah Winfrey, Serena Williams and Tyler Perry. ‘If Ari can’t build her into a global brand, no one can,’ commented an expert. In a specially commissioned photo shoot, Meghan presented herself with a blow-dried look as a putative Hollywood mogul.[395] Then followed a series of unfortunate events.

One year earlier, the Sussexes had starred as Time magazine’s Most Influential People in the World. Now, they were not even mentioned as one of Time’s Top 100. Unexpectedly, they had not been invited to Barack Obama’s sixtieth birthday party or to the Clooneys’ humanitarian awards party in New York, despite Amal having been a guest at Meghan’s New York baby shower in 2019.[396] Meghan had even flown back to London in Amal Clooney’s private jet. The change of attitudes was inspired by the Royal Family’s unhappiness with the Sussexes. America’s A-listers had chosen sides.

Meghan’s income now depended on retaining her royal title and securing titles for her children. Buckingham Palace’s website listed Master Archie Mountbatten-Windsor and Miss Lilibet Mountbatten-Windsor. Despite Harry’s demands, the King still refused to sign the letters patent to rename the children as prince and princess.

No one in the Palace had forgotten Meghan’s insistence at Archie’s birth that her children would not accept titles. From her ‘experience’, she explained, titles caused ‘a lot of pain’.[397] Two years later, Meghan told Oprah Winfrey that the Royal Family had originally intended to deny the unborn Archie a title because of ‘the colour of his skin’. That accusation changed in 2023. Despite the Royal Family’s racism and the Palace’s refusal to protect the Duchess from suicide, Meghan demanded the Windsors’ titles. In their quest for legitimacy, she and Harry could not bear that their children should not have the same rank as William’s children.[398]

Ignoring Charles’s procrastination, on 3rd March 2023, the Sussexes hosted a christening in Montecito for 21-month-old Lilibet. The Bishop of Los Angeles, the Reverend John Harvey Taylor, a former newspaper reporter and Richard Nixon’s one-time chief of staff, blessed Princess Lilibet Diana Mountbatten-Windsor in the garden, watched by Diana’s sisters, Jane Fellowes and Sarah McCorquodale. Tyler Perry was named as her godfather. Unlike all others employed by the Sussexes, the bishop was not asked to sign an NDA. The event and the naming of ‘the prince and princess’ was announced in People magazine.[399] The Palace’s official court circular ignored the baptism.

Charles refused the invitation to the christening but finally relented to Harry’s demands. Days later, Buckingham Palace officially recognised his grandchildren’s titles. Instantly, Meghan instructed her lawyers to change Prince Archie’s and Princess Lilibet’s surnames from Mountbatten-Windsor to Sussex.

* * *

Focused on detoxifying her image and earning her own fortune, Meghan had ‘checked out’ of Harry’s passion to defeat the tabloids. Though, in her bid to avoid collateral damage, she nevertheless paid more than lip service to Harry’s life’s mission to get police protection. Not because she planned to return to Britain, but she did fear Harry was vulnerable to assassins. She also believed Harry’s father could have intervened to provide protection.

To avoid Harry’s embarrassing demands, Charles had ordered that his son’s telephone calls be blocked. ‘His Majesty is unavailable,’ was the standard answer. The rejection fed Harry’s paranoia of a conspiracy against him orchestrated by unsympathetic Palace officials. In retaliation, Harry further inflamed relations by briefing People magazine about his father’s stubbornness.[400]

Clearly enjoying the controversy, Harry arrived in London on a private jet from Miami at the end of March 2023 for the first hearing in his case against the Mail group.Unexpectedly, Charles was in London. After an outbreak of riots across France protesting President Macron’s government, the King’s two-day state visit to Paris had been cancelled. Clearly, Charles had an empty diary, but Harry was told that his father was ‘busy’ and ‘unavailable’. The King was evidently unwilling to be associated with Harry’s legal warfare.[401]

Harry’s first case was his continuing defamation claim against the Mail on Sunday; the second case against the Mail group was the new claim based on unlawful bugging. Ignoring the criticism from the King and Palace officials that royals should not risk opening up ‘a can of worms’ by testifying in the witness box, Harry was pleased he could attack the Mail’s ‘unchecked power, influence and criminality’.[402]

Once again, Harry was relying on Sherborne. The lawyer had read the Mail’s financial records provided to the Leveson media inquiry in 2012. To keep those files secure, Judge Leveson had given the Mail’s editor his assurance of total confidentiality. The Mail’s files, Leveson had promised, would not be passed on or read by anyone beyond the inquiry. Sherborne had signed an undertaking not to ‘disclose, publish or use the documents’. Yet suddenly, Harry’s solicitor possessed the Mail’s files. Sherborne explained that the records were given to Harry’s solicitor by ‘an investigative journalist at an online media publication who has not revealed his source’. Sherborne denied there was any evidence that the files had been obtained from Leveson’s archives.[403] Within the historic files was evidence of payments by the Mail group to private investigators. The unanswered question was whether any of those investigators had acted unlawfully and whether they had illegally targeted Harry.

On the first day of the hearing, Harry sat in Courtroom 76 with Elton John, Doreen Lawrence and Sadie Frost. He heard the Mail’s lawyers argue that Harry’s ‘preposterous’ case should be dismissed without a trial. Harry bluntly replied that if the Mail’s attempt to evade justice was successful ‘the whole country is doomed’.

As usual, Sherborne pitched to the gallery. With the information provided by Harry, said Sherborne, Doreen Lawrence apparently had become ‘deeply paranoid’.[404] On Lawrence’s behalf the lawyer said, ‘She finds it hard to believe the level of duplicity and manipulation that was clearly at play, knowing now that the Daily Mail’s support for her fight to bring Stephen’s killers to justice was hollow and worse, entirely false.’ As he sat in court, Harry was given the chance to consider the extraordinary collection of convicted criminals that he had aligned himself with for the trial. Among the witnesses Harry was destined to call was Daniel ‘Danno’ Portley-Hanks, a private investigator. He admitted being arrested about fifty times and convicted ‘more times than I can remember’, including for extortion for a criminal gang. He had spent eight years in prison.[405] Harry would also call Jonathan Rees, a private investigator who had been jailed for seven years for perverting the course of justice.[406]

Harry also had to consider whether to rely, as Sherborne advised, on Christine Hart, a former journalist, ‘blagger’ and private investigator.[407] Accused of targeting Lawrence and others to illegally obtain medical records, Hart strongly denied carrying out any unlawful activities for newspapers. However, she did describe an approach by Graham Johnson, a former News of the World reporter, to help Hugh Grant’s complaint against the Mail. ‘Grant was out to destroy/get the Mail,’ Johnson allegedly told Hart.[408]

Graham Johnson was publicly described as a ‘self-confessed professional liar’ who admitted that he had ‘no integrity at all’ after he was sacked from the News of the World for fabricating stories. Accused of ‘destroying people’s lives using illegal means,’ he was employed by Harry’s solicitors.[409] In Harry’s case, Johnson admitted that he paid Christine Hart £16,000 for information and had agreed to pay £5,000 to Harry’s star witness, the private investigator Gavin Burrows, to ‘provide evidence to back up claims’ made in his original statement. Johnson, it was suggested, had been loaned £500,000 by Max Mosley, the deceased Formula One racing executive and financier of litigation against the tabloids.[410]

Sherborne did not convincingly explain to the judge how it was possible that Gavin Burrows had signed two statements – one for Harry admitting his dishonesty and another for the Mail utterly denying that he had ever committed any dishonest acts against Harry and the others. ‘I wish to make clear,’ stated Burrows, ‘that I was never instructed or commissioned by anyone at the Mail on Sunday or the Daily Mail to conduct unlawful information-gathering on their behalf.’ Against each of Harry’s allegations of Burrows’s crimes, he stated for the Mail, ‘This is false.’ Among Burrows’s rebuttals was an outright denial that he collected cash regularly left by the Mail on Sunday at a drop-off in London’s Regent Street.[411]

In that wilderness of mirrors, Harry did not question how a member of the Royal Family could rely on Paul Hawkes, a convicted phone hacker. Hawkes testified that he was brought into the case by another convicted private investigator, Dan Evans. According to Hawkes, he was told by Evans ‘it would be in my best interests’ to testify that he had hacked Hugh Grant’s computer. After Hawkes refused to sign an untrue statement, Evans allegedly threatened to ‘destroy’ him. Hawkes also accused Evans of having threatened to ruin him if he didn’t ‘play ball’ and testify for Harry in his claim against the Mirror.[412]

Adding to the murkiness, members of the claimants’ ‘legal research team’ were also allegedly pursuing unethical means to avoid the six-year limitation rule: once the claimant knew about the alleged illegality, he or she had six years to bring the claim. According to the Mail’s counsel, ‘corrupted’ emails between members of the team showed that at least two claimants, including Sadie Frost, had discussed their cases more than six years before they issued their claims.[413] The researchers were accused of concocting a ruse to ‘camouflage’ that destructive timeline, something both lawyers and their claimants denied.[414]

At the end of a four-day hearing, Judge Matthew Nicklin called Sherborne’s explanation about the appearance of the Mail’s financial ledgers ‘theoretical . . . even fanciful’. ‘To rely on the archives’, Nicklin said, would be ‘an abuse of process’ and ruled that Harry could not use them in his case.[415] Nicklin’s decision would later be overturned by the government in ‘the public interest’.[416] But the Mail was encouraged that Harry’s lawyers, accused of delays, obfuscation and their alleged refusal to hand over key documents, had produced only one allegation of unlawful information-gathering by the newspaper against Harry. And, to the claimants’ lawyers’ embarrassment, they had to deny an alleged conspiracy – based on emails from their own research team – of a plot to overcome the laws of limitation, barring the right to bring a case six years after the complaint was known.[417] The route to the trial, due to start in January 2026, was strewn with accusations of skulduggery.

Unseen while he was in London, Harry discussed with Palace officials his proposed presence at the coronation on 6th May. No concessions were made about his seating position in the abbey. Additionally, he conceded that he would not enter the abbey in the procession nor stand on the Buckingham Palace balcony. Instead, after the ceremony he would be speedily driven to Heathrow to return immediately to California. He volunteered that Meghan would not come. Their official excuse was the clash with Archie’s birthday.

Some insiders were critical of the King and especially of Edward Young for denying Harry a role in the coronation. Young’s anger with the Sussexes, believed one senior official, forestalled any thought of how to accommodate Harry. ‘It was a catastrophe not to put Harry in the procession. He should have been given something to carry,’ suggested a senior official.[418]

The final details were agreed after Harry had consulted Meghan on his return to Montecito. In the excitement building up to the coronation on 6th May, speculation resumed about a reconciliation between Harry and his family. Some suggested that he wanted to spend more time in Britain. The truth was different. Harry had no wish to live in Britain, not least because Meghan would refuse to join him.

Buckingham Palace announced on 12th April that the King was ‘happy’ that Harry would be in the abbey and was disappointed that Meghan and his grandchildren would not be there.[419] On the same day, depicting marked contrast with the fusty Royal Family, Meghan issued photographs of herself as the sun-kissed Californian girl. In her accompanying statement, the Duchess urged the media to stop ‘creating an exhausting circus’ around their lives.[420] Two weeks later, Meghan recreated their circus.

Clearly determined to be the ringmaster, she emerged from the shadows to stage her first public appearance of 2023 with Harry at the Los Angeles Lakers basketball stadium. Her message – that they were pursuing different career paths – was choreographed. As Harry tried to kiss her it was reported that she pulled away.[421] Harry’s emotions were being torn, and a time where, rather than seeking a ceasefire with his family, he was about to resume hostilities.

The battleground was the High Court and Harry’s claim against News UK for ‘unlawful information-gathering’. At the heart of his complaint was his perceived victimhood – he was the victim of the media, the government and the Royal Family. Breaking the convention that the Royal Family was always neutral, Harry issued a 31-page statement against Rupert Murdoch’s News UK and Mirror newspapers. Presenting himself as the knight in shining armour, he said: ‘Our country is judged globally by the state of our press and our government; both of whose reputations, I believe, are currently at rock bottom.’ He accused newspapers of failing to criticise the government but ‘getting into bed with them’ to maintain ‘the status quo’, conveniently forgetting that only one year earlier the newspapers had helped drive Prime Minister Boris Johnson out of Downing Street.[422]

Specifically, Harry blamed the tabloids for causing ‘in large part’ his mental illness by their ‘grotesque and sadistic’ methods. The tabloids, he said, constantly coaxed a ‘damaged’ young man to excesses. His use of drugs, drinking, cavorting in the nude and dressing in a Nazi uniform was all the tabloids’ fault. He had to ‘play up’ to the tabloids’ headlines and the stereotypes ‘they wanted to place upon me’. Compounding his misery, they had exploited his mental health by describing him as a ‘failure’, ‘drop-out’, ‘thicko’, ‘cheat’, ‘underage drinker’ and ‘irresponsible drug-taker’. He feared that the public believed those descriptions. ‘This is brainwashing at the highest level,’ he said. Someone would hate him so much that they would stab him. Or, having killed his mother, their next victim would be Meghan. Journalists were killing innocent people. ‘How much more blood will stain their typing fingers before someone can put a stop to this madness?’ He accused journalists of aiming to ‘destroy our relationship and destroy my wife with their endless lies while giving a platform to her abusers’ and using ‘illegal methods to dig into her past’. He gave no examples of any illegal methods used against Meghan.

Less than two weeks before the coronation, Harry loudly proclaimed – in his lawyers’ words – his noble cause: ‘There is no greater public interest argument than exposing the unlawful practices of those that act in the name of the public interest.’ He included the Royal Family among the perpetrators of illegality.

Harry’s specific complaint now was one he had made before, about his family’s secret conspiracy with Rupert Murdoch and News UK. To secure media support for Camilla to become Queen, Harry claimed that both Queen Elizabeth and Charles had agreed before 2012 not to sue News UK for hacking the Royal Family’s telephones. Once Camilla had been rehabilitated, said Harry, News UK had in 2020 secretly paid William £1 million as compensation for hacking.[423] That, he pronounced, was another example of William being treated more favourably than him. His ‘crusade’ against newspapers, he now claimed, was ‘central’ to the breakdown of his family’s relationships.[424]

His evidence of the conspiracy between the Palace and News UK was his failure to get the same £1 million compensation as William. After three years of negotiations between Sally Osman, the Palace’s director of communications, and News UK’s chief executive Robert Thomson, Harry’s claim against Murdoch’s newspapers and journalists for hacking into his phone had been sidelined. ‘We risk becoming a laughing stock,’ Harry emailed Osman in 2018 after she failed to get even a reply from Thomson.[425]

In Harry’s scenario, the Queen’s and Charles’s secret agreement with News UK was implemented by Edward Young and other senior Palace officials. Thereafter, along with Charles, they had actively discouraged Harry from bringing his claim against News UK.[426] Inspired by Sherborne and his solicitors, Harry ignored the Palace’s objections to starting a case against Murdoch. In September 2019, he had issued a High Court claim against News UK. Nearly four years later, the case was still wending its way through the legal process.

At 4am on 25th April 2023, William was in London getting ready for a ceremony in Hyde Park to honour fallen soldiers for Anzac Day. Then he would complete an ITV documentary about homelessness. On the same day in Montecito, Harry got up in the middle of the night to log on to the livestream of a preliminary hearing of his case against News UK. To his horror, he heard Judge Timothy Fancourt question his honesty.

In combative mood, Sherborne told Fancourt that the Queen herself had been party to the secret deal to stop Harry’s claim against News UK. It was only after her death that the conspiracy could be exposed. Sherborne faced two obstacles. Both News UK and the Palace denied making any secret agreement and he possessed no evidence to prove the conspiracy.

Unimpressed by Sherborne, Fancourt turned on Harry. Why, he asked, did Harry not mention the ‘secret agreement’ at the outset of his claim? Nor was it specified in Harry’s statements of truth signed in 2019, 2021 or in his autobiography. Even his answers about when he discovered his phone was being hacked, declared the judge, were filled with ‘fanciful and factual inconsistencies’. And how could there have been a ‘secret payment’ if William received £1 million during the Queen’s lifetime?

Harry’s ‘secret agreement’ between the Palace and News UK, the judge was told, was ‘Alice in Wonderland stuff’ and a ‘construct’ by Harry’s lawyers. Fancourt found that Harry’s case ‘lacked credibility and cogency’, and was ‘inconsistent’, ‘vague and limited’. On that basis, Fancourt declared, Harry’s allegation of a secret agreement was an ‘implausible’ fantasy.[427] For a member of the Royal Family to be subject to these criticisms by a judge was unprecedented. No outsider witnessed Harry’s embarrassment. The judge’s stark comments about Harry within his forty-page judgement would be publicised only after the coronation.

Nevertheless, the judge agreed that Harry’s lawyers should have access to News UK’s and the Palace’s emails.[428] Fancourt also allowed Harry to run a claim against News UK for their alleged illegal investigations and their unlawful invasion of his privacy.[429] That success took second place to Harry’s case against the Mirror, which was due to begin shortly after the coronation.

CHAPTER 21

Coronation

Just twenty-four hours before the coronation of King Charles III, Harry arrived at Heathrow from Los Angeles on an American Airlines flight. Denied any invitations to the Palace’s pre-coronation receptions or the three days of celebrations after the ceremony, he could not disguise his isolation. As agreed with the Palace, he was protected by armed policemen as he drove to Frogmore for his last night at the house.

After the Queen’s jubilee and her funeral, for the third time that year central London was prepared for a royal parade. The majority of Britons welcomed the reaffirmation of the monarchy. Crowned as King, Charles would demand Britons’ allegiance and at the same time offer to serve. The unique religious service arranged by Charles could not conceal new challenges. Some Commonwealth countries were planning to become republics; Britain’s youth and immigrant community were largely against a hereditary monarchy; and many Britons were appalled by the distasteful spectacle of Andrew’s and Harry’s behaviour.

Charles was criticised by some senior members of the Establishment for failing to resolve conclusively the embarrassments presented by Harry and Andrew. His reticence weakened the Crown’s reputation. By failing to consider properly the consequences of the princes’ actions for the future of the monarchy, Charles rightly questioned his own and Camilla’s popularity.

Public opinion mattered. During her short life, Diana showed how the monarchy depended on communal support. The Royal Family’s initially mistaken reaction to her death exposed their vulnerability. Still tainted by his treatment of Diana, Charles could not be certain that the British would genuinely accept Camilla as Queen. For so many years, she had been the ‘Tampax mistress’ who had originally rejected Charles for the man she truly loved, Andrew Parker Bowles. Charles, however, could be reassured that his own popularity had increased, not least because forty years earlier he had, unfashionably, championed the environment. But the bulwark of his reign would be William and Kate. Their popularity guaranteed the succession. In the slimmed-down monarchy, so much depended on them to take on the responsibility as patrons of a thousand charities and organisations.

The prospect of seeing the new Prince and Princess of Wales in the abbey irritated Harry, as did the plan for his arrival at the abbey with Prince Andrew.

Meghan’s absence from the coronation puzzled many. Some wondered how a woman who clung to royal titles could refuse to attend Britain’s most important ceremony. ‘The Sussexes felt they were treated appallingly by the Royal Family,’ stated the Daily Telegraph in a sympathetic article amended three times online. After all, Harry had not been told in time about the Queen’s death; he wasn’t allowed to wear a uniform at her funeral and an invitation to a Buckingham Palace reception before the funeral had been withdrawn. Some suggested that Meghan was ‘irate that the King had failed to answer her concerns’ about being racially abused by the Royal Family. Amid all the froth, no one published an alternative perspective of the situation: that Meghan was contemptuous of the Royal Family, both the individuals themselves and their traditions. To many, it reasoned that Meghan wouldn’t give an audience to people that didn’t respect her, and to others it seemed that she lacked the courage to face the people she had lambasted so publicly in the Netflix series six months earlier. By contrast, Harry seemingly had no qualms about facing those he had repeatedly trashed.

In the driving rain, Harry arrived at the abbey with Andrew. The disgraced Prince was, at the time, still refusing the King’s order to move to Frogmore from Royal Lodge, the 30-bedroom mansion he occupied with his ex-wife, Sarah. Relations between the uncle and his nephew were not good. In some accounts, Andrew had scathingly dismissed Meghan as an ‘opportunist’.[430] More recently, a report had emerged of Andrew’s extraordinary rudeness to Robin Barnett, the deputy ambassador at the British embassy in Warsaw. In front of a group of businessmen, Andrew had spectacularly humiliated Barnett, mocking the diplomat’s club foot as he limped across the room to pass on to the Prince an urgent message from London.

Wearing an unpressed Dior morning suit and his medals, Harry walked alone up the aisle. Unsmiling, the outsider nodded at a few members of the congregation but noticeably ignored his brother, Kate and their three children sitting in the front row. In turn, they ignored him. Placed in the third row and glaring at William’s back, Harry sat beside Jack Brooksbank, Princess Eugenie’s husband. ‘I’m fed up with the way they treat me,’ Harry told the marketing executive who had left university without a degree to become a bartender. ‘It’s not an ideal situation. They don’t care.’[431] Harry’s view of the ceremony was soon blocked by Princess Anne’s large red feather – the plume of the Blues and Royals – on her hat. She asked whether she should remove her hat. She was told ‘no’.[432]

After the Crown of St Edward had been safely placed on Charles’s head, Harry intoned, ‘God Save King Charles. Long Live King Charles. May the King live forever.’ The camera did not focus on Harry as his father’s former mistress was crowned Queen. The heralds shouted ‘Vivat Regina Camilla’. In other circumstances, they would have loudly proclaimed ‘Vivat Regina Diana’.

Harry could have reflected that the crowning of Camilla, an unpopular divorcee, as Queen had proved Charles’s tenacity. In a previous era that would have been impossible. But Harry’s family were romantics. Just as Harry had sacrificed everything for Meghan, Edward VIII had abdicated the throne for Wallis Simpson. The passing camera shot of Harry caught the face of a sad man.

To Harry’s visible irritation, after the historic symbols were passed around Charles, William stepped forward to collaborate in the most solemn rituals. Paying homage, William knelt in front of his father, pledged his loyalty – ‘So help me God’ – and then kissed his father on the cheek. Harry saw an unusual bond – an intense relationship – the same one he had sacrificed and now sought to destroy. At that moment, the future of the monarchy appeared to be secure for three generations. The caravan had moved on without him.

King Charles rose from his throne and headed alone towards the abbey’s exit. After years of controversy, he had fulfilled his destiny. More consciously than others in his family, Charles recognised how other European monarchies had been swept aside because of extravagance, stubbornness or scandal. The greatest threat to the British monarchy, the new King feared, was Harry. Indeed, throughout a thousand years of history, kings and queens had been repeatedly threatened by renegade brothers, sisters or sons.

As Queen Camilla walked alone towards the abbey’s exit, Harry could not fail to notice her hands reach towards the loose crown, clearly fearful it might topple to the floor. Noticeably, Harry did not bow to the new Queen. Nor did anyone else in the family section.

Thirty-five minutes after the coronation ended, Harry was back at Heathrow. He had spent a mere twenty-nine hours in Britain. As the King and Queen stood on the Palace’s balcony waving at a vast enthusiastic crowd, Harry took off on BA’s 3.45pm flight for Los Angeles. As he headed towards the Atlantic, there was a call for silence at the Palace reception. Raising his glass, Charles proposed several toasts, including one to his grandchildren and, on his fourth birthday, to Archie ‘wherever he is’. A guest would later reveal that William had decided that afternoon not to invite Harry to his coronation. They would never be reconciled. Some guests wondered whether Harry would ever attend another formal royal event. At 6.30pm, Harry landed in Los Angeles and completed the ninety-mile journey northwards in two hours. Just in time to wish Archie a happy birthday.

At the Windsor Castle concert that night, William included in his short speech a rebuke to the Sussexes: ‘Most importantly of all, my father has always understood that people of all faiths, all backgrounds and all communities deserve to be celebrated and supported. Pa, we are all so proud of you.’ There were loud cheers as William proclaimed, ‘God save the King.’

CHAPTER 22

The Chase

Ten days later, on 16th May 2023, Harry and Meghan were back in New York. Both appeared revitalised, not least to challenge the new King.

A few months after the Sussexes befriended and hosted in Montecito the celebrated feminist Gloria Steinem, the 89-year-old activist’s Ms Foundation for Women had acclaimed Meghan’s leadership with its World of Vision Award. The citation for Meghan’s prize celebrated ‘her global advocacy to empower and advocate on behalf of women and girls’, and she was praised as someone who ‘ignites policy and cultural change’. The award would be presented at a glittering celebration on the foundation’s fiftieth anniversary.

The Sussexes had every reason to welcome their return to the spotlight. Over the previous weeks, their approval ratings among Americans had fallen to about 25 per cent. While a minority of Americans still regarded the Sussexes as heroes, the majority had become exasperated by their attacks against the Royal Family. Meghan’s popularity had plunged 36 points to minus 33. After the publication of his book, Harry’s popularity had fallen 45 points to minus 22. The slide threatened to continue.

The sniping generated by South Park’s sarcastic cartoon was continued after the publication of Spare by television host Jimmy Kimmel mocking William’s and Harry’s grudge fight in the kitchen. More woundingly, the New York Times switched sides. Under the headline ‘Has Prince Harry’s Confessional Tour Run Its Course?’ the newspaper asked whether the Sussexes’ rehash had become repetitive and tiresome.[433] Having exhausted their favourite topic – themselves – ‘What is left for them to talk about?’ After washing their linen in public, the Sussexes were no longer revered royals but merely common celebrities.

Before flying to New York, in order to eradicate the slurs, Meghan arranged a lunch at a Japanese Michelin-starred restaurant in Montecito. Present were Cameron Diaz and her husband Benji Madden, Gwyneth Paltrow and her husband TV producer Brad Falchuk, and Whitney Wolfe Herd, the co-founder of Tinder and the CEO of the online dating platform Bumble, and her husband the Texan oil heir Michael Herd. Being spotted with Hollywood royalty would enhance her appearance in New York for the relaunch of an empowered woman with opinions.

In anticipation of the event, Steinem praised Meghan as ‘smart, funny and devoted to social issues’. Returning the compliment, Meghan glorified Steinem as her ‘inspiration’ and ‘mentor’.[434] Interestingly, Meghan also denounced her role in 2006 as a hostess on Deal or No Deal, a TV show offering contestants the chance of winning $1 million. Over thirty-four episodes, dressed in a tight miniskirt and a stuffed bra, Meghan regularly earned a healthy income. ‘It objectified me,’ she complained, ‘as a showgirl.’[435]

Rather than opt for a hotel in New York, the Sussexes arranged to stay overnight at a private house in Upper East Manhattan owned by the cosmetics manufacturer Victoria Jackson.[436] The ceremony would be held at the Ziegfeld Ballroom on the other side of Central Park. Three SUVs and a bevy of bodyguards employed by TorchStone, a global security company, had been booked for the journey. TorchStone provided not only bodyguards but also checked on journalists researching the Sussexes. That weekend, Caroline Graham of the Mail on Sunday was a particular irritant. She reported that Dior was considering appointing Meghan as a brand ambassador.[437] As Meghan dressed for the Steinem event in a strapless gold Johanna Ortiz outfit and five-inch Tom Ford heels, Dior emphatically denied any relationship with Meghan. Pertinently, Queen Camilla had worn a Dior dress at that day’s Ascot races in England.

On that same Tuesday, Harry’s lawyers in London were in court once again to argue against the Home Office’s refusal to provide armed protection for the Sussexes. Harry’s lawyer, Shaheed Fatima, told the judge how Harry’s safety had been ‘compromised’ in July 2021 after he left a charity function in Kew without police protection. She said that the paparazzi chased the Sussexes’ vehicle and argued that it proved the Sussexes’ need for armed police protection. Meghan would be murdered, Harry feared, after what he had ‘experienced over the last six years . . . at the hands of the tabloids’.[438] Not mentioned was Harry’s claim that he was a target of al-Qaeda. The hearing would continue the following day.

That evening in New York, photographers had gathered outside the Ziegfeld Ballroom. A good snap of Meghan, they knew, was worth a few hundred dollars. None had expected Harry that night. Once he was spotted, the photographers’ interest soared. A joint photograph was worth thousands of dollars. But to their irritation, the Sussexes darted from the SUV into a Hertz shop to enter the building through a back entrance, instead of posing as usual. The disappointed photographers agreed that the Sussexes had contrived to control the narrative – no photographs except on their terms.[439]

Meghan’s power to attract publicity was critical to the charity. The ambition to raise $100 million over the following year depended on Meghan and Harry inspiring generosity from the one thousand high rollers in the ballroom.

The Sussexes’ entrance was warmly applauded. New Yorkers were genuinely curious to see one of the world’s most famous couples. Surrounded by champions of virtue signalling, the couple greeted the famous and smiled at the unknowns. Both were professional performers. Told to keep it brief, Meghan’s six-minute speech struck all the right notes. Highlighting her lifelong feminist activism, she raved about the impact in her youth of her mom buying Ms, Gloria Steinem’s magazine.[440]

‘I also knew that to my mom – to my dear mom who I’m honoured to have here with me tonight – I knew that the significance of these magazines was important,’ she said, adding a good joke: ‘I mean, it wasn’t a one-off. She had a subscription!’ Meghan praised Ms’s diversity and how female politicians and astronauts were heroes: ‘Ms was formative in that cocooning. It piqued my curiosity and it became the chrysalis for the woman that I would become and that I am today.’

A few in the audience were sceptical but everyone applauded her final sentiment: ‘My greater value and purpose in life was to advocate for those who felt unheard, to stand up to injustice, and to be not afraid of saying what you know is true, and what is just, and what is right.’ The organisers were thrilled. They expected huge contributions over the following days. Instead, the night raised less than $1.5 million. One reason was the events that followed.

Aware of the court hearings in London, the Sussexes left the ballroom determined not only that their destination should remain unknown but also, on Harry’s orders, that they would not be photographed. Acting on Harry’s plan, as they emerged, bodyguards obscured their faces. ‘Security were being arseholes from the start,’ complained a photographer. ‘We’d waited for more than four hours and none of us could get shots.’[441] But it was worse. ‘They were mocking the paps, provoking them. Those security [guys] egged on the paps.’ A few photographers were more than furious.[442]

As the Sussexes’ convoy moved off, about six cars and motorbikes with paparazzi followed. In Harry’s version, he was chased for two hours by ‘about a dozen cars, bikes and scooters’. Ashley Hansen, his spokeswoman, called it ‘a near catastrophic car chase at the hands of a ring of highly aggressive paparazzi who mounted pavements, jumped lights and reversed down one-way streets resulting in multiple near collisions involving other drivers on the road, pedestrians and two NYPD officers’. Hansen’s version was embellished by a member of Harry’s security, Chris Sanchez, who claimed, ‘It could have been fatal.’ The Sussexes, summarised Hansen, were left ‘incredibly scared and shaken up’. Adding to the drama, Omid Scobie authoritatively reported that the Sussexes’ car had been driven at 80mph ‘to lose’ the pursuing photographers.[443] Harry offered his conclusion: ‘You want to talk about history repeating itself. They’re not going to stop until [Meghan] dies.’[444]

The news dominated Britain’s morning headlines. Ashley Hansen ensured that everyone, including the High Court judge who at that very moment was hearing Harry’s case for armed protection, should know that his life had once again been endangered because he was unprotected.

Yet soon after daybreak in New York, Harry’s version of the chase was dismissed by the New York Police Department (NYPD) and New York’s mayor, Eric Adams. The scenes, they agreed, were ‘challenging’, but it was ‘hard to believe’ there had been a two-hour chase in the congested city. ‘It was a bit chaotic,’ said the police spokesman, ‘but there were no collisions, injuries or threats.’[445]

Photos of Meghan distributed by the celebrity news agency BackGrid showed her smiling from her SUV. According to BackGrid, Harry’s SUV was ‘reckless, zigzagging, coming close to other cars and blocking off streets. They pulled out into the oncoming lane and caused chaos.’[446]

After driving for about forty-five minutes, the Sussexes had headed to the 19th Precinct police station on 67th Street between Third Avenue and Lexington. According to Ashley Hansen, the Sussexes went into the station, discussed their plight and then emerged to hail a cab.

Mike Lombardi, the precinct’s police chief, was puzzled by Hansen’s claim. The Sussexes, he knew, never entered the police station. Nor did the Sussexes make a complaint or a request. And the police never went near Harry’s SUV. Police cars leaving the station for emergencies didn’t see Harry. The precinct chief declared that, ‘Harry and Meghan got carried away, the paparazzi got carried away, the media got carried away.’ All a single policeman posted outside the precinct station saw was the Sussexes getting into a yellow cab, only for it to be stuck stationary in the street. More confusion followed.[447]

The cab driver, Sukhcharn Singh, recalled two cars following him. ‘I don’t think I would call it a chase,’ he recalled. ‘I never felt like I was in danger. They kept their distance.’ A garbage truck blocked his getaway cab. No photographer approached the stationary vehicle. After just ten minutes, Singh was back at the police station. He was paid $17 for the fare, plus a $50 tip. The Sussexes got back into the SUV and headed uptown alone to Jackson’s brownstone on the Upper East Side. Based on a briefing from Harry’s team, the New York Times misreported even that short journey: ‘The couple got home by police convoy without having their location discovered.’[448]

Challenged that her version of a ‘near fatal, catastrophic car chase’ was clearly inaccurate, Hansen replied, ‘It would be abhorrent to suggest it was a PR stunt.’[449] Few were convinced. Harry’s protests frequently appeared to be exaggerated. Melodrama reflected his expectation of being believed without question.

With an eye to the live court proceedings in London, Harry demanded that the BackGrid photo agency surrender their photos. Clearly he had forgotten the ridicule he incited in 2021 after he condemned the First Amendment of the US Constitution, guaranteeing the freedom of the media. BackGrid’s lawyer repeated the mockery. England’s royal prerogative, Harry was told, had been rejected by America more than two hundred years earlier.

Undeterred, Harry demanded an investigation into whether the police should have done more. The NYPD demurred. Harry called the Manhattan district attorney (DA). Impatiently, he demanded that the photographers be prosecuted. After interviewing two photographers and consulting the police officers at the 19th Precinct, the Manhattan DA decided that although the incident was ‘unfortunate’ and the journey was ‘stressful for the passengers’, the photographers were ‘unpleasant but not criminal’. Prince Harry and those speaking on his behalf were incorrect to say the ‘chase’ was ‘near catastrophic’, said the DA. It was ‘not a near-death experience’.

Under pressure from Harry, John Hart, the NYPD’s chief of intelligence, wrote on 18th September 2023 to Chief Superintendent Richard Smith of the Royal Family’s protection unit. Yet Hart’s letter could not have been what Harry expected. Hart confirmed that while the photographers’ conduct had been ‘reckless’ and ‘persistently dangerous’, the incident did not amount to an indictable offence. Nevertheless, Hart added, the NYPD ‘will be enhancing the security resources’ for the Sussexes, starting with a planned visit in October.

In London, the judge would decide that just because photographers were unpleasantly close did not mean that they had a hostile intention to kill Harry and Meghan. Once again Harry’s truthfulness was doubted.

The car chase wiped the awards ceremony off the news agenda. Instead of applause for the couple, there were sniggers and accusations. A-listers realised that having the Sussexes on their guest list posed a threat. Meghan’s publicists might leak details, distracting from the host, and possibly she would cause a scandal.

By now, it was clear that one of Meghan’s skills was to recognise bad news and seek to repair the damage. Philanthropy and ‘service’ was her solution. On 24th May, one week after the car chase, a tragic school shooting killed nineteen students and two teachers in Uvalde, Texas. Twenty-four hours after the news broke, Meghan flew 1,400 miles with a photographer to lay flowers at a shrine. Later, she allowed her accompanying publicist Mandana Dayani to describe how she had sat in a room consoling the grieving families.[450] At precisely the same time, 200 miles from Montecito, Thomas Markle had suffered a life-threatening stroke, yet Meghan did not visit or reach out to her father.

That day displayed an irony about the Sussexes’ world. Both claimed to have fled from Britain partly out of fear (unjustified in truth) that they and Archie would be denied police protection from assassination. Harry was making a huge effort to prove that he was vulnerable to potential murderers in London and needed British taxpayers to fund his protection. In America, both claimed they were safe. Yet the massacre in Uvalde, by no means a rare tragedy, exposed the real dangers of a country flooded by guns used frequently in random shootings.

On the day Meghan flew to Uvalde, Harry lost his claim in London to pay for his armed police protection. The government’s legal costs were £492,000. Generously, the judge ordered Harry to repay just £10,000. His second claim against the Home Office for free protection continued.[451] More importantly, he was gearing up for his day in court against the hated tabloids. The first target was the Mirror Group.

CHAPTER 23

Cross-Examination

Harry did not apologise after arriving a day late in the London court-room, even after Judge Timothy Fancourt’s reprimand. Nothing, he said, could have prevented him celebrating Lilibet’s second birthday in Montecito.[452]

Shortly after the hearing started on 6th June 2023, the first member of the Royal Family since Edward VII in 1891 stood in the witness box to testify against Mirror Group Newspapers (MGN). Four years after Harry and his lawyers had first accused the newspaper group of unlawful information gathering, Court 15 saw the result of thousands of hours of work costing millions of pounds. Dozens of boxes surrounded the barristers as David Sherborne stepped into the spotlight. The Mirror had not offered to pay enough compensation to stop the trial.

‘Call me Prince Harry,’ announced the 38-year-old. The judge ruled that Harry should be addressed as ‘Sir’.[453]

Morland’s cartoon in The Times showed Harry placing his hand on a copy of Spare for the oath: ‘I swear to tell my truth, my whole truth and nothing but my truth.’ The Prince had good reason to be confident. MGN had already paid £105 million in compensation and costs to about six hundred claimants for hiring private investigators to hack into their voicemails or unlawfully obtain personal information. Mirror journalists had used the harvest of private messages as the source of front-page scoops, exposing embarrassing relationships among the rich and famous.

Harry claimed that the Mirror had spent £10.7 million commissioning 114 illegal investigations into his activities and relationships by hacking the mobile telephones of him, his friends and staff. Allegedly, 135 separate payments were made to private investigators searching Harry’s phone and 154 payments for hacking his friends, including Guy Pelly and Mark Dyer, described as Harry’s ‘second dad’, and his former nanny, Tiggy Legge-Bourke. ‘Utterly vile,’ Harry defined the Mirror’s journalists.

Discovering the Mirror’s illegality was time-consuming. His lawyers had looked for embarrassing stories about Harry in the Mirror Group’s newspapers, then searched for the journalists’ sources. First, they scoured the telephone records of the private investigators looking for calls to the mobile phones of Harry’s friends. Then they unearthed the Mirror’s payments to those private investigators who had hacked into voicemails. The lawyers did not know how much incriminating evidence had been destroyed, but the surviving records showed that Harry’s friends had been targeted.

‘A flood of illegality over a period of twenty years,’ Sherborne called it. He blamed Piers Morgan, the Mirror’s editor from 1995 until he was fired in 2004. Morgan, said Sherborne, ‘lies right at the heart of this in a number of ways’.[454] Morgan vigorously denied ever approving any hacking. Only one of the Mirror stories cited by Harry – published in 2002 about Harry and drugs – appeared during Morgan’s tenure and he denied knowing about its source. He would be contradicted during the trial by Omid Scobie. Judge Fancourt accepted that Morgan had openly discussed phone hacking in front of Scobie. In the week after Omid Scobie was shown to be a liar about naming two Royal Family ‘racists’ in the first draft of his book Endgame (to be published later that year), the judge called Scobie a ‘straightforward and reliable witness’. Morgan, who would not be called as a witness, labelled Scobie a ‘deluded fantasist’. Although Harry relied on Scobie’s evidence, he was contemptuous when asked about their relationship.‘I know of him,’ he said.

In his 55-page witness statement for the trial, Harry portrayed himself as an isolated and damaged target exploited by the media. ‘I have experienced hostility from the press since I was born,’ he said. Harry was particularly outraged that, when he was a young man, gangs of paparazzi had waited outside nightclubs swinging intimidating cameras: ‘It was like being swarmed by a rabid mob. Their arms stretched out pushing a button, taking hundreds of photographs all at once with the flash in your face. I couldn’t even see where I was going. As I reached the car, I could hear taunting. I was being egged on for a reaction, knowing I’d been out and had a few drinks.’ In his opinion, the tabloids coaxed a ‘damaged’ young man to excesses: ‘They took great pleasure in knocking me down, time and time again,’ he complained. Especially in their efforts to destroy his relationship with his girlfriend Chelsy Davy.

Blonde and vivacious, Davy had grown up on a game reserve near Victoria Falls in Zimbabwe. After meeting Harry as a teenager at the Berkshire Polo Club, their relationship was forged in Cape Town in 2005. They split up in 2011. He was twenty-seven and she was twenty-six. Harry blamed the tabloids’ hacking for ruining their relationship. Based on the voicemail messages on Davy’s phone, tabloid journalists had written juicy accounts of their stormy relationship.Harry said that at the time he did not realise the phones were being hacked. He assumed that friends and employees were betraying him to Mirror journalists. Not only were the newspaper reports ‘incredibly upsetting’, said Harry, but they also caused him ‘huge bouts of depression and paranoia’ because ‘he could not trust anybody’.

Based on his lawyers’ research, Harry listed incidents where he believed that the Mirror journalists could only have possessed the detailed information about his relationship with Davy by hacking. The stories included: confidential details of Davy’s arrivals at Heathrow; a secret holiday in Bazaruto, a small island off Mozambique, where Mirror journalists and photographers had ‘booked into the hotel before we got there’; a surprise meeting with Davy arranged by his friend Mark Dyer at the El Remanso ranch in Lobos, Argentina, which was a secret even for Harry but not for the Mirror journalists; two stories headlined ‘Harry’s Girl to Dump Him’ and ‘Chelsy Is Not Happy’, reporting that ‘furious’ Davy had given Harry a ‘tongue-lashing down the phone’ after accusing him of flirting with a brunette at the party; and that Chelsy had made twelve phone calls in an hour and ‘begged [Harry] not to be a hero’ by going to Iraq; and then in an ‘emotional phone call’, Davy had asked for a trial separation.

After a private investigator had made six calls on a single day to Davy’s telephones to hear Harry’s voicemails, Mirror journalists reported that Harry had ‘bombarded her with texts and phone calls apologising for the antics that caused the split’ and had ‘repeatedly begged her’ to take him back.

The climax was the Sunday Mirror’s revelation on 25th January 2009 that Davy was ending the relationship.Under the headline, ‘HE just loves boozing & army SHE is fed up & is heading home’, the Mirror reported that Davy had ‘dumped’ the Prince because he loved the Army more than her. The final blast was published on 26th April 2009. Under the headline ‘Chelsy New Fella’, Harry was reportedly ‘bombarding’ Davy with calls asking her to take him back after she told him the truth – she had a new man.

Equally ‘shocking and so blatant’ for Harry were the Mirror’s reports allegedly based on private telephone conversations with his father. One article described Harry’s insistence to Charles that he wanted to join the Army rather than go to university. And following another hacked conversation, the Mirror revealed the details of a disagreement between Charles and Harry about his relationship with Davy. According to the article, Harry had ‘exploded’ after his father mocked their ‘puppy love’. Harry, the Mirror accurately reported, had rebuked his father that he had no right to give lectures on morals and then ‘slammed the phone down’. Shocked by the outburst, Charles had banned Harry from seeing Davy.[455] In Harry’s version, ‘Our lives were entertainment for them. It felt as though the tabloid press thought that they owned me absolutely.’[456]

In their search, Harry’s lawyers found eight private investigator payments for hacking Diana’s phone messages.[457] ‘The thought of Piers Morgan and his band of journalists,’ said Harry, ‘earwigging into my mother’s private and sensitive messages three months prior to her death makes me feel physically sick and even more determined to hold those responsible, including Mr Morgan, accountable for their vile and entirely unjustified behaviour.’

Two years after Morgan left the Mirror, Buckingham Palace read a News of the World story headlined ‘Chelsy Tears Strip Off Harry!’ Two journalists, Clive Goodman and Neville Thurlbeck, described Davy’s fury about Harry’s night at ‘gentlemen’s club’ Spearmint Rhino involving ‘lap dance antics’. The Palace realised that someone’s phone had been hacked. The journalists were arrested in 2006, convicted and jailed. Pertinently, Mirror journalists continued to rely on hacking telephones.

‘It does make you feel completely helpless and hopeless,’ Harry lamented. The Mirror’s lawyers and directors, Harry claimed, ‘covered up the truth, turning a blind eye to ensure that it would continue unabated’. Even the police and the government, he suspected, were ‘too scared to seek justice against them. All ganging up to protect each other, they truly believe they are above the law.’

Expecting to be treated with deference, Harry was not prepared for cross-examination. He never expected his ‘truth’ to be challenged. Representing the Mirror, Andrew Green showed that with one exception, there was ‘no evidence whatsoever’ that the newspapers’ reports about Harry were based on hacking his own phone. Meticulously, Green set out to humiliate the Prince by showing that the Mirror stories were all legally sourced. Mirror journalists had copied stories published earlier in a rival newspaper, cited a BBC report, quoted Harry’s press spokesman or a Buckingham Palace statement, repeated Harry’s own interviews, secured an interview with Mark Dyer or relied on normal journalism – namely, speaking to a bar owner or an eyewitness.[458]

Harry admitted that a Mirror description of his twelfth birthday could not have been produced by hacking because he did not own a mobile until the following year. He appeared surprised when informed that newspapers routinely republished stories appearing in a rival newspaper. ‘I see the similarities,’ he conceded but never admitted a mistake. When told that Chelsy Davy’s uncle Paul Davy spoke frequently to the press, he was silenced. With each confrontation exposing the fallacy of his claim, Harry replied, ‘I didn’t know,’ ‘I wasn’t aware’ or ‘I honestly can’t remember.’

‘Ask the journalists,’ he replied, when he was stumped about contradictions between his court claim and his version in Spare. ‘Which line in this article do you think comes from hacking a phone?’ Green asked. ‘I can’t be sure,’ Harry replied. ‘You would have to ask the journalists themselves.’ Or, when unable to concentrate, the champion of ‘my truth’ waffled, ‘It’s a question for my legal team.’[459] Flummoxed, Harry insisted: ‘Every single one of these articles played a destructive role in my growing up.’ And then he admitted that he had not read the newspapers at the time. Nor had he read most of the articles before they were shown to him in court. His claim that they caused him ‘distress’ appeared suspect.

At the end of five hours’ cross-examination on the first day, the Prince looked unhappy. ‘His accusations were vapid, unsubstantiated and some simply ridiculous,’ sniped the Sun.[460]

Although ordered by the judge not to discuss the case overnight – Harry replied that he would only be FaceTiming with his family – he appeared refreshed the following morning. His replies were markedly different and monosyllabic: ‘Yes’, ‘No’, or ‘The evidence [of hacking] has been destroyed.’

Harry struggled to understand ‘the public interest’. Was a newspaper report that he had received preferential treatment to get into Sandhurst of legitimate public interest? Green asked. ‘No,’ replied Harry. ‘I don’t believe that it affects the wellbeing of society.’[461] That exchange encapsulated Harry’s mindset. Only favourable media reports about him were justified. Anything critical – even if truthful – was malicious and should be suppressed.

The climax of the second day was the Mirror headline ‘Hooray Harry Is Dumped’. The newspaper had reported that Chelsy had ended their relationship.It was, said Harry, particularly ‘hurtful that such a private moment was turned into a bit of a laugh. They were celebrating that I had broken up with my girlfriend.’ Green was incredulous. Did Harry think that the newspaper was celebrating that he was dumped? ‘Yes, I am. I’m the victim of this.’

Did Harry not realise, asked Green, that ‘Hooray’ referred to his class? For ‘Hooray’ to summarise a celebration would have required a comma after the word. Harry was stumped. Eton had not apparently taught him basic grammar. He admitted he had never heard that the term ‘Hooray Henry’ referred to a toff.[462] ‘My mind’s gone blank for a moment,’ he replied with embarrassment.

‘Your case’, Green told Harry, ‘is based on total speculation without any evidential basis whatsoever.’ Harry blinked. It’s likely that no one had ever spoken to him in public like that before. Scotland Yard’s investigation, continued Green, had found no evidence that Harry’s phone had been hacked: ‘Zilch, zero, nada.’ Even the convicted phone hackers giving evidence for the Mirror – Graham Johnson and Dan Evans – did not testify that Harry’s phone was hacked. At the end of his second day in court, Harry admitted that there was no direct evidence his mobile had been hacked. But it would be an ‘injustice’ if he did not win the case.

The common headline in the following day’s newspapers was ‘Total Speculation’. Those headlines, Harry admitted to Sherborne, were ‘even more destructive’. He added, ‘For my whole life, the press has misled me and covered up the wrongdoing.’ Sherborne would turn to the gallery and pronounce that the case was Harry’s campaign to reform the press.[463]

Readers of newspaper accounts of Harry’s cross-examination would have believed that his chance of success was remote. But Sherborne understood the Prince’s advantages. The High Court had decided in 2015 that hacking was rampant in Mirror newspapers and no British judge had ever rejected a civil claim from a member of the Royal Family. Meghan’s successful case against the Mail on Sunday proved that England’s judges were prejudiced against the media, even though the Duchess had signed an inaccurate statement.

As Fancourt considered the evidence that the phones of Harry’s friends had been hacked – his judgement took six months to write and would be issued on 1st December – there was little doubt that the Mirror would lose.

Harry’s anticipated victory against the media was precisely the publicity Meghan appeared determined to avoid. She needed to move away from controversy.

CHAPTER 24

Blow-Up

Rolling Stone’s headline ‘Meghan Markle and Prince Harry are in Their Flop Era’ reflected the mood. A Hollywood sage pronounced that Harry had been transformed from ‘too much soldier, not enough prince’ into an overprivileged snowflake.[464] Harry’s publicists were forced to deny that occasionally he slept in San Vicente Bungalows in Los Angeles or at a hotel in Montecito.[465] His solo act – performing as a royal – was perfect, but an eyewitness noticed that behind the scenes he was flummoxed by any criticism: ‘He was puzzled, and he became worried.’ Not least about Meghan.[466]

Meghan understood some harsh realities. Going through the options, she recognised that casting the Sussexes as a global humanitarian power couple was beyond their financial means. The commitment to ‘service’ and charities suited Harry. Invictus and Sentebale, he acknowledged, had become ‘a bit of a lifeline for me’.[467] But Meghan dreamed of becoming an entrepreneurial influencer like Gwyneth Paltrow or an icon like Michelle Obama and Oprah Winfrey. She recalled Oprah Winfrey’s advice: ‘It was so clear . . . the essence of who you are was about feeling seen, knowing that you’re enough, knowing that you’re beautiful, despite what anybody would say, and putting that essence in a product that could be shared with millions of people.’[468]

Her marriage to Harry naturally fuelled her ambitions. After breaking free from the Palace, she wanted to earn money from commercial endorsements – food, wellness, fashion – just like the famous American lifestyle expert Martha Stewart. To rake in millions of dollars, she thought about launching herself on Instagram, imitating the Kardashians’ lucrative promotions. Meghan urged Ari Emanuel, her William Morris agent, to mastermind her rebirth as an independent celebrity separate from Harry’s battles in Britain, implying to her advisors that fame alone entitled her to success.

Thanks to her agents, Netflix had finally agreed to commission her own lifestyle series to sell her products. Yet the debate about ‘Meghan-aissance’ boomeranged as her advisors tried to answer the question: What was Meghan’s ideal image? Beyond the label, what was her message? ‘I was still in such an incubation stage,’ she would say. ‘Not even of a brand, but just an “ideation” of what it could be.’[469]

All those calculations were manageable until the newspaper headlines splashed in mid-June, disclosing that Spotify had ‘ditched’ the Sussexes. Anonymous Spotify sources accused the Sussexes of failing to meet ‘productivity requirements’ by delivering just one Archetypes series in two and a half years.[470] Crushing headlines described ‘The air going out of their balloon’, ‘A bad day for their brand’, ‘Their star is really falling’ and ‘Spotify pulled the plug’. Joining the gunfire, Jeremy Zimmer, the chief executive of United Talent Agency, was blunt: ‘Turns out Meghan Markle was not a great audio talent, or necessarily any kind of talent.’ One commentator twisted the knife: ‘Just because you’re famous doesn’t make you great at something.’[471]

Meghan did not need Zimmer’s condemnation to tell her she had so far failed Hollywood’s test. To stay on top she needed to offer a stream of original new material. Harry had not helped their cause by criticising Spotify for broadcasting Joe Rogan’s anti-vax conspiracies during Covid. ‘False information,’ Harry had called it.[472]

The Sussexes’ publicists tried to gloss over the humiliation. Reed Hastings, co-founder of Netflix, agreed to praise the Sussexes as ‘smart’ with ‘a great eye for a story’ which generates ‘epic entertainment’.[473] Hastings had forgotten Netflix’s cancellation in April 2022 of Meghan’s proposal for Pearl, the ‘heroic adventures’ of a twelve-year-old girl.

To repair the damage, Netflix’s publicists arranged for the Sussexes’ original series about the Royal Family to be nominated for the Hollywood Critics Association’s Best Streaming Non-Fiction Series award. Even Netflix could not twist enough arms to get a nomination for an Emmy. Netflix also agreed to accelerate the announcement of Archewell buying the film rights of the bestseller Meet Me at the Lake by the Canadian writer Carley Fortune. The Sussexes were tasked to produce the script. Although Meghan had no experience producing films, Netflix agreed to publicise a fanciful ‘$3 million deal’.[474]

But even the Sussexes’ publicity machine could not suffocate the disastrous judgement streamed by Bill Simmons. The 53-year-old who had sold his podcast company to Spotify for $200 million was merciless. ‘I wish I had been involved in the “Meghan and Harry leave Spotify” negotiations,’ said Simmons. He continued, ‘The fucking grifters. That’s the podcast we should have launched with them.’ (‘Grifter’ meaning con artist or petty swindler.)[475]

On his own podcast, Simmons explained, ‘I gotta get drunk one night and tell the story of the Zoom I had with Harry to try and help him with a podcast idea. It’s one of my best stories. He just whines and gives interviews.’ Then Simmons went on: ‘Shoot this guy to the sun. I’m so tired of this guy. Who cares about your life? You weren’t even the favourite son. You live in fucking Montecito and you just sell documentaries and podcasts and nobody cares what you have to say about anything unless you talk about the Royal Family – and you just complain about them.’ As a throwaway afterthought, Simmons added that it was ‘embarrassing’ to be affiliated with Harry.

Outsiders were not allowed to witness the aftermath of Simmons’ damning words. The tension inside the Montecito mansion was, said an insider, ‘hysterical’. Harry ‘fell to pieces’, according to one eyewitness. Meghan was distraught but eventually she could process the rejection. ‘What do you do when despite giving it your all, it still doesn’t work out?’ she asked herself in a podcast. ‘When you still get a no, a crushing no? It’s a lot to process. It makes you question whether chasing your dream is even what you’re meant to do. But here’s the thing, this is precisely the moment that you have to dig deep.You have to use every tool you’ve got and get right back up.’[476] Survival was precisely the lesson she had learned from her father, Thomas Markle.

The termination of the estimated $20 million Spotify contract embarrassed the Sussexes but the serious income continued to flow from Netflix, which was committed to five series over five years. Harry’s Heart of Invictus series was praised for illustrating Harry’s passion and men’s indomitable courage and there was some hope for his future series on polo. Although the audiences would be small, the Sussexes were certain to receive their advance, now authoritatively estimated at $100 million (£81 million).

‘There are plenty of offers on the table,’ Ari Emanuel announced, reflecting optimism rather than reality after Spotify’s announcement. ‘The offers have been pouring in, including from other podcast platforms. This is about building a global brand.’ To give his confidence credibility, Emanuel added, ‘Some big deals will be announced soon.’ The old rumour that Meghan was likely to become the face of Dior was recirculated. Unspoken was the absence of a vital ingredient to turn her celebrity into status. Namely, originality. Meghan was a woman of instinct rather than intellect and imagination.

As before, the Sussexes reshuffled their employees. Harrison Colcord, the head of sales at the local San Ysidro Ranch, was made chief of the Sussexes’ private office.[477] But Colcord could not stop the bad publicity, even for their rare joint appearances on anniversaries. Every outing sparked carping. There was nevertheless some hope that Meghan’s celebration of her forty-second birthday on 4th August would change the narrative.

Meghan’s publicists let it be known that the Sussexes would be eating at Tre Lune, an Italian restaurant in Montecito, with her friend Heather Dorak and her husband Matt Cohen. The silence of others that day reflected the Sussexes’ quandary. For the first time, the Royal Family sent no congratulations. Everyone noticed there was also silence from the Clooneys, the Obamas and other A-list celebrities.

Fuelling speculation about their relationship, Harry was visibly glum at a Beyoncé event in Los Angeles. Wearing an anxiety patch on her wrist, Meghan separately partied with her friend Genevieve Hillis, singer Kelly Rowland and actresses Abigail Spencer and Kerry Washington.[478]

It seemed to many observers that Meghan felt safer among women. She could count on loyal Californian friends, including singer Katy Perry and a ‘wellness group’ specialising in cosmetic products, including entrepreneur Victoria Jackson, Kadi Lee, Myka Harris and the hairstylist Amanda Leone.[479] With women she posed as an equal, reflecting their success as her own. Perhaps she assumed that famous men would not treat her as an equal.

Although she was on the guest list, Meghan stayed away rather than meet the Beckhams in Los Angeles when Harry watched an Inter Miami football match alongside actor Leonardo DiCaprio and basketball legend Magic Johnson. Normally, Meghan would have shone in that environment, but managing their reputational crisis must have felt beyond even her and Harry’s abilities. Four days after Meghan’s birthday, Harry fled to safety.

CHAPTER 25

Out of Africa

Thousands of miles away from his problems, Harry smiled on arriving in Japan with Ignacio ‘Nacho’ Figueras, a suave 46-year-old Argentinian polo player married to an equally attractive Argentinian socialite, Delfina Blaquier. Nacho, the face of Ralph Lauren, undoubtedly benefited from his relationship with Harry. Both played for California’s Los Padres polo team. Alongside Nacho, Harry felt on home turf.

Harry’s trip was financed by the International Sports Promotion Society (ISPS) founded by Haruhisa Handa, a Japanese billionaire. Over the previous ten years, ISPS had raised £10 million for Sentebale, Harry’s charity in Lesotho and Botswana, and was committed to donate a further £1.5 million over three years by sponsoring an annual polo match in America and Singapore. Since the charity’s annual turnover was about £3.5 million, Handa’s donation was important.

To fulfil the sponsorship deal, Harry had agreed to participate in a panel discussion in Tokyo about the combined value of sport, community and philanthropy before heading to a polo match in Singapore. ‘My life is charity – always has been, always will be,’ Harry told the audience.

‘I could happily live here,’ Harry told his hosts.[480] Possibly Harry was being truthful. Japan would be an ideal haven from his overwhelming problems. But by the end of the panel session, Harry had become unhappy. His trip, he discovered, had been mismanaged and Sentebale was facing a crisis.

Harry had first visited Lesotho in 2004 at the age of nineteen during his gap year between leaving Eton and entering Sandhurst. Two years later, he and Prince Seeiso of Lesotho co-founded the charity in honour of their mothers to help the one in four adults who were HIV positive in the nation, the world’s second highest rate of infection. Most sufferers were also victims of extreme poverty. Sentebale – which means forget-me-not in Sesotho – had survived early difficulties. In 2008, it emerged that just £84,000 of the £1.15 million raised through events, including a concert in memory of Diana and a TV documentary featuring Harry, had been spent on helping AIDS orphans. The charity’s first director had been paid £100,000 a year, plus the perks of a four-bedroom villa with staff and a private education for his three children. Thousands of pounds had also been spent on offices and a fleet of new 4x4 vehicles. A new chief executive had rescued the charity, but by 2022, many of the 560 rotating local staff caring for about 78,000 children were complaining about their pay and conditions, not least because one-third were facing disciplinary proceedings. A camp financed by a donor for £250,000 had been effectively abandoned. Harry had not ordered Sentebale’s chief executive Richard Miller to visit Lesotho since his appointment in 2019. Locals in South Africa assumed that Harry was uninterested in the turmoil. Indeed, after arriving in Tokyo, it looked to be true.

Harry’s anger that day in Japan had been triggered by Haruhisa Handa’s loud executive director Midori Miyazaki. Having agreed to just one intimate dinner for twenty people, Harry discovered that Miyazaki had also arranged for him to speak in an arena to over 2,000 people followed by a gala dinner for 250 guests. Harry was expected to meet, greet and speak at both events. He also realised that very few had ever heard of Sentebale. Peeved that he was being ‘manipulated’ and ‘exploited’ by Miyazaki, Harry complained to Sentebale’s new chairwoman, Sophie Chandauka.

Appointed just weeks earlier, Chandauka, a Zimbabwean Oxford graduate and a senior associate at the global law firm Baker McKenzie, was flummoxed but not surprised by Harry’s irritation. Sentebale faced a watershed, she believed. For nearly twenty years, Harry had spoken about his devoted attention to Sentebale, but he had not visited Lesotho for four years and was unaware of the crisis.

Chandauka’s appointment had followed a search by headhunters to find a replacement for the British marketing executive Johnny Hornby, the chairman since 2018. Just weeks before the end of the financial year, Hornby had signalled his exit. One of Hornby’s complaints was Sentebale’s precarious finances. The annual expenditure – roughly £3.5 million – was never covered by its income from international agencies including UNICEF and rich foundations. Every year, the charity was running at an annual loss of about £370,000 and dependent on its reserves. The five staff in the London office cost £600,000 a year. Like the trustees, none of them visited Lesotho and added little to the charity’s operation other than to organise Harry’s two annual polo matches. Even the famous polo matches proved to be of limited value. Each match cost about £400,000 to stage and the profit from donations was only about £350,000, about 18 per cent of Sentebale’s income.

The only relief to the charity’s precarious finances had come in 2022 after Harry contributed £1.1 million from the profits of Spare. But making the charity dependent on Harry’s book disturbed pro-royalist donors. Some supporters had even resigned. And once Harry’s ‘tainted’ donation was spent, Hornby admitted he had no solution to finding more money in Britain. Rich Americans, he agreed, were the charity’s best hope, but he had no contacts.[481] Unexpectedly, Hornby’s fate was sealed after his friend, the television presenter Jeremy Clarkson, publicly ridiculed Meghan. ‘When you cross Harry,’ said one insider, ‘you don’t last long.’

Another potential casualty, Chandauka discovered, was Midori Miyazaki. She had exploited Harry in Tokyo because she knew Sentebale’s finances were dire and that Harry relied on Handa’s donation. But Miyazaki failed to take into account Harry’s moods. Harry, Chandauka discovered, hated talking about money. He expected Chandauka to resolve all the problems created by her predecessors.

At the outset, Harry praised Chandauka’s ‘experience, passion for social change and entrepreneurial spirit’. Between 2015 and 2019 she had sat on Sentebale’s board, and in 2021 had received an MBE for ‘extraordinary services’ to diversity in business. Over the years, Chandauka had worked for Meta, Morgan Stanley and Virgin Money. She had also advised a slew of public companies including Nike, Citibank and Alliance Boots. ‘She will bring’, Harry said, a ‘tremendous benefit to Sentebale’s next chapter.’

With that experience, Chandauka told Harry a harsh truth: Sentebale was struggling. Gleaming SUVs were parked outside its Lesotho headquarters, but some HIV children in the villages appeared to have been abandoned by Sentebale.[482] The charity’s employees in Lesotho had presented a petition to Ntoli Moletsane, Sentebale’s country director, criticising their pay and conditions, and questioning the directors’ use of the charity’s funds.[483] The two directors based in London, Richard Miller and Graham Leith, were earning £350,000 plus many extras and, in her opinion, were overpaid and underperforming. Chandauka did not mention to Harry that a senior Lesotho government official, Chief Khoabane Theko, had complained that after marrying Meghan, Harry had lost interest in the charity and had not visited Lesotho.[484] Chandauka had asked Iain Rawlinson, a former banker who had been based in South Africa and now attached to Global Philanthropic, to support a review of the charity’s strategy.

During her intensive conversations with Harry in Tokyo, Chandauka added that proper governance had become an essential condition of every charity’s funding. Corporate sponsors, Chandauka told Harry, were no longer willing to hand over money without their experts confirming, after due diligence, that Sentebale followed the rules of governance. Sentebale’s amateur accounts and traditional fundraising by Harry and his chums – a smile and a handshake – were unacceptable to potential corporate donors. Harry nodded but with hindsight, Chandauka realised he assumed that while she would do the governance, he would retain control. Better still for him, Chandauka believed, she was African. She should find new donors but he didn’t envisage any change. What Harry wanted, Harry got.

On their flight to Singapore, the outspoken lawyer introduced another unpleasant reality check. Corporate brands hate controversy. After conducting a brand audit among fifty organisations and donors, she told Harry she had discovered that his personal brand value had crashed. ‘People don’t want to be associated with your Netflix shows and especially not with Meghan,’ she reported. The survey also discovered that Meghan had little brand value in America. Across the globe, she actually damaged Harry’s remaining brand value.

Accustomed to being hailed as ‘box office’, Harry was stunned. Johnny Depp, he replied, had still attracted a lot of money despite his bitter courtroom battles with Amber Heard. Couldn’t he do the same? Times have changed, Chandauka replied. The proof was in the finances. Following critical comments about Harry and Meghan on the polo clubs’ websites and suspicions about Harry’s acceptance of a $1 million fee for addressing a conference in Florida organised by a controversial cryptocurrency firm,[485] American polo sponsors had cancelled their donations and Audi had withdrawn its annual $1 million sponsorship.[486] ‘They don’t want to be associated with a Page Six story,’ Chandauka told Harry, referring to the New York Post’s gossip column.

Eyewitnesses at the polo match in Singapore noticed Harry’s coolness towards the new chairwoman. He pointedly failed to introduce Chandauka to guests and only reluctantly posed with her at a photocall, which was itself notable for Harry’s love grab at another man’s nipples.[487] Before Harry left Singapore, Miyazaki revealed that Handa was considering ending his sponsorship of Sentebale. In Harry’s version, Chandauka was to blame because she had allegedly insulted Miyazaki.

Sentebale, Harry told Chandauka, was relying too much on his money and his polo matches. He resented the pressure. He would only commit to future polo matches if the profit was doubled to at least £700,000. Chandauka realised that Harry hadn’t listened. He did not want to register that Spare and the Netflix series had damaged his brand value. And Nacho Figueras, added Chandauka, was hanging on to Harry to stem his own waning attraction.

By September 2023, Harry had understood Chandauka’s warning. At Sentebale’s board meeting, Harry agreed to close the charity’s London office, move the management to Lesotho and find more American donors. Most importantly, the charity would abandon its unique focus on HIV sufferers. Instead, under ‘Project Pivot’, Sentebale would promote children’s health and education. The transformation matched the ambitions of the staff in Lesotho and Botswana. Finally, Harry agreed to re-engage with Sentebale by flying to Lesotho in late 2024, his first visit after five years.

At the same meeting, the trustees considered Harry’s brand value. ‘The more you ascend, the less oxygen you have to tell the truth,’ Jonathan Mildenhall, a marketing expert introduced by Chandauka, told Harry. ‘Spare should have been called Duty,’ Mildenhall continued. ‘Your image is bad,’ the Prince was told. Raising money in America would be difficult because ‘you’re not special.’ ‘How come no one told me?’ asked Harry, puzzled by the term ‘brand audit’.

The solution, Harry agreed, was to abandon the ‘poor rich Prince’ narrative and go back to basics. ‘Americans love a comeback story,’ said Chandauka. ‘We need American corporates who want to be associated with your mission, not you personally. They don’t want your victimhood. We’ve got to pitch it right for the young philanthropists. It can’t be Africans with a begging bowl.’

Days later, Harry and Chandauka’s relationship was tested. To restore goodwill, Chandauka met Midori Miyazaki for dinner at Nobu in New York. After sending back several bottles of champagne for lacking enough ‘bubble’, Miyazaki expressed her outrage that Harry objected to his over-exposure in Tokyo. Shortly after, Chandauka repeated Harry’s request that Handa double his annual donation to £1 million. Miyazaki’s anger soared. Insulted by Harry’s ingratitude for her loyalty after every other sponsor had pulled out, Miyazaki confirmed that Handa would no longer support Sentebale’s polo matches. With that, she ordered an Uber and disappeared. That night, Sentebale lost 23 per cent of its income.

The Nobu bust-up was reported to Harry, who blamed Chandauka for losing the sponsorship.‘Midori says that she won’t sponsor us unless you leave,’ he told Chandauka on a Zoom call. He went further. ‘Your brand audit has damaged me. You shouldn’t have done it.’ Supported by Mark Dyer’s emails, Harry implied that he had suffered psychological harm from the audit. Inevitably, Archewell’s publicists had fuelled their employers’ fears. Harry repeated Meghan’s alarm: Chandauka’s audit had also damaged his wife. The Zoom meeting ended on an unsettled note.

While Sentebale’s fate hung in the balance, a crisis bubbled at another of Harry’s charities. African Parks, a charity with an $83 million (£71.5 million) annual budget enhanced by multi-million-dollar annual grants from the European Union, is dedicated to protecting the wildlife in twenty-three national parks in thirteen African countries from poachers. Harry was persuaded to become the charity’s president in 2017 when the founder, Peter Fearnhead, the son of an Isle of Man fund manager, introduced him to some of America’s and Europe’s richest philanthropists, all donors to the organisation. Harry was doubly impressed after he accompanied six American senators and congressmen on a trip to Mozambique and Rwanda. Like the billionaires and the politicians, Harry said he was attracted to the charity’s ‘business approach to conservation’. It sold biodiversity and carbon credits called ‘verifiable nature units’, and paid bonuses to their ranger army to confront armed poachers. The combination of billionaires and the military appealed to Harry – until in 2023 when he came under pressure to resign as president.

Since 2013, Survival International, a human rights organisation, had accused the charity’s billionaire sponsors of paying African Parks’ rangers to hunt down and suppress West Africa’s Islamist insurgents, sometimes dying in the battles.[488] The Parks’ rangers were also accused of persecuting the indigenous Baka people in neighbouring Congo. The conservation group, according to Survival International’s investigators, had driven the Bakas out of their tribal lands on to barren land without grazing for their herds and denied their access to harvest medicinal herbs. The Bakas’ lands were transformed by ‘green colonialists’ into tourist national parks. African Parks’ armed rangers were also accused of raping and beating the Baka and killing poachers and other indigenous people.[489] Alleged poachers were tortured by ‘the swing’ – hung between branches and beaten.[490] ‘Conservation is for many indigenous people the primary threat to their existence,’ claimed Survival International.[491] In 2023, these allegations were sent to Harry and Meghan.

To distract public attention from the catalogue of crimes, African Parks’ directors suggested to Harry that he switch from president to join the governing board of directors the following year.[492] Seemingly untroubled that the organisation had ceased to be a registered charity, Harry agreed to become more involved in promoting its good name.[493] Either he decided to ignore the allegations against African Parks or else he was motivated by William’s opposition to the charity.[494] While Harry supported fencing to separate humans from animals, William favoured schemes financed by Tusk, a charity that financed locally led schemes and communities protecting the wildlife. To reinforce his attachment to African Parks, Harry agreed to propose to Netflix a documentary, produced and presented by himself, about African Parks’ campaign to protect the continent’s wildlife.[495]

Nevertheless, stung by the negative publicity, Fearnhead commissioned an independent report into the allegations.[496] That was sufficient for Harry to resign as president and join the board. To some, it appeared that Harry was desperate to associate with the billionaires sponsoring the charity.

On his return to California, Harry bumped into more bad news. The Heritage Foundation in Washington DC, a conservative think tank, was probing whether Harry had been truthful in his original 2020 visa application to enter the USA from Canada. One sensitive question was whether he had taken banned drugs. A positive reply would normally mean his entry to America would have been denied. British newspapers had reported his drug habit and Harry had explicitly described himself as a serial drug offender in his book. The foundation appealed to a judge to order the Department of Homeland Security (DHS) to release his visa application.

For the moment, Harry’s status was uncertain: did he enter America on an A-1 head of state visa, exempting him from paying taxes and immune from any prosecution, or an O-1 visa that left him exposed? Unknown to the Heritage Foundation, while Harry publicly insisted that ‘Home for me now, for the time being, is in the States,’[497] his primary residence was still registered as Frogmore. To protect him from the Heritage Foundation, Harry and Meghan asked how they could find help. Everything, they were advised, depended on the Democrats and the Biden administration.

Over the previous two years, Meghan had built a relationship with the Democrat hierarchy in California. Since urging Americans during the 2020 presidential election to ‘reject hate speech, misinformation and online negativity’ associated with Donald Trump, she had visited California’s governor Gavin Newsom, sparking speculation that she was seeking nomination to Congress. That relationship produced critical advice for Harry: the president could prevent a judge ordering the release of his visa application. And indeed the Department of Homeland Security did refuse to release Harry’s application. A judge upheld that rejection.

Harry was also facing new embarrassments in London. In his case against the Home Office, a judge questioned the veracity of Harry’s ‘statements of truth’.[498] Across the city, Sally Davey, the chief executive of his eco-travel campaign Travalyst, had launched the rebranding of the sustainable travel company without mentioning its founder, Harry. After signing up Tripadvisor, Google, Booking.com, Visa and Expedia, Davey decided the Prince was bad for the brand.[499] Not only because of his autobiography but also the hypocrisy of his own statements, as shown in a 2019 Instagram post: ‘There is a ticking clock to protect our planet – with climate change . . . and fossil fuel emissions, we are jeopardising this beautiful place we call home.’ His frequent flights on private jets mocked his piety. While back in Hollywood, an anonymous Netflix source conclusively pronounced about the Sussexes, ‘The lemon has been fully squeezed.’[500] Battered from all sides, no comfort came from his family. There was silence from Buckingham Palace.

‘I thought someone would call,’ Harry told one of his few remaining British friends. Harry gave the impression to his friend that he was looking for reconciliation. Life in California had separated him from his roots. The Sussexes had been stripped of their HRH titles on the Royal Family website,[501] and photographs of Meghan and her children had been excluded from the Royal Collection. Moreover, Misan Harriman’s photograph of the Sussexes appearing at Manchester’s One Young World Summit was itself mired in controversy. ‘I’m humbled and proud to announce that my portrait is now part of the permanent collection at the National Portrait Gallery,’ posted Harriman. But the gallery disagreed. The portrait, said a spokesman, had been delivered without any prior discussion and it would not be displayed.[502] There was worse to come.

The Netflix series and Harry’s book had not sunk the Windsors. America remained fascinated by the Royal Family. Over the previous year since his coronation, Charles had worked hard, broken formality and successfully shrugged aside any notion of being a caretaker king. Americans particularly admired William and Kate. Their refrain from any counter-attack against Harry had won respect. In a Gallup poll organised by People magazine, William was named the world’s most popular and unifying ‘newsmaker’, beating Donald Trump and Joe Biden.[503] On the eve of William flying to New York in early September 2023, Kensington Palace briefed that ‘This trip is part of his evolution as a global statesman which is incredibly important.’[504] The Waleses were serious players. Unlike the endless resignations of the Sussexes’ staff, the Waleses’ household was stable. Their latest requirement for a new chief executive specified their search for a candidate who was ‘emotionally intelligent with low ego and strong self-awareness and understanding of their impact on others’.[505]

William’s problem was in Britain. Polls showed that only 28 per cent of 18 to 24-year-olds supported the monarchy.[506] The younger generation had little affection for the senior royals and, undoubtedly, a substantial number of young Britons sympathised with the Sussexes. To win over the disaffected and ease William’s transition to be the next king, the new Prince and Princess of Wales bombarded the public on social media with videos about their family life, promoting their children and William’s focus on big causes, especially the environment and the homeless.

Alongside their own battle for popularity, William and Kate rejected Harry’s feelers for reconciliation. Neither of the Waleses were willing to forgive the Sussexes. On the contrary, William insisted that Harry be decisively unwelcomed when he returned to Britain on 7th September. Harry’s request to stay overnight in a royal palace, preferably Windsor Castle, was rejected. The staff, he was told, had moved for the summer to Balmoral. He was offered alternative accommodation, which he turned down.[507]

The next day, some members of the Royal Family at Balmoral were commemorating Queen Elizabeth’s life. Harry was not invited, although his spokesman would say that he had rejected the invitation to fly to Scotland. Charles’s short public address thanking the nation for their ‘love and support as we do our utmost to be of service to you all’ raised one unanswered question: Had the Sussexes permanently damaged the monarchy?[508]

Staying at a hotel near Windsor, Harry visited the Queen’s grave inside St George’s Chapel. Inevitably, there was no arrangement for him to call on William, who was actually present at Adelaide Cottage, his four-bedroom home on the Windsor estate.[509] In the evening, Harry headed to the WellChild Awards ceremony at the Hurlingham Club. As the patron since 2007, Harry was warmly welcomed. Over the years, he had donated £750,000 to the charity. Mixing with the parents of seriously ill children, he inevitably spoke about Diana: ‘She is looking down at us tonight.’[510] The emotions were genuine but Harry appeared unable to move on. It appeared to many that he needed applause to escape from his demons. Fortunately, the following day, the Invictus Games offered the chance to show himself at his best.

CHAPTER 26

Düsseldorf

Arriving in Düsseldorf, the Prince commanded the stage. He was the unquestioned star in the Merkur Spiel-Arena. Five hundred competitors and 1,100 family members had come from twenty-one countries to show that war injuries could be overcome. Thanks to the sponsors, the German government and the Invictus organisers, the arena on the opening day was packed for a star-studded music show. ‘Ich bin ein Düsseldorfer,’ cried Harry and the excited crowd stood and cheered and yelled ‘Harry’. However, after the buzzy showbiz event, the mood in the stadium was downbeat and anti-climactic, and for the next two days, Harry pottered around watching the sporting competitions in empty venues. Few paying spectators sat in the cavernous halls. Harry, said his publicist Beth Herlihy, would remain on the sidelines. The star attraction should be the competitors. Meghan, it seemed, had another idea.

On 12th September, the atmosphere in the arena was suddenly electrified. Meghan had arrived. Apologies for the late arrival, she told 1,600 people in an otherwise empty arena built for 54,600 spectators. She had been delayed by family duties: ‘I had to spend a little more time getting our little ones settled at home – three milkshakes and a school drop-off.’ Few outsiders cared about her two minutes of contrived introduction, but her audience was enraptured.

With Meghan in town for the Sussexes’ first joint public appearance since the New York car chase, and the fourth time out together over the previous ten months, Harry was pushed into the background. ‘My husband is a man of few words this evening,’ laughed Meghan as the previously friendly Prince looked noticeably sullen.

Insiders spoke about tensions between them and arguments about their children. Harry was reportedly irritated that Meghan used their children to promote herself. He believed they should remain shielded from the media to avoid the exposure he had suffered as a child. Worried about security, Harry insisted that their children should not be photographed. Meghan argued the opposite. The children, she believed, were important for her brand. She spoke of them living as normal Californian children. More pointedly, she demanded that in time, her little prince and princess should have the same exposure as William and Kate’s children. Eyewitnesses speculated that the tension between the couple was resolved, or perhaps not, in their presidential suite in the Hyatt Regency.

Meghan’s use of her children was a sideshow compared with the real cause of friction between the couple: Düsseldorf became Meghan’s global fashion parade for her brand. Every few hours, her publicist briefed journalists about the latest clothes she was wearing. At first, a black Banana Republic dress, a Bottega Veneta belt and black high-heeled Aquazzura shoes. As the Sussexes entered the arena for wheelchair basketball, her publicist briefed that she was wearing a J. Crew cardigan. After the news hit social media, unprecedented demand crashed the brand’s website. And then she changed into Chanel and Givenchy. The next day she wore Zara, Celine and Saint Laurent. Repeatedly, Meghan posed for selfies.[511]

Even her hair colourist, Kadi Lee, and stylist, Jason Low, were promoted, despite their salon, Highbrow Hippie Haircare, being based in Venice, California. ‘I truly have a soft spot for beautiful brunette hair colour,’ the publicist quoted Meghan. ‘It requires a gentle touch when highlighting or low lighting and adding dimension, and depending on the season can range from deep and striking to glossy and regal.’ The following year, Meghan would invest in the business.[512]

Invictus was Meghan’s stage. A visiting delegation from the organising committee for Vancouver, the next venue for the Games, was dazzled by the Duchess. They even discussed what her high heels would do to a hardwood floor in Vancouver. One delegate’s question remained unanswered: ‘Why doesn’t she just wear Adidas sneakers?’ Another Canadian commented, ‘Her shoes seem out of place.’ Just like the Germans, some of the the Canadians were baffled by Meghan’s use of a disabled servicemen’s event to reinvigorate her profile.

Shortly before arriving, Meghan had announced that DNA tests revealed her mother’s Nigerian ancestry. That became the curtain-raiser at a volleyball competition. Waving the Nigerian flag while standing alongside Nigeria’s defence minister, Mohammed Badaru Abubakar, Meghan privately agreed with the defence minister that she and Harry would make a ‘state visit’ to the country the following year.[513] At the end of the match, she posed as usual for photos. Impatiently, Harry urged her to leave.[514]

Meghan resisted giving any interviews but Harry wanted a platform during his own games. On his publicist’s recommendation, he decided to trust the German ZDF TV journalist Ulrike Grunewald. Alongside him throughout the week, Grunewald dismissed the speculation about the couple’s imminent separation: ‘They seem intimate and very close,’ she reported. ‘Either that or they are very good actors.’ Harry saw no reason not to rely on the German’s assurances of producing a favourable documentary.

To keep Harry in the news, his thirty-ninth birthday dinner, which was celebrated in a traditional bierkeller, the Im Goldenen Kessel, was ‘leaked’ by his publicist to Hello! magazine. Britain’s journalists rushed to Düsseldorf’s old town to witness the end of the dinner. The following morning, his actual birthday, was ignored by the Royal Family. But in the packed stadium – awaiting another star-studded pop concert – Düsseldorf’s mayor Stephan Keller presented a chocolate cake to the Prince. As the stadium sang ‘Happy Birthday to You’, Harry beamed. Meghan did not come on to the stage for Harry’s emotional closing speech, instead deciding to stay out of view.

‘You should not feel lost without your uniform,’ Harry told the competitors. ‘You have provided the magic to impact on millions of people around the world.’ As the stadium rose for a standing ovation, he repeated, ‘Danke schön.’[515]

Having ended on a high note, Harry could not resist attacking his enemies in an aside after he stepped down. The Sun and other British newspapers, he said, had ignored the plight of wounded veterans. That was untrue. The Sun had always sponsored Help for Heroes.[516]

Unseen, the Sussexes flew on to Portugal. Their hosts were Eugenie, Prince Andrew’s younger daughter, and her husband Jack Brooksbank. After promoting George Clooney’s tequila, Brooksbank’s new job was selling plots of land and houses at the Costa Terra Golf & Ocean Club in Melides. The development was founded by Clooney’s business partner. Months later, the Sussexes were said to have bought a plot.[517] That was a fantasy to boost sales. The cold Atlantic and an undeveloped beach were unlikely to be an appealing destination for Californians.

Rejuvenated by success in Düsseldorf, the Sussexes returned to Montecito. The ecstatic welcome in Germany and the positive headlines in Britain reassured both that the bad polling had been buried. Three weeks later, they set off for a new adventure.

CHAPTER 27

Where Billionaires Escape from Millionaires

On 10th October 2023, a convoy of seven SUVs, escorted by police cars with blaring sirens, transported Meghan and Harry from the Equinox Hotel in midtown Manhattan to Brooklyn. The adrenaline rush as they sped through New York’s traffic must have excited the Sussexes. Five months after the now famous ‘catastrophic car chase’, the NYPD provided the Sussexes with VVIP protection.

That morning, the couple were visiting the ‘alternative’ Marcy Lab School for ‘underestimated’ engineering students. Again, Meghan’s publicist briefed the media about her clothes. She had dressed in black skinny jeans, Jennifer Chamandi-designed Mary Jane shoes and a letterman jacket given to her at an Essex school on International Women’s Day in March 2020. Meghan was promoting herself. During a discussion with the students in a computer room about education, she interrupted Harry to express her opinions.[518] He reportedly looked crestfallen, especially when Meghan suddenly interjected, ‘I wish my kids were here with us but they are doing well.’

Back in their hotel suite shortly before lunchtime, Meghan changed into a $2,000 white off-the-shoulder Altuzarra cocktail top and trousers with camel Aquazzura pumps, and had her hair styled in the signature messy chignon. To complete the look, Meghan’s publicist briefed the media that she wore gold bespoke earrings by Sarah Hendler and a $4,100 Logan Hollowell emerald choker. But Meghan and Harry were not heading for a celebrity bash but to meet parents whose children had committed suicide after online bullying.[519]

The Sussexes were hosting their first in-person event. It was called ‘The Archewell Foundation Parents’ Summit: Mental Wellness in a Digital Age’ and they planned to provide a platform for parents navigating their children’s mental health problems, especially families who were ‘passionate about building a safer online world for children and teens’. It was arguably not a coincidence that on the same day, William was hosting a hundred young people in Birmingham to discuss the same on World Mental Health Day.[520]

The Sussexes took a lift to the hotel’s basement garage. The seven-vehicle convoy and police cars were waiting. Exiting the hotel, the convoy turned left into 33rd Street, drove 47 metres and entered the garage of 100 Hudson Yard, the venue for the conference.

Since the morning, hundreds of people had been listening to speeches in many rooms for an event entitled ‘Project Healthy Minds’. The Sussexes hosted what a friendly eyewitness described as an ‘intimate event’ in a ‘cosy room’.[521] Videos showed an audience of fewer than twenty people. Sitting alongside the Sussexes in the panel were NBC’s Carson Daly and Vivek Murthy, the US Surgeon General. To illustrate ‘How the internet and social media affect youth mental health’, two families first described their children’s suicides after watching social media. The question, Vivek Murthy posed, was whether social media caused mental illness among young people.[522]

At a critical moment, Carson Daly turned to Harry and asked, ‘What do you think a healthy social media environment will look like in the future – when you think about the work that your foundation is doing?’ Nonplussed, Harry replied, ‘I don’t know.’ Meghan turned to very briefly stare at Harry and then poured out a lengthy explanation, confirming that neither had a plan for safe social media.[523]

To fill the void, Harry then emphasised that other than Archewell, ‘There’s no one else working in this space.’ The tech companies were so big and so powerful, he said, that they ignored the problem. ‘That’s a reason why I think people are scared and feel helpless.’ This inaccuracy prompted Meghan to steer the discussion towards herself and the anecdotes about her alleged suicidal thoughts when she lived in Kensington Palace.

One year later, the panel’s fifty-minute discussion had attracted a mere 8,500 viewers on YouTube – and over a hundred hostile comments. Some critics wrote that Meghan pretended to influence culture but said nothing unique or creative. A few viewers confirmed there was no mystery about Meghan. Overall, her familiar confessions had left a sense of disappointment.

Hours after the event, the Sussexes drove into Teterboro Airport. A privately owned Dassault Falcon 7X was waiting to fly them to Canouan, a Caribbean island in the Grenadines. The jet’s owner, the British hedge fund financier Ian Wace, had first met William and Kate in June 2011 and co-hosted their first gala charity dinner at Kensington Palace to raise funds for mental health. In 2019, Wace financed the ‘fab four’ to establish Shout, a charity to help young people facing mental problems or ‘a tough moment’, and later he backed a fundraiser for Sentebale.[524] After arriving in California, Meghan and Harry maintained the relationship.Wace’s wife, Saffron Aldridge, a former Ralph Lauren model, enjoyed a wide range of contacts in Hollywood – including Gwyneth Paltrow, Bryan Adams and Sting. A well-connected Hollywood ranker with a private jet is always a helpful friend to have.

Canouan is known as a tax haven for billionaires to escape from millionaires. The island, run by a gruff businessman – who had recently become infamous after an argument over a woman between an Irish hotel owner and an Italian – featured attractions including Donald Trump’s golf courses, a casino and a residence owned by Soho House. Less attractive was the island’s reputation of having an unofficial apartheid system which discriminated against black employees. Canouan’s fishermen were pushed aside to make way for the super-rich. They were denied access to some beaches, teenage pregnancy was rife and they had an absence of a decent secondary school and poor healthcare.[525]

Eyewitnesses reported that the Sussexes appeared untroubled by those abuses as they switched between their villa, Soho House and the empty sandy beaches. For them, the week on a discreet island was an ideal moment to take stock of an exceptionally turbulent four months.

Meghan had been through the wringer enough to recognise that bad could get worse. The previous months had been plagued by indecision and problems. Weighing up the advances against the setbacks since May 2023, the defeats appeared insurmountable – but not for Meghan. ‘Hollywood loves a comeback’ had been her mantra for years. That would be her agenda over the following week.

Canouan’s detached atmosphere allowed Meghan and Harry to review their lives. They could be relieved that Düsseldorf and New York appeared to have repaired the damage sparked by the ‘grifters’ label. Fortunately, Netflix agreed to announce Harry’s polo series and although Amazon Audible had rejected Meghan’s pitch to host a podcast series, Lemonada, a female-founded company seeking to ‘make life suck less’ was delighted to sign up ‘a transformative celebrity’.[526] Crucially, Netflix had also agreed to produce Meghan’s new lifestyle series that would launch American Riviera Orchard, her new brand offering home, garden, food and lifestyle wares. In all, at the end of their holiday they could feel certain of their future path.

A private jet flew them from Canouan to Atlanta. Harry went on alone to Austin, Texas. As the guest of the former Scottish Formula One champion Jackie Stewart, he watched the F1 race won on 22nd October by Red Bull’s Max Verstappen. A private jet flew Harry back to Santa Barbara.

The feel-good moments did not last long. Two days later, cartoon parody show Family Guy showed Harry and Meghan sitting by a pool. A butler presents a wodge of cash.

‘Sir, your millions from Netflix for no one knows what.’

‘Put it with the rest of them,’ orders Harry.[527]

Once again, the couple were seen as entitled grifters. Meghan, as ever, refused to be humiliated and was certain she could contain the latest damage by being photographed with celebrities. Katy Perry’s concert in Las Vegas was ideal. Hitching a ride on Michael Herd’s private jet along with Cameron Diaz, Celine Dion and Zoe Saldaña put Meghan back on track. Harry, however, reportedly could not conceal his boredom, preoccupied with another argument with his father.[528]

During the trip to Las Vegas, there were conflicting newspaper reports about whether Harry had rejected an invitation to Charles’s seventy-fifth birthday party the following week in Clarence House. In reality, Harry was not invited. The fragile relationship with the Palace had been disrupted earlier in the year. Under pressure, the King had agreed to Harry’s suggestion of a private telephone conversation, their first in six months after the Queen’s funeral. To the monarch’s surprise, Montecito publicists later leaked the event to a newspaper as a ‘turning point’. Irritated by Harry’s indiscretion, the Palace was bewildered by the newspaper’s suggestion that the Sussexes would accept a family invitation to Sandringham or Balmoral. Not only would William, Kate and the family refuse to meet the Sussexes, but the King would resist associating with Harry while his litigation against the government continued. In Buckingham Palace, everyone concluded once again that the Sussexes could not be trusted.[529]

Palace officials believed the controversy was created by the Sussexes as a ruse to focus on Charles’s recent state visit to Kenya. Critics, including the Sussexes, had highlighted his refusal to apologise for Britain’s colonial regime. The reason, said anti-royalists, was the King’s racism.

The Palace’s distrust of the Sussexes redoubled after People magazine serialised Endgame, Omid Scobie’s new book about the Royal Family, which was published in November 2023. The Queen’s death, splashed the magazine, created two victims – Harry and Meghan.[530] Originally, the Sussexes had welcomed the opportunity offered by Scobie to stir things up. Now, Meghan simpered, the timing was most unfortunate.

CHAPTER 28

Endgame

The Sussexes trusted Omid Scobie. The Anglo-Iranian journalist, born in Wales in 1981, had loyally reported their distress in Kensington Palace and the Royal Family’s vindictiveness after they fled to California. To boost Meghan’s claim against the Mail on Sunday, Scobie had signed an untruthful statement denying that he had received any assistance from Meghan in writing Finding Freedom, his bestselling book published in August 2020. In reality, he had submitted a long list of questions to the Sussexes’ publicist Jason Knauf and Meghan had answered them at length. Scobie had continued to rely on the Sussexes after their move to Montecito to provide authoritative reports about their thoughts and activities for American magazines and TV. In turn, the Sussexes relied on Scobie to promote their truth.

Scobie was a natural soulmate for Meghan. He enjoyed luxury. On his social media platforms, he posed in a gold smoking jacket, touted Chanel skis, wore expensive jewellery and visited the best restaurants. Proving his loyalty, he had appeared as Harry’s witness in his case against Mirror Group Newspapers and had denounced Piers Morgan as a hacker.

Two years since Finding Freedom’s publication, Scobie and the Sussexes shared a continuing dislike of the Royal Family. Scobie’s vitriol was fuelled by the criticism of his first book and himself. Racism, he believed, had motivated that disapproval. He moved to America and re-categorised himself as ‘mixed race’ instead of Anglo-Iranian. The Royal Family’s ‘racism’, he and the Sussexes agreed, had similarly driven the Sussexes to flee to California. He pronounced that Meghan had been a ‘woman of colour working in an entitled, exceedingly white space’.[531] He concurred with the Sussexes that racism among the Palace’s staff was endemic. That was a good reason for them to collaborate again. Jointly, it seemed, they had a common purpose.

With the Sussexes’ help, Scobie weaved Endgame’s prediction of the monarchy’s sunset or ‘nightfall’ amid Britain’s irreversible decline. The monarchy’s demise had been hastened, Scobie wrote, by the Sussexes’ departure. Supported by the Sussexes, he believed that his intimate portrayal of the Royal Family would be another bombshell. Until publication, its contents were secret.

Scobie’s publishers, HarperCollins, owned by Rupert Murdoch, were impressed by Scobie’s speed in delivering the book. His editors, led by Carrie Thornton, were also certain that he had relied on trustworthy sources at the palaces and especially on Meghan herself. ‘I’m not sure that Harry ever trusted Scobie,’ recalled one editor, ‘but Omid was fed lines by Meghan. And from Harry through another person.’ In particular, his editors assumed that ‘the stuff on Kate – phrases like “Katie Keen” – and the revelations she was “cosplaying Diana” came from Meghan.’ One shocking allegation about the racist royals was also sourced by the editors from the Duchess.[532]

Endgame’s broad canvas, akin to Spare, depicted in Scobie’s words the ‘cantankerous, fragile’ King – ‘a waffler and a dilettante’ whose shoelaces were ironed – of engaging in a perpetual battle against the ‘combustible’, ‘adulterous’, ‘lazy and dishonest’ William. Scobie echoed Harry’s illustration of the tension in the family, fuelled by Charles’s fear that William would ‘upstage’ him. Scobie was naturally pleased by the controversy that wrecked the Cambridges’ visit to Jamaica in 2022.

Echoing the Sussexes’ own damnation of the Royal Family, Scobie described the rival Windsors fighting each other while the corrupt King and his jealous older son, surrounded by ‘a tiny minority of British society – white, privileged and well-heeled’, struggled against growing republicanism as the monarchy ‘crumbled’. Focusing on Charles’s poor decisions, not least about Prince Andrew, Scobie predicted that William would be Britain’s last king. The ‘pliable future Queen’, dismissed as a ‘Stepford-like royal wife’, was obviously ‘scarred’ by her jealousy of Meghan.[533] Scobie had likely satisfied the Duchess’s wish to highlight Kate’s envy.

The Sussexes, in Scobie’s retelling, were the victims of innumerable secret agreements between the media and the Palace. While the Sussexes were convinced about the dissolute disintegration within Buckingham Palace, they were also haunted by conspiracies orchestrated against them, they believed, on the orders of Charles and William. In Harry’s version, William was ‘increasingly comfortable with the Palace’s dirty tricks and the courtiers who dream them up’,[534] mirroring the intensive media campaign waged by Charles after 1996 to rehabilitate Camilla. In that bygone era, a Buckingham Palace official had sniped that Charles reigned over ‘an old-fashioned court filled with a sackful of snakes’.[535] In Scobie’s version, Charles and Camilla ‘had leaked personal details about [Harry’s] life to save their own skin’, while Charles and William combined to destroy Meghan and Harry.[536] No examples of the skulduggery were offered.

For Endgame, Harry’s intermediary told Scobie that the reports about Meghan’s bullying first published in The Times in 2021 were untrue. Two of the three employees, said Harry, had withdrawn their allegations. The third woman was ‘unreliable’.[537] Harry, Scobie added, ‘was gutted that his family would watch this kind of dirty game played out’.[538] Harry, though, never published his 25-page rebuttal of the bullying allegations to prove Meghan’s innocence.

Scobie also described how William had intentionally maligned his brother. William was accused of inspiring false descriptions in the tabloids about Harry’s precarious mental health. ‘It’s pretty disgusting they would pull out the mental health card for this,’ Scobie quoted Harry’s spokesman.[539] Harry’s repeated public confessions about his mental breakdown over the previous seven years were ignored.[540]

The BBC, according to Scobie, co-operated with the Palace’s dirty tricks. In the aftermath of the corporation admitting in 2021 that the Panorama interview with Diana had been obtained by deceit at the highest level within the organisation, the BBC’s Director-General banned further broadcasts of the interview. But in Harry’s opinion, it was Charles who had demanded the suppression of the famous interview. His reason was to ‘derail’ or stifle Diana’s thunderous assertion that Charles was unsuitable to be king. Harry also believed that those describing Diana as fragile and manipulated were authors of a ‘masterful snow job from the Palace’. His spokesman told Scobie that the same smears had been produced against Harry: ‘It’s happening to him too.’[541]

Endgame also gave Harry the opportunity to revise his judgement of Camilla as ‘dangerous’ and ‘evil’. In the new scenario, Harry rowed back. Scobie now set the record straight: ‘There is no animosity on Harry’s side . . . He doesn’t consider Camilla an “evil stepmother”.’[542]

In another revision, Scobie could evidently not resist mischaracterising Charles’s relationship with Camilla. Over the years, royal writers lazily accepted the version that Charles’s request to marry Camilla in the early 1970s had been vetoed by his mother because Camilla was neither a virgin nor an aristocrat.[543] The reality was different. In 1973, Camilla was deeply in love with the dashing army officer Andrew Parker Bowles. She never wanted to marry Charles. After Charles’s phone call from the West Indies – unhappily he was on duty with the Royal Navy – to congratulate Camilla on her engagement, she replaced the receiver and laughed loudly with Andrew Parker Bowles about the ‘Prince being an emotionally immature boy’.[544] Camilla’s misfortune was that Parker Bowles never really loved her. His reluctant proposal of marriage followed his commanding officer’s order that his single status was unacceptable. Officers of the Royal Horse Guards were expected to marry. Camilla was chosen as ‘the best of the bunch’ of his many girlfriends.[545]

Naturally, Harry knew dozens of similar outlandish anecdotes involving his father and brother. Many had been deleted from Spare’s manuscript. But few were as harmful as Harry’s accusation that Buckingham Palace was permeated by uncontrolled racism.

The Sussexes’ agenda was clear. Until the rise of Black Lives Matter in May 2020, Meghan had been relatively silent about race. Her stance altered after returning to California. Implicit in championing her mixed-race background, Meghan joined those criticising white people. Echoing the historians featured on Netflix to highlight the racism implicit in historic furnishings at the palaces, Scobie embellished accusations that the royals’ wealth was ‘built on the backs of others’ from the proceeds of slavery.[546] Not only, wrote Scobie, did Susan Hussey ask Ngozi Fulani ‘at least seven times where she was from’ at the Buckingham Palace reception, but Hussey’s racism was excused by the Royal Family.[547] In Fulani’s original version, the nearly deaf elderly woman asked the question three times.

To hammer home the Palace’s racism,[548] Scobie highlighted Meghan’s comments to Oprah Winfrey about ‘several conversations . . . in those months when I was pregnant’ with the Royal Family about the colour of her unborn son’s skin. Winfrey had summarised the several conversations: ‘They were concerned that if he were too brown that would be a problem?’ Meghan agreed. Meghan’s ‘truth’ fuelled global headlines damning the Royal Family. With the Sussexes’ agreement, Scobie reinforced Meghan’s accusation and gave the firm impression that he had been briefed by the Sussexes’ staff about the letters exchanged between Charles and Meghan following the Winfrey interview, in which the King had allegedly written that there was ‘no ill-will or casual prejudice present when the two people had spoken [to Harry] about his future grandson’.

In the Oprah Winfrey interview, Harry said the single conversation was ‘right at the beginning’ of their relationship ‘before we even got married’. Harry’s teatime conversation in Clarence House in 2016 with Charles and Camilla was, as Harry revealed, light-hearted.[549] Harry was not troubled by the banter until Meghan weaponised it.

Presumably relying on Meghan, Scobie wrote in the draft that the two royals involved in the ‘several conversations’ were Charles and Kate. But Kate was not involved in Harry’s single conversation. The circumstances of those fictitious conversations were not described. Innocent Kate, the future Queen, appeared to have been deliberately stigmatised.

Charles’s and Kate’s names appeared in Scobie’s manuscript until the publishers insisted the names be removed. In their place, Scobie wrote that British laws prevented him from identifying the guilty royals.[550] That excuse avoided accusations of inaccuracy. The manuscript was then distributed to publishers across the world for translation.

In the weeks before the book’s publication, every move by Kate and William was monitored by the Sussexes’ team. It was not a coincidence that just as William landed in Singapore for the third Earthshot Prize in early November, Harry released a video of himself wearing four medals and a poppy with the caption ‘Gingers, an endangered species’.[551]

Meghan chose the eve of the keenly anticipated publication of Endgame as the moment to stage yet another relaunch. Meghan, her publicists said, was making a ‘strategic effort’ to pose as a ‘power player’. Although her brand American Riviera Orchard remained a secret, her publicists quoted her impatience: ‘We have so many exciting things on the slate. I can’t wait until we announce them.’ To fill the vacuum, Meghan muttered about creating ‘things that make people feel a sense of community’.[552]

The venue Meghan chose to stage her latest relaunch without Harry was the red carpet at the Power of Women Hollywood gala hosted by Variety magazine. Standing with Universal Studio Group chairwoman Pearlena Igbokwe and Janet Yang, president of the Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences, she was ‘thrilled’ to be back in the entertainment business. Other guests included Mariah Carey, Emily Blunt, Terri Seymour and Leonardo DiCaprio. None featured with Meghan in any photographs.

Her rare appearance in Hollywood generated attention but raised questions about her ability to translate the publicity into hard cash. Even Scobie admitted that standing on the red carpet was just another photo opportunity. ‘They really need to establish what their purpose is,’ he volunteered.[553] Being seen with Harry was deemed unwise unless the reach was global. The Sussexes decided not to publicise a joint visit to the Navy SEALs’ fitness base in San Diego ahead of Remembrance Sunday.[554] But the Invictus Games was different.

On 21st November 2003, Meghan appeared at an ice hockey game in Vancouver with Harry to publicise the next Invictus Games, which were set for 2025. Meghan waved at fans and recalled her stint in Suits, filmed in Toronto, and Harry dropped the puck to start the game.

In London, in the week before Endgame’s publication, the Windsors agreed ‘not to be emotionally blackmailed’ by Harry.[555] The whole Royal Family was summoned to welcome the president of South Korea and his wife to Buckingham Palace for a state dinner.[556] Charles had just returned to London after speaking at COP28 in Dubai. William and Kate had hosted a formal reception at the Royal Albert Hall. Unity in strength was the Palace’s agenda.

On 24th November, Scobie launched his book. Speaking authoritatively in interviews, he boasted that ‘people around’ the Sussexes had briefed him about the ‘ins and outs’ of the Sussexes’ battles with the Royal Family.[557] As an insider, Scobie said with certainty that the Sussexes had become ‘disruptors’ because Charles mishandled their decision to leave. They had been in ‘a desperate place’. They simply wanted to be heard, but Charles was too stubborn. Harry, he said, wanted to ‘forget’ his recent troubles and end the feud with his family – if necessary, without an apology. But Meghan would have nothing to do with the royals. She would never set foot in England again, he said.[558] Some in the Palace would say that rather than ‘disruptors’, the Sussexes were ‘destroyers’.

Scobie attacked the Royal Family for trying to ‘sweep’ the issue of race under the rug and not ‘properly address’ its prejudice. Scobie then said that Meghan’s letter to Charles had accused the Royal Family of ‘unconscious bias’. She had never suggested that they were racist.[559]

As the Sussexes’ mouthpiece, Scobie faced a tricky question. He was asked why the Sussexes were entitled to brief him against the Royal Family, but if Buckingham Palace briefed about the Sussexes it was a conspiracy to undermine the couple. Quickly, Scobie denied any relationship with Harry and Meghan.[560]

And Scobie was asked to reconcile another contradiction. Why had Meghan sued the Mail on Sunday after her letter to her father was leaked on the grounds of privacy, yet someone on her staff had leaked Charles’s letter to her about racism? Scobie remained silent. Meghan would deny that she had leaked Charles’s letter but as an English court had commented, she had previously suffered from an ‘unfortunate lapse of memory’.

Within three days, Scobie was under pressure from the media to confirm the identity of the two royals accused by Meghan of racism. Unexpectedly, the names Charles and Kate had been printed in the Dutch edition. Scobie emphatically denied any responsibility. ‘I never submitted a book that had their names in it,’ he told one TV programme. ‘There’s never been a version that I’ve produced that has names in it,’ he told another interviewer. He blamed ‘translation errors’ for the inclusion. He even swore on his parents’ lives that his denials were the truth.[561]

Few could believe that Charles’s and Kate’s names had appeared in the Dutch edition unless written by Scobie. He had form though, previously saying he was thirty-three years old when he was thirty-eight.[562] At the beginning of December, the Dutch translators volunteered that they did not invent that content. The names had been in Scobie’s manuscript. Pertinently, the Sussexes refused to comment.

‘Omid is his own worst enemy,’ declared a senior editor at HarperCollins in New York. Renamed internally as ‘Endpapers’, the book was suddenly ‘problematic’. In telephone calls to his editors, Scobie complained, ‘Everyone in Britain hates me.’[563]

Ten days after publication, Scobie surrendered. He admitted that ‘an early and uncleared text’ did contain the two names. The scrutiny, he complained, ‘has caused me a lot of frustration’.[564] The author’s credibility was shredded.

Neither of the Sussexes denounced Endgame. Few believed their perfunctory denial of any involvement with Scobie’s book. Once again, it appeared to many that the Sussexes had crossed the line. The year that started with Harry’s book and ended with Scobie’s ended any speculation about reconciliation. Endgame, some believed, was the Sussexes’ last throw of the dice.

CHAPTER 29

The Biggest Losers

The Hollywood Reporter crowned the Sussexes the ‘Biggest Losers’ of 2023. In the aftermath of their ‘whiny’ Netflix documentary and Harry’s ‘whiny biography’, the Reporter chortled that everything had gone wrong. Endgame had sealed their fate. Scobie’s lies had fuelled a crisis of trust in the Sussexes’ brand: ‘The Harry and Meghan brand swelled into a sanctimonious bubble just bursting to be popped – and South Park was the pin.’[565]

The Sussexes’ brand was confused between self-promotion, philanthropy and anti-Royalism. Associating with the Sussexes, more celebrities apparently agreed, was unwise. Seen as troublemakers, the Sussexes were denied an invitation to the Duke of Westminster’s wedding at Chester Cathedral, even though the bridegroom, Hugh Grosvenor, was a godfather to Archie. Harry was also excluded from They Also Served, Sandhurst’s guide to its two hundred most notable alumni. William wrote the book’s foreword.[566]

The kickback damaged Archewell. Despite a glossy promotional video featuring the Sussexes hugging veterans, donating school bags and taking selfies with fans, the commentary citing Archewell’s ambition as an ‘impact-driven global non-profit organisation that puts compassion into action’ could not conceal a financial crisis. Donations to Archewell in 2022 had fallen from £10.3 million to £1.6 million, and that money was from only two unnamed donors. The corporation’s annual loss was £536,357 ($647,485). Just $950,000 in gifts had been spent: on a gender justice initiative ($200,000), flood relief in Nigeria ($20,000), the anti-landmine Halo Trust and a play space for children in Uvalde, Texas, after the school massacre. Archewell’s chief of staff James Holt, paid annually £180,835, halted further payments apart from $127,807 to the London-based publicists Herlihy Loughran for ‘programmatic strategic support’ and $120,000 to a digital consultant, Jiore Craig. Archewell’s purpose to ‘put compassion into action’ was falling flat.

There was improvement during 2023. Archewell raised $5.7 million – $5 million from Fidelity Charitable and $10,050 from Tisbet Philanthropy – but they handed out $1.3 million while bearing expenses of $1.9 million.[567] The grim news concealed the Sussexes’ generous sponsorship of one unknown charity, the Women’s Wellness Space in Philadelphia. A drop-in space for traumatised women created and managed by President Biden’s daughter Ashley, a 43-year-old social worker, the charity received $250,000 from Archewell, the highest donation the foundation made that year.[568] At what was described as a ‘developing endeavour rather than something that’s already set up’, the women were given a healthy meal, meditated and received therapy, specifically eye movement desensitisation and reprocessing (EMDR) treatment. Sympathising with ‘trauma’, the Sussexes declared themselves ‘dedicated to illuminating thought-provoking and diverse narratives’.[569] Archewell’s highest donation that year was brokered by the President’s sister, close confidante and campaign manager Valerie Biden Owens.[570] Shortly before making the donation, Biden Owens had ‘endorsed’ Meghan as a ‘good presidential candidate one day’.

Archewell’s donation also coincided with the Heritage Foundation’s renewed attempts to secure Harry’s visa application. ‘The Biden administration went to great lengths to prevent the release of Harry’s records,’ recalled the Foundation’s director, Nile Gardiner. He wondered whether the Prince and his wife had received ‘special treatment’ from the White House.[571] Gardiner’s opinion was reinforced by John Kerry, the unsuccessful Democratic presidential candidate in 2004 who had travelled with Jill Biden to Charles’s coronation. Kerry told Lady Anne Glenconner, ‘We all feel very, very sorry for Harry.’[572]

Suspicions about the Sussexes’ relationship with the Bidens were fuelled by Ashley Biden’s tax return. She registered the Women’s Wellness Space total income in 2023 as $170,296. Yet she had received $250,000 from Archewell and a further $250,000 from another charity supporting President Biden.[573] Ashley Biden had failed not only to declare the $500,000 but she also claimed that no donation had exceeded more than $5,000.[574] Grateful that President Biden’s office was blocking the release of Harry’s visa application, the Sussexes remained silent.

The mystery was compounded by Archewell’s own accounts. Although the charity claimed to have received just over $5 million, that year’s accounts showed income of only $2,000,911. Archewell would deny that it did not declare $3 million of income, but nor did it explain the discrepancy.[575] The accounts and their donation to Ashley Biden reflected the Sussexes’ tangled lives.

* * *

Just before Christmas, Harry’s search for favourable publicity took another hit. Kensington Palace posted a video of Kate and her children meeting babies, and staged a photocall of Charles, Camilla, Kate and William at a glittering evening reception for five hundred diplomats in Buckingham Palace. Hours later, Archewell released an unremarkable promotional video of the Sussex family. The battle of the videos coincided with mixed results for Harry in London’s courts.

Just before Christmas, Harry could claim a victory but not an overwhelming triumph. In his case against the Mirror, Judge Fancourt declared there was ‘compelling evidence’ that all the newspapers’ editors including Piers Morgan ‘knew very well’ that phone hacking had been ‘widespread’ and ‘habitual’. The untraceable burner phones used by the private investigators hired by the Mirror explained the lack of records.

But, said the judge, Harry was the victim of phone hacking only ‘to a modest extent’. Nearly half of Harry’s claims (fifteen out of thirty-three) were dismissed. In the remainder, Fancourt decided that the journalists describing Harry’s thoughts and plans could only have discovered these facts by hacking Harry’s friends’ phones between 2002 and 2011.[576] The other articles Harry had cited relied either on standard journalistic reporting or were copied from other newspapers.[577]

For the Mirror, the principal question was the amount of damages. Green (representing the Mirror) had told the judge that Harry should receive no more than £50 on each confirmed ‘hack’. The damages should be ‘low’ because he hadn’t read the newspapers at the time of his relationship with Chelsy Davy. Sherborne countered that he should receive £570,000. The judge criticised Sherborne for pursuing ‘outlandish claims’[578] and, after meticulously calculating each confirmed allegation, awarded Harry £140,600. Since the lawyer reportedly expected to earn over £4 million for his work, the judge’s criticism was tolerable.

Harry hailed his victory as ‘a great day for truth: I’ve been told that slaying dragons will get you burned. But in light of today’s victory and the importance of doing what is needed for a free and honest press, it is a worthwhile price to pay. The mission continues.’ Especially against Piers Morgan.[579]

‘Prince Harry’s outrage at media intrusion into the private lives of the Royal Family,’ replied Morgan, ‘is only matched by his own ruthless, greedy and hypocritical enthusiasm for doing it himself.’ He continued: ‘He says he is on a mission to reform the media when it is clear that his real mission, along with his wife, is to destroy the British monarchy. I totally agree with Prince Harry that the ruthless intrusion into the private lives of the Royal Family for financial gain is utterly reprehensible. I just wish he’d stop doing it.’

In the wake of his victory, Sherborne announced Harry’s continuing fight against the Mirror on another 115 stories and a bid to recover £2 million for his legal costs.[580] But in the end, Harry climbed down. Offered a ‘substantial additional sum’ by the Mirror, the insurers pocketed a decent profit and settled Harry’s four-year battle. Harry’s ‘winnings’ were comparatively small. The Mirror’s lawyers were delighted by the outcome.[581]

The Mail on Sunday’s lawyers were also thrilled that Harry had surrendered. Perhaps fearing the consequences of handing over sensitive documents to the newspaper, he immediately paid the newspaper £48,000, just part of the £750,000 in total costs. The newspaper welcomed Harry’s ‘embarrassing defeat’.[582]

During those same weeks, a third team of Harry’s lawyers were engaged in another London courtroom. Those lawyers were still arguing that the Home Office should provide, at the taxpayers’ expense, armed protection for Harry and his family in Britain. To support his case, Harry declared in a statement: ‘The UK is my home. The UK is central to the heritage of my children and a place where I want them to feel at home.’ He made no attempt to reconcile that statement with his CBS interview – ‘I want to live in America’ – or telling NBC, ‘Home is the States.’[583] [584]

Harry presented a new scenario for his case. He and Meghan had not fled from Britain because of the media’s intrusion into their privacy or the Royal Family’s racism, but rather because Buckingham Palace was unwilling to protect them from assassination. Murderers, Harry suggested, lurked everywhere.

In this battle, Harry’s hurdle was again a lack of evidence. Neither the intelligence services nor the police had found any credible threat to the Sussexes’ lives. Ravec’s chairman Richard Mottram’s reply to Harry’s protests was an assurance that with ‘finite public resources’, Ravec would examine the potential threats before each visit for a non-working royal who chose to leave Britain.[585] That ‘bespoke’ arrangement still did not suit Harry. He wanted an unqualified, permanent commitment. To boost his argument, he turned again to the ‘catastrophic car chase’ in New York.

Disappointed that John Hart, the New York Police Department’s chief of intelligence, denied that the car chase had been a threat to his life and by the state’s refusal to prosecute the photographers, Harry called California’s Democrat governor, Gavin Newsom. The Prince asked for the photographers to be prosecuted in California. After that failed, he asked the governor to bring pressure on Manhattan’s lawyers to bring a charge. The enquiry from Newsom’s office astonished the Manhattan prosecutors. ‘Prince Harry was heavy-handed and super-privileged about what he thought we should do and the criminal process,’ observed New York’s senior prosecutor. ‘I don’t think it helped his case that he thought he could expedite a favourable outcome by going through the Californian jurisdiction. He didn’t understand the American legal system. But I get it. He’s royalty, so it might be second nature to act like that. The Prince was naïve. It just wasn’t an effective tactic.’[586]

Harry’s American lawyers scored one success. On 6th December, in the middle of yet another court hearing in London, Harry’s lawyers presented a second letter from John Hart. The intelligence chief’s description of the chase was identical to his original letter but he came to an opposite conclusion. Namely, that there was after all sufficient evidence to prosecute two photographers. ‘New evidence has come to light,’ Hart explained. There was sufficient grounds on which to arrest two ‘individuals’ for reckless endangerment.[587] Hart’s letter was dismissed as a ruse. He refused to disclose why he had somersaulted.[588] Many suspected that Newsom, under pressure from Harry and his lawyers, had after all influenced Hart. One year later, the governor would also publicly defend the Sussexes against allegations that Archewell had failed to properly file its annual returns.[589]

To Harry’s surprise, nothing happened in New York. No photographers were prosecuted. In a letter to the New York district attorney, Harry accused the city’s prosecutors of ‘intentionally misleading’ him in pursuit of a ‘cover-up’. He won no converts. ‘Prince Harry was very overbearing,’ recalled a prosecutor.[590]

The day after Hart’s letter was released in London, the government gave the trial judge the letter written after the Sandringham summit by Edward Young to Mark Sedwill, the Cabinet Secretary. Young stressed that the Sussexes’ safety was of ‘paramount importance to Her Majesty’. The letter demolished Harry’s complaint that Young was prejudiced against providing protection and, noticeably, Young did not mention Harry’s offer to pay for his security in Britain.[591]

In his judgement, Peter Lane rejected Harry’s case. Ravec’s ‘bespoke’ process, said the judge, was legally sound and their decision to deny Harry permanent protection was not made with any ‘irrationality or unlawfulness’.

As Harry had ‘comprehensively lost’ his case he was ordered to pay 90 per cent of the Home Office’s costs, £514,000. His own legal costs were about £1 million. He was not given the right to appeal.

In a burst of anger towards a judge who dared to reject his truth, Harry had ignored the judge’s direction that Ravec’s security memoranda were subject to the Official Secrets Act. He sent the secret reports used by Ravec to Johnny Mercer, a Conservative MP and an Afghan veteran.[592] In doing so, Harry showed that he felt he was beyond the law.

CHAPTER 30

A Living Legend

Harry was now avidly searching for opportunities to present himself in the best light. Fortunately, the organisers of the Living Legend of Aviation award at Los Angeles’s Beverly Hilton on 19th January 2024 were looking for a publicity boost. Those casting the awards list approached Harry, hoping that Meghan would accompany him. To the organisers’ delight, Harry agreed to accept the award from John Travolta. The actor was famous for his shimmering performance during his White House dance with Diana in 1985. Harry’s father was photographed seething with jealousy as he watched his dazzling wife with the Saturday Night Fever heart-throb – ‘like a lemon’, wrote one observer.

Previous recipients of the award were Buzz Aldrin, the second astronaut to walk on the moon, and Captain Chesley Sullenberger, who in 2009 safely landed an Airbus with 155 passengers and crew on the Hudson River. Harry was listed on the night’s programme as a pilot in Afghanistan. In truth, Harry was an Apache helicopter’s gunner and a co-pilot. ‘He is not a living legend of aviation,’ scoffed Admiral Lord West, the former head of the Royal Navy after the announcement. ‘To suggest he is, is pathetic.’[593]

Another prizewinner that night would be Lauren Sanchez, the 54-year-old partner of Amazon’s founder, Jeff Bezos, then worth an estimated $130 billion. Sanchez won a prize for qualifying as a helicopter pilot. Nothing else, except her presence at the event also guaranteed media coverage.

Though her absence from the Living Legend award ceremony was excused with the usual formula – ‘caring for a sick child’ –[594] Meghan’s decision not to join Harry at the $1,000-a-ticket event could be viewed as strategic. Self-made Lauren Sanchez lived not only in a $165 million Beverly Hills mansion but also in Bezos’s outstanding homes scattered across the country. Lauren also enjoyed Bezos’s fleet of mega-yachts and private jets, and she wore the most expensive dresses showing off her remarkable figure. Compared to Archewell’s meagre finances, the Bezos Earth Fund’s budget was $10 billion, and among their other charities the Bezos Award for Courage and Civility gave away $78 million a year. Even on her five-inch stilettos, Meghan would be dwarfed by Sanchez’s exuberance.

To the Sussexes’ dismay, they had not been included on the guest list for Jeff Bezos’s sixtieth birthday party four days later. As Meghan knew, many of her famous neighbours were invited, including Oprah Winfrey and Katy Perry. Other A-listers to receive invites included Beyoncé, Kim Kardashian, Jay-Z and Bill Gates. To Meghan’s disappointment, even with her duchess title, she was not included as one of them.

On the evening of the Living Legend awards, Lauren Sanchez posted a photo with Harry on her website. She hailed the two prizewinners for having ‘shaped the history and future of flight’. Harry also posed for pictures with Prince Mario-Max Schaumburg-Lippe, a local resident invited to add more royal glamour.[595]

Harry played his part. Replying to Travolta’s recollection of the famous dance, Harry told the audience: ‘I was just one year old when you danced with my mum, as you’ve told everybody here, and continue to dine out on that probably every single night.’ In better humour, he mentioned that when his father took over the controls of a Westland helicopter, ‘I was terrified.’ Harry welcomed the laughter.

In his speech, he did not acknowledge the news that had captured the world’s attention earlier that day, which was the public announcement that both Charles and Kate had been admitted to the London Clinic. Both were having surgery – Charles for an enlarged prostate and 42-year-old Kate for ‘non-cancerous’ abdominal surgery.[596] No get well messages from the Sussexes had been sent. William noted his brother’s silence.[597]

In fact, spotted leaving a fitness club earlier that day, Harry had maintained his silence.[598] His appearance in Montecito village appeared contrived. His home had its own gym. It appeared obvious to many that he had wanted to be seen.

Britain, Harry knew, was rocked by the news. Charles was vulnerable. Just months after the death of the Queen and Prince Philip, the King faced the chill of mortality. Having championed a slimmed-down monarchy, Charles knew that Buckingham Palace’s balcony would be disturbingly empty.

Four days after collecting his award from John Travolta, Harry ignored the Bezos snub and grabbed another opportunity to shine in the media headlines. Invited by Paramount’s chief executive Brian Robbins to the premiere in Jamaica of One Love, a Bob Marley biopic, the Sussexes arrived in a Gulfstream jet with Tracy Robbins, their neighbour in Montecito. They had celebrated their sixth wedding anniversary with the Robbins at Montecito’s Lucky’s Steakhouse, famous for its $175 Porterhouse steak. The Robbins had also not been invited to Bezos’s birthday bash.

Brian Robbins’ career was the sort of Hollywood success story Meghan was keen to emulate. He had started his career as an actor and had become a writer/director with a string of successful hits, including PAW Patrol. Then he was appointed as a studio chief.

‘I had to be here,’ Harry beamed as he stood on a stained red carpet in Kingston, Jamaica. Just as Charles and Kate were struggling in hospital, Harry and Meghan were thrilled to find the spotlight alongside one of the Royal Family’s bitter critics – Andrew Holness, the prime minister of Jamaica. Harry showed no concern that Holness had orchestrated a calculated embarrassment of his family and Britain on TV during William and Kate’s 2022 visit. On the contrary, Harry and Meghan flew to Jamaica knowing that Holness wanted to remove the King as Jamaica’s head of state.

Paramount’s publicists had rightly calculated that the film premiere in Kingston’s shabby Theatre 1 would be ignored without the Sussexes’ presence. Certainly, the after-party at the unexceptional Terra Nova All-Suite Hotel would have been overlooked if the royals had not sat in the VIP enclosure. Jamaicans, the publicists knew, had fond memories of Harry’s official visit in 2012 for the Queen’s Diamond Jubilee. The highlight was his friendly ‘race’ against Olympic champion sprinter Usain Bolt. Few were aware that Meghan’s short-lived first marriage had been celebrated during a four-day beach party in 2011 at the Jamaica Inn. All her guests had been given a pouch of cannabis. No photos existed of that celebration. Meghan had destroyed them all before she left the island.[599]

The British High Commissioner, Judith Slater, heard by accident that the King’s son had landed in Jamaica the day before the premiere. The couple had stayed overnight in Montego Bay’s Half Moon Resort. Although invited to the film premiere, Slater kept her distance. Critics, she suspected, would pinpoint Harry’s ‘reckless misunderstanding of how his appearance was represented across the globe – an endorsement of pro-Marxist ideology’.[600] After all, in a video for the Queen’s Commonwealth Trust in 2020, the couple had hailed Black Lives Matter as a ‘moment of reckoning’ for the guilty whites. They had also advised the Commonwealth to acknowledge its ‘uncomfortable’ past and warned that ‘change is needed and is coming’. After the Cambridges’ disastrous visit to Jamaica during her tenure, she decided to stay out of sight.

Standing alongside Holness and his wife Juliet, Meghan exuded Hollywood glamour. Dressed in a black shoulderless Carolina Herrera maxi skirt, her publicist briefed that she was carrying a Jimmy Choo black ‘J Box’ clutch and was wearing a Cartier Love bangle and $3,000 earrings by Californian designer Jennifer Meyer. But other than the sun, little shone in that unglamorous town. Except gossip about the Sussexes.

Weeks earlier, Meghan’s publicist had told US Weekly that 2024 would be Meghan’s ‘year of redemption’ and her year of ‘revival’. But until the announcement of her new ‘slate’, said their spokeswoman, the Sussexes would keep a low profile.[601] Now was the comeback.

Newspapers hired body analysts to judge the state of the Sussexes’ marriage. Meghan defied them. As usual, her ‘purring rituals with her soft doe-eye-smile’ put on a show of ‘mutual affection’. With her hands of ‘loving ownership’ all over Harry, the message was ‘he’s mine’. By ‘placing a hand on his back to usher him forward in steering gestures, she put herself in charge’.[602] As a bid for publicity the visit was a success.

After their return to California on Paramount’s Bombardier jet, the news was familiar. Another Archewell employee, Bennett Levine, a TV production manager, had resigned. The departure of the fifth executive to leave in recent months signalled an unfortunate fact: the Sussexes’ ‘slate’ was uninteresting, the atmosphere in Montecito was uncomfortable and the Sussexes were being widely mocked.[603]

At the Golden Globes in Los Angeles, Netflix’s chief Ted Sandaros was asked by the host Jo Koy why Harry and Meghan had pocketed ‘millions of dollars for doing absolutely nothing’. Meghan’s normally loquacious neighbour just smiled. He could do without the embarrassment. The American Riviera Orchard and polo series were on the horizon. The Sussexes were excited, but they were also scrabbling.

Meghan decided once again to rebrand Archewell. Three years earlier, on the Palace’s orders, they had closed the ‘Sussexroyal’ website and promoted Archewell. That compromise no longer suited Meghan. In her latest makeover, the commercial website was reopened and headed ‘The Office of Prince Harry and Meghan. The Duke and Duchess of Sussex.’ At the top of the Sussex.com website was the coat of arms given to Meghan by the Queen after her marriage. Harry and Meghan knew that using their royal titles for financial gain broke the Sandringham agreement with the Queen. But trading as a royal had become irresistible.

On the rebranded website Meghan identified herself as ‘One of the most influential women in the world’. In the colossal scale of her self-esteem, Meghan genuinely believed in her own importance as a ‘feminist and champion of human rights and gender equality’.[604]

The new website described Harry as a ‘humanitarian, military veteran, mental health advocate and environmental campaigner’. His adult life, the bio continued, was ‘dedicated to advancing causes that he was passionate about and that advance permanent change for people and places’. Archewell’s mission statement was explicit: ‘Shaping the future through business and philanthropy’. Quite explicitly, Archewell was positioned not as a charity but as a business to promote the Sussexes.

In anticipation of the relaunch, Archewell churned out press statements about children’s wellbeing and child abuse on the internet. ‘Turn pain into purpose,’ urged Harry. Meghan could not resist personalising her sound bite. ‘Days are long but years are short,’ she reminisced about her rush to Uvalde, Texas, after a school shooting. Both Sussexes used grief as empowerment to speak with heavy hearts.[605] Few remembered that on the day Meghan dashed to Uvalde, she chose not to drive three hours to see her father, Thomas, stricken by a stroke.

Back in Britain, there was more bad news on the horizon.

CHAPTER 31

Bad Optics

Just as Archewell was pumping out its mission statements, on 5th February, Harry read online that King Charles’s prostate problems had revealed the ‘early’ stages of cancer. Doctors said that his prognosis was ‘positive’. While refusing to define the type of cancer, Charles stopped all his public duties. He would live in Sandringham and travel to London for weekly treatment. Under the revised Regency Act, Prince Edward and Princess Anne could act on Charles’s behalf. Harry had been excluded.

Charles’s friends reported that the King took the news badly. Fearful of his mortality, he had plunged into depression and, his few visitors noticed, became surprisingly frail. ‘This is awful,’ Charles heard a courtier exclaim. The apprehension was not only about the King’s cancer but the threat of an early death. William, some officials agreed, was not ready to become the monarch.

Among senior courtiers, several were concerned that the 42-year-old heir did not yet fully understand the monarchy’s traditions, symbolism and history. They questioned whether William would be equipped to keep the institution well anchored in a country losing its cultural identity. ‘William’s still too fluid,’ said a courtier. A strong monarch was required to manage any necessary changes without bowing to gusts of destabilising opinions. Some were particularly alarmed by William’s suggestion after the coronation that his own ceremony would be shorter and with fewer symbolic rituals. Compared to Charles, William’s grasp of the detailed aspects of a coronation’s historic roots was judged to be flimsy. History, as William admitted, was not his strength. Andrew Gailey, chosen, as a noted historian, to be William’s housemaster at Eton, had failed to excite the heir about his inheritance.

Insiders fretted about the absence in Buckingham Palace of any authoritative veteran to persuade William to study the nation’s history. Former wise men including Martin Charteris, David Ogilvy (the 13th Earl of Airlie) and Christopher Geidt had learned how to guide the monarch to regard the Crown as an immortal institution and not merely a group of personalities. Their wisdom had not been replaced. The successors were loyal but not weighty. None of them could convince William that while living in Adelaide Cottage suited his priority for family life, his relaxed lifestyle was not appropriate for a future monarch. ‘He’s a school-run father rather than the next King,’ complained an insider. One advisor even muttered, ‘Hanoverians make good constitutional monarchs because they’re so stupid.’

Hours after hearing the news about the King’s cancer, Harry telephoned his father. Charles agreed to meet his son in London but only briefly. Rushing for that night’s flight, Harry landed at Heathrow shortly after 3pm.[606]

Charles’s helicopter was waiting in Buckingham Palace’s garden as Harry entered Clarence House to meet his father for the first time since the Queen’s funeral, seventeen months earlier. In Camilla’s opinion, Charles needed to prevent his hot-tempered son from veering off into a debate or recrimination. There could be no repeat of the ugly confrontation after Philip’s funeral in Windsor. Mindful of King Lear, Charles knew by heart the lament, ‘How sharper than a serpent’s tooth it is to have a thankless child.’

Fearing nothing would remain private, Charles did not specify the type of cancer or the gravity of the prognosis. Some Palace insiders wondered whether Harry would offer an apology for the litany of his hurtful accusations and seek reconciliation. Neither Charles nor Camilla would be surprised by Harry’s refusal to back down. Rather than arriving for reconciliation, other officials assumed that Harry came with an agenda to obtain the King’s surrender on armed protection, money and status, perhaps also assuming that Charles’s illness would soften him. Having set the tone, Charles ignored Harry’s offer to ‘gladly step up’ to any royal duties. By now, it would have been hard for anyone to trust Harry. Even though the monarchy looked depleted – the senior working royals were over seventy – Charles would not dare to defy William’s veto on Harry. Even if William looked exhausted at a recent investiture, his fury about Harry’s ‘treachery’ was unabated. Openly, he condemned his brother: ‘He’s an embarrassment.’[607]

After only thirty minutes, the King signalled that the meeting was over. While Harry was escorted out, the King and Queen were driven across to Buckingham Palace. Ten minutes later, their helicopter took off for Sandringham. Harry stayed the night in a hotel and took the first flight back to California.

Those puzzled by Harry’s 10,000-mile round trip wondered whether it signalled a genuine desire for reconciliation. Hours after landing in Los Angeles, Harry’s reappearance offered one explanation. That same night in Las Vegas, he presented the ‘Man of the Year’ award for the Confederation of European Paper Industries. Paid $200,000, Harry joined the celebration of the organisers’ success in recycling paper. For the audience, the news from London about the King was a reminder of Harry’s status. After a thirty-second speech mocking American football for stealing rugby, Harry handed the prize to Cameron Heyward of the Pittsburgh Steelers. ‘I’m in shock. That’s Prince Harry!’ exclaimed the football star.[608] After this gig, some were less puzzled by Harry’s transatlantic dash, not least because he failed to appear at the following day’s Super Bowl.

The Sun posed that same question one week later. ‘Was Harry’s trip,’ asked the newspaper, ‘done to be used in a TV programme?’ Was the thirty-minute meeting just a showcase? Did he need material for a TV interview?[609] That possibility arose as Harry appeared on ABC’s Good Morning programme. Asked about his father and his flight to London, Harry replied: ‘I love my family. I think any illness, any sickness, brings families together. I can always get on a plane to see them.’

Buckingham Palace rejected the olive branch. On the Palace’s website, the Sussexes were downgraded. Their previously prominent separate biographies – the extent of Harry’s was 2,700 words and Meghan’s 1,300 words – were now summarised in 500 words at the bottom of the page alongside Prince Andrew’s. In retaliation for the Sussexes’ new website, they were labelled as non-working royals.[610] Open warfare had erupted again between the Sussexes and the Palace.

Two weeks later, Harry didn’t appear at a ceremony in London to honour Diana. Instead, he and Meghan flew once again in a private Bombardier jet to Vancouver for a three-day inspection of the preparations for the 2025 Invictus Games. Meghan promoted her new Netflix series on the journey. Harry’s reconciliation agenda was pushed by his spokeswoman, but critical headlines in Britain aroused the response: ‘The Sussexes will not be broken. They’re still here.’[611]

The Invictus Games was still the anchor of Harry’s professional profile. Beyond that, he was adrift. Increasingly, the isolation from Britain and his family eroded his purpose. Life in Montecito was solitary, the same friendless routine broken by an occasional game of polo. Netflix’s polo series would be formally announced in mid-April.[612]

Concern for his father’s health was a good reason to call the Palace, but Harry was always told that the king was ‘unavailable’. The doctors had stepped in. The King, they decided, was too weak to cope with the risk of confrontation. Charles had to be shielded from any outburst from his son. Inevitably, Harry railed at being blocked. And then another cloud appeared.

Two years earlier, in reply to Harry’s damning criticism of Donald Trump, the presidential candidate had ridiculed Meghan: ‘Harry is whipped like no person I think I’ve ever seen. I’m not a fan of Meghan. I think poor Harry is being led around by the nose. It’ll end and it’ll end bad.’ Meghan’s sanctimonious Californian attitudes irritated Trump: ‘I want to know what’s going to happen when Harry decides he’s had enough of being bossed around. You know, I think Harry’s been led down a path.’

Now, with the real prospect of Trump’s re-election, his son Eric had described the Sussexes as ‘spoiled apples’, adding that ‘the Brits can happily have those two.’[613] Trump himself also denounced the Prince. The Royal Family, he told an interviewer, had been ‘too gracious’ towards Harry, not least because he had ‘betrayed’ the Queen. ‘If he lied,’ he said about Harry’s visa application, ‘they’ll have to take appropriate action.’[614]

The Reform UK party leader Nigel Farage asked his friend if, as president, he would continue Biden’s protection. Trump said not. There would be no special privileges. He continued to talk about the consequences for Harry’s disloyalty towards the Queen which ‘broke her heart. I won’t protect him. He betrayed the Queen. That’s unforgiveable. He would be on his own.’ But he would not commit himself to deportation.[615]

Asked during an ABC TV interview if he would become an American citizen, Harry replied: ‘I have considered it but it’s not a high priority for me right now.’ By law, if he pledged allegiance to another country, he would have to give up his titles.[616] Aggravating the question was the prospect of Trump’s election victory in November. President Biden was all that protected Harry from the Heritage Foundation’s repeated attempts to force the release of Harry’s visa application.[617] Likely fearful that Trump would defeat the 81-year-old president, Meghan remained uncharacteristically silent during the election campaign. Ignored by the Democratic presidential candidate Kamala Harris, her political ambitions had run into the sand. Meghan pointedly said that she was remaining ‘non-partisan’.[618]

* * *

At the end of February 2024, the whole family was due to gather in Windsor for the memorial service of King Constantine of Greece, who had died a year earlier. But instead of a show of confidence, the image of the mourners walking down the hill to St George’s Chapel reflected a new crisis. William was marked to lead the family that day. At the last moment he was absent without explanation on a ‘personal matter’. Kate, it later transpired, had just been diagnosed with cancer. William stayed at home.

On the drive to Windsor from London, the Royal Family heard that Tom Kingston, the husband of Prince Michael’s daughter Ella, had shot himself. His company had been mired in debt. As the family gathered its thoughts for the walk down to St George’s Chapel, Prince Andrew and his ex-wife Sarah Ferguson pushed themselves to the front of the procession. Behind them stood Princess Anne and Queen Camilla. The image of the two disgraced royals outside the chapel glad-handing the clergyman for the cameras while the procession waited provoked media speculation about the monarchy’s vulnerability. The Palace had seemingly failed to manage a crisis.

Two weeks later, the monarchy’s frailty was compounded. The King’s illness prevented his presence at the Commonwealth Day service at Westminster Abbey. To reassure those worried about her own absence owing to her still unannounced cancer, Kate’s office posted a Mother’s Day photo of herself and the three children. Within hours, a photo agency spotted that the image had been photoshopped. In the uproar, the photo was ‘killed’ – withdrawn by agencies from further distribution.[619] Rumours erupted across the world: Kate was accused of orchestrating a cover-up of her illness, William was damned as guilty of adultery and the King was said to have altered the succession. Kate’s Kensington Palace advisors had lost control of the narrative.

Fuelling the controversy, Meghan’s spokeswoman volunteered that the Duchess would never edit a photo: ‘She would have been annihilated.’ The reality was that in 2021, Misan Harriman had produced a Valentine’s Day photo showing the pregnant Meghan in a field near Montecito, shot remotely from London. He had digitally added an olive tree. ‘It’s amazing what you can do with technology,’ Harriman said at the time.[620] Harry had similarly benefited from digital editing. His face on the cover of Spare had been ‘touched up’. Hair had been added to conceal his growing baldness and his skin was darkened.

Days later that admission was explained as poor experimentation with editing, and swiftly followed by a video, posted by Kate, revealing that she had cancer. Instead of attracting unqualified sympathy, Kate was met with more derision.[621] Among Meghan’s passionate supporters was the influencer Christopher Bouzy, a black American tech entrepreneur. In January, after the first announcement of Kate’s illness, Bouzy had posted on his social media a gymnast doing backflips captioned ‘Kate Middleton this weekend’.[622] Bouzy also labelled Kate as ageing as fast as a banana despite using plastic surgery, claimed she was the victim of domestic abuse and said she had used a body double for an ‘appearance’ with William at a farm shop.And, added Bouzy, Kate was divorcing William. Hours after Kate’s disclosure of cancer, Bouzy posted a message that Kate’s video was fake. This was followed by an American doctor saying the Palace’s press release about her illness ‘doesn’t make a lot of medical sense’.

Meghan appeared soon after on CBS’s News Sunday. Once again, she spoke about teetering on the edge of suicide in Kensington Palace. To re-energise her continuing battle with the Royal Family, she threatened, ‘I’ve really scraped the surface on my experience.’[623] She didn’t mention Kate.

Days after Kate’s video ‘misadventure’, Meghan spoke again on International Women’s Day. At a convention in Austin, Texas, she criticised without any hint of irony female media executives for allowing online bullying. ‘It’s not catty, it’s cruel,’ she said about the abuse she received from trolls while she was pregnant. ‘What I find the most disturbing is how much of the hate is women completely spewing that to other women. I cannot make sense of that.’[624] The ‘champion’ of humanitarianism and feminism overlooked the abuse she had directed at Kate in her broadcast interviews and through Omid Scobie and Harry himself.

Bafflingly, damaging Kate’s reputation appeared to be part of the latest move from the Sussexes. The other was to improve their own popularity. Worried about her own image, Meghan appointed Charlie Gipson, a British publicist, to represent her in London. Gipson started by picking up the pieces.[625]

Belatedly, Harry sent a message of support to his sister-in-law: ‘We wish health and healing for Kate and her family and hope they are able to do so privately and in peace.’ People magazine published that Harry has ‘privately reached out to William and Kate’. Since the Sussexes told People about their message it was hardly ‘private’.[626] Contradictions were frequently apparent in the Sussexes’ battle for success – and survival.

CHAPTER 32

The Brand

Nothing was ready but Meghan couldn’t wait. Ever since the trip to Canouan, she had been planning her new Netflix series, to be titled With Love, Meghan. There was every reason to feel excited. Her dream of being a self-made star was about to come true. The Netflix series would show the real Meghan.

Netflix’s head of content, Bela Bajaria, had bought her lifestyle show. Taking advantage of her global fame, Meghan was certain to attract viewers. Whether those viewers were fascinated or outraged didn’t matter to the streamer. In Meghan’s pitch, as the hostess in her Montecito house, she would be combining the roles of homemaker, gardener, crafter, cook, mother and, above all, entrepreneur and female founder. Unlike Martha Stewart, Gwyneth Paltrow and other TV lifestyle hosts in the crowded market, she would present herself as more than a domestic goddess. ‘At its conception,’ she later explained, ‘I had thought about the interest that people seem to have in my fashion – what I would wear.’ Her criteria were ‘things that present beautifully but don’t break the bank’. Or ‘high-low’, as she described it – good-looking but not expensive.[627]

Her brand, she told Omid Scobie, would be ‘something more accessible’ than Gwyneth Paltrow’s Goop.[628] ‘Something rooted in my love of details, curating, hosting, life’s simple pleasures and family.’ She was aiming, she said, at ‘creating something safe and timeless. And something that won’t be accused of riding on the back of anything royal.’ Her public commitment to curtail her royalty was intended as a signpost of sincerity.

Meghan spoke about launching her own business by offering tips that illustrated her philosophy as an authentic, glamorous and inspirational feminist.[629] In conversations with Netflix, she excluded resurrecting The Tig or restoring herself as an influencer. She classed herself as an entrepreneur. ‘Women,’ she said, ‘don’t need to be afraid to talk about finance. And I think the more financial literacy we have, the stronger we’re going to be.’ Finance and business, Meghan ought to have known, was no longer a challenge for women. Females were the chief executives of the world’s biggest corporations including Glaxo, Diageo, General Motors and Accenture. Plus pharma businesses, media conglomerates and hospitality chains. The real challenge for Meghan was that to create a business, she needed products and partners in design, manufacturing and distribution, and a financial backer.

Those hurdles were put to one side while Netflix’s executives concluded that, while Archewell was named as the series’ producer, Meghan would need help.To tilt the chances in her favour, two producers employed by Sony for Selena Gomez’s cookery show were hired. Known as ‘The Kings of Reality TV’, they had produced over a hundred shows. The director, Michael Steed, was an experienced Netflix loyalist. As usual, the seventy-plus crew and staff were carefully vetted. Before they were approached, their social media was checked for any antagonism towards the Sussexes. Then each was interviewed without disclosing the project. Meghan hoped that questions would expose any lurking disloyalty. Finally, if they were acceptable, Meghan required that each sign a binding NDA.

As in all productions, the technicians could only work with the material they were given. ‘At the beginning,’ Meghan said, ‘I just liked making jam. All I liked to do was just make jam and preserves.’[630] She needed more products for her Netflix series though. With a love for good food, she had toured restaurants across the world with her first husband, looking for new culinary experiences. But she could not cook. Her limit was roast chicken and hamburgers. It wasn’t just Italians who would be baffled by her recipe for cooking spaghetti – the uncooked pasta was laid on top of vegetables in a frying pan.[631] Even the two pizza ovens in her garden were not used.[632] Her producers persuaded Meghan to avoid suggesting she was a skilled chef.

She agreed that instead, professional chefs would appear in the series as guests in her kitchen. Scouring the internet, she found recipes for cakes, and ways to present vegetables and fruit artistically on platters and in bowls. Without any original recipes she could focus on the appearance of food rather than the taste. Meghan even praised a Chinese takeaway for being placed ‘beautifully’ on a dish. Her guests could praise her delicious ‘cooking’, even though it was delivered by a restaurant, because feeding friends was ‘probably my love language’.

Hampered by Meghan’s indecision, filming the series was delayed. Ideas and scripts were not forthcoming and Meghan had failed to appoint a chief executive of Mama Knows Best, her Delaware-registered company that sold her jams, cutlery, nut butters, dog beds, bird feeders, blankets, spices and dishes. No one suitable, it appeared, wanted the job. Fearful of the vacuum, she planned to announce her brand, American Riviera Orchard, prematurely.

Eventually, as filming started in a Montecito house rented by Netflix from her neighbours Tom and Sherrie Cipolla, Meghan appeared to be confused about the identity she was projecting. Was she Meghan Markle, or the wife of a British prince, or the Duchess of Sussex, or a self-made feminist or a standard American mom? During 2025 all her favoured magazines including Harper’s Bazaar, People and Time continued to name her Meghan Markle. Whatever her title, she presented herself during the filming as a traditional housewife and mother.

To establish American Riviera Orchard, she arranged to produce fifty jars of strawberry jam, supposedly all made from her own crop in her kitchen. According to the best jam manufacturers, she would have needed at least 100lbs of strawberries. Her garden’s strawberry beds did not appear big enough to produce over one thousand strawberries. Since her jam proved to be unusually liquid and contained few berries, it is just possible that the fruit was grown by Meghan in Montecito. But she refused to volunteer the truth. Even the manufacturer of the distinctive glass jars refused to be identified.

One week before the trailer for American Riviera Orchard was streamed, the fifty jars were distributed among Meghan’s celebrity friends and contacts including Tracy Robbins, Kris Jenner, Mindy Kaling, model Chrissy Teigen, former Suits actor Abigail Spencer and wife of Nacho Figueras, Delfina Blaquier and Meghan’s friend Kelly McKee Zajfen, a co-founder of a mothers’ organisation. All were asked to praise the jam on social media – along with a snippet of gossip scripted if necessary by Meghan’s publicists. Spencer performed the best. Lying on the grass with a pot of jam in a hamper of lemons and white flowers, Spencer intoned, ‘This jam is my jam. A delicious taste of what’s to come. Love you so much M.’ Simultaneously, Meghan posted a short video of herself on Instagram.[633]

The gender-equality campaigner was shown posing in the kitchen wearing a white tank top and then a black ballgown doing a range of domestic tasks – arranging hydrangeas, whisking in a bowl, pouring a drizzle of olive oil on to hummus and placing a shrimp on a grilled lettuce leaf, all to the background soundtrack of American jazz singer Nancy Wilson’s 1960 hit ‘I Wish You Love’. Offering viewers ‘some little tips and tricks’, Meghan made a ‘Ladybug’-themed appetiser. The caption, produced by a committee of scriptwriters – ‘Everybody’s invited to create wonder in every moment’ – was overlaid with Meghan’s voice urging viewers to ‘celebrate the joys of cooking and gardening and entertaining and friendship’. The publicists promoted the Duchess as living the American Dream, ‘telling her life through her recipes’.

Considering that filming of the Netflix series would not be completed until July, three months later, the rushed and premature launch of social media trailers advertising American Riviera Orchard on 14th March was puzzling, until an unsurprising coincidence arose. That same night, at 6.30pm in London, William arrived at London’s Science Museum to greet twenty international winners of the twenty-fifth Diana Legacy Awards. Merely three hours after the London ceremony, Archewell announced its $100,000 civil rights awards.[634] In between, just as William walked on to the stage, Meghan trailed herself as a lifestyle celebrity.[635] Her debut drew mixed reactions.

Comments about her celebrity jam were combined with questions why a Californian mother living in a house with nine bedrooms and fourteen bathrooms rented a nearby farm growing cannabis rather than grapes and avocados. And why did she cook in £600 pans sitting on a £15,000 cooker? [636] Eyewitnesses in her home saw Meghan curl up in horror about the trolls – but not on camera. And as always Meghan’s response was to reappear smiling, undaunted and regal.

Hectic telephone calls persuaded Netflix to bring forward the announcement of the Sussexes’ two new TV series – Meghan’s cookery shows and Harry’s polo extravaganza – to 14th April. While Meghan’s series celebrated ‘joys’, Harry’s polo programmes still lacked a catchy one-liner.[637]

Looking for an opportunity to highlight the announcement, Meghan chose Harry’s appearance on 12th April at Sentebale’s Royal Salute Polo Challenge charity match in Palm Beach, Florida. In January, she had refused Sophie Chandauka’s invitation to the match saying she had a previous engagement. Now, with less than twenty-four hours’ notice, Harry announced that Meghan would, after all, be coming. Both Harry and Meghan were aware that Sentebale was beset by problems. And Harry knew that Meghan’s sudden decision was certain to exacerbate the charity’s difficulties.

* * *

Back in January 2024, Harry had declared that he no longer would be Sentebale’s ‘funder of last resort’. The charity, he told Chandauka, was ‘an albatross’. It was no longer ‘working for me’, he said. If only the Lesotho or British government would take over, he said, he could concentrate on Archewell’s activities. Harry wanted to hasten Chandauka’s plan to move its headquarters to South Africa, instantly fire the chief executive Richard Miller and find new donors in America. ‘You can’t just shoot off,’ Chandauka told Harry. ‘Employees have rights and our image would suffer if we fired Miller.’ Harry was shocked, seeing Chandauka’s challenge to his control as unacceptable. A showdown was averted after Miller agreed to resign within weeks.[638] Chandauka planned to replace him temporarily with an experienced development professional, Carmel Gaillard. Harry backed down.

Chandauka was faced with another hurdle, though. Trustees Mark Dyer and Damian West – Harry’s two wingmen on Sentebale’s board: Dyer, a former army officer and long-time confidant, and Damian West, an investor in African mining – as usual, supported the Prince. ‘You won’t change anything unless you get rid of Mark Dyer and Damian West,’ had been Hornby’s last advice to Chandauka before he left the charity the year before. ‘Harry doesn’t tolerate “No”.’ The trio controlled the charity’s board of trustees. Fortunately, they all agreed to Chandauka’s planned ‘Return to South Africa’.

On 5th March 2024, Harry declared his full support for Chandauka’s new vision. All eyes were focused on the forthcoming polo match in Florida. Chandauka had spoken about raising $1 million ‘hopefully in the bank’.[639] But there was a new problem. Harry had decided that the match should be filmed for his Netflix series. The game’s host, the Santa Clara Polo Club near West Palm Beach, refused to allow the switch from a charity game to a commercial venture on their pitch. Fortunately, Harry’s friend Marc Ganzi, a Florida billionaire businessman and the owner of a neighbouring polo club in Wellington, agreed to host the game. Despite the move costing £100,000, Harry demanded the change of venue. ‘I’ll make it up to you,’ Harry told Andrew ‘Tucks’ Tucker, the global organiser of polo matches. All the income, Marc Ganzi agreed, would be donated to Sentebale. Rich players paid up to $100,000 to the charity to participate in the game with Harry.[640] Then, on Harry’s orders, for ‘security reasons’, the number of spectators at Wellington was drastically limited. That reduced the potential number of donors and Chandauka would complain that Harry never paid the £100,000. Tucker’s irritation soared.

First, Tucker objected to the additional work changing the venue. Secondly, he wanted nothing to do with Netflix. But worst of all, he was incandescent that Meghan was coming. He knew the sponsors and some players would object to her presence. Some might even stay away. Meghan also jeopardised his relationship with Prince William, another of Tucker’s clients. But Harry expected Tucker to ‘fall into line’.

After arriving from Santa Barbara on Marc Ganzi’s Bombardier jet, Harry faced Tucker’s anger. Harry’s behaviour, the organiser decided, was intolerable. After the match, he would resign. Capable of being politic when required, Harry concealed his own irritation towards Chandauka at the pre-match dinner for potential donors at the Zaytinya restaurant in Miami Beach. Fluently, Chandauka presented Sentebale’s new mission to move the charity’s headquarters to South Africa and, performing at his best, Harry eloquently endorsed the new journey.[641]

In good spirits, Chandauka met Harry the following afternoon at the Wellington ground. Harry was nervous. More so after Meghan and her entourage arrived. Dressed extravagantly in an ivory silk and hemp Heidi Merrick pleated dress with a halterneck top and cut-out at the waist, carrying a Valentino purse and walking on five-inch Aquazzura heels across the turf, Meghan was accompanied by tennis champion Serena Williams, who lived nearby.

‘Hi,’ Meghan greeted Chandauka, then turned her back, heading with Williams to a marquee. ‘Champagne,’ she ordered, pointedly ignoring the long-standing sponsor’s drink, Royal Salute World Polo whisky. ‘And I want an ice bucket.’ No ice bucket was available. ‘Buy one,’ Meghan’s publicist ordered. At once the mood changed. Meghan’s staff barked their imperious demands and Sentebale’s events manager stood paralysed. Tears began to flow. ‘You heard,’ snapped a Meghan staffer. The manager withdrew. Unwilling to confront Meghan she was told to buy an ice bucket instantly. Back in the tent, Meghan refused Chandauka’s invitation to mingle with the event’s supporters.

Harry’s team won the match. As usual, the winner would be presented with a cup.Sophie Chandauka stood on the small platform expecting to perform the honours. But Netflix’s director vetoed that scenario. Suddenly, Meghan appeared. Putting herself next to Harry, Meghan told Chandauka to move down the line, out of the picture. Harry looked puzzled. After Meghan’s repeat of the order, Chandauka understood. Ducking inelegantly underneath the arms holding the trophy and trying not to fall off the small stage, she moved away from Harry. Throughout, Meghan’s smile never faltered. Then, bursting with theatrical laughter, she presented Harry with the cup – and a kiss. Chandauka was cut out of the shot.[642]

Meghan then headed to her $8,000 suite at the nearby Four Seasons hotel. The organisers were told that she would not be going to that evening’s dinner at the Santa Rita Polo Farm.[643] [644] Harry persuaded her to change her decision. She did appear but the atmosphere in the room was strained – especially after the seating arrangements had to be changed to accommodate her.[645] Chandauka was clearly irritated and Harry’s discomfort grew after Sentebale’s director in Lesotho, Ntoli Moletsane, told him that the charity was losing direction and had funding problems.[646]

The following day, the kickback started. Video footage of the awkward dance on the podium to move Chandauka away from Harry appeared on the Miami Herald’s website. Hundreds of critical comments were directed at Meghan.[647] Her publicists were alarmed. Meghan was horrified. To deflect criticism from her, Harry ordered Ashley Hansen to call Chandauka. ‘We want you to issue a statement to rebut the trolls,’ said Hansen. Chandauka was to say that she was not pushed aside by the Duchess. Hansen’s tone, Chandauka recalled, was ‘unpleasant’ and ‘imperious’.[648] Chandauka refused. ‘We cannot be an extension of the Sussexes’ PR machine,’ she replied. ‘I didn’t sign up for PR mitigation for Meghan. That’s for Archewell. You should have thought through the consequences of Meghan coming.’[649] Harry was outraged. Chandauka’s refusal represented gross disloyalty and was damaging to Meghan and Archewell. For the moment Harry remained silent. Then he sent a short WhatsApp: ‘What’s it all about?’ Chandauka’s long reply laid out the battle lines: she was not part of the Sussexes’ machine; Harry’s staff had treated her and the Sentebale team at the polo field like servants; and, if he wanted, he should find another chairman.

Unexpectedly challenged, Harry told Ashley Hansen to pursue peace. Chandauka included her media assistant in the Zoom meeting. She decided that Harry would not be given an excuse to malign a black woman. At the end of the conversation, Chandauka believed an equilibrium had been restored. She was mistaken.

CHAPTER 33

Nigeria

Harry’s triumphant smile as he climbed the steps to St Paul’s Cathedral on 8th May 2024 was seen to many as the hallmark of a son delighted to embarrass his father. The service to celebrate the tenth anniversary of the Invictus Games was contrived to herald the Sussexes’ status. The Montecito court was asserting its legitimacy within the Royal Family.

Supported by Charles Spencer, his sister Jane Fellowes and a clutch of cousins, Harry had chosen to mount an event to rival his father’s Buckingham Palace garden party for 8,000 guests – the King’s first public event since his cancer was diagnosed. Nearly every standing member of the Royal Family was in the garden to support the King while he shook hands with well-wishers.

As usual, Harry had played the media game, leaving the media to speculate whether he would see his father or even stay at Buckingham Palace. Charles’s spokesman said that Harry had never asked to see his father, while Harry insisted that Charles had refused his request. In fact Harry had rejected the offer of a bedroom in a royal palace on security grounds. His exit from a palace, he explained, would have been public, and without police protection he would be vulnerable to an assassin. ‘It seems it was not good enough,’ said a Palace spokesman. ‘Maybe he was worried about the mice?’[650] On security grounds, Harry preferred to stay at Coworth Park Hotel in Ascot, fifteen minutes from Windsor Castle.[651]

The acclaimed Invictus Games had become Harry’s lifeboat. The military in over twenty countries supported the competition. Without that global passport, his status and even life’s purpose was diminished. No one disputed the value of the $60 million games for the military community. Men and women injured in the service of their country deserved exceptional support. Participating in a sporting competition boosted the injured servicemen’s enjoyment of life. For all the participants and their families, Harry was the champion of a commendable achievement. At $120,000 per competitor, it was a worthwhile investment.

But beyond the military community, few were interested in the Games. Since August 2023, fewer than 300,000 people had viewed his Netflix series Heart of Invictus and fewer still had watched to the end. By comparison, Barack Obama’s Leave the World Behind attracted 121 million viewers in its first three weeks. Harry preferred to ignore the poor ratings.

In the Sussexes’ battle for popularity, the Spencers’ support for Harry and Damian Lewis’s reading of W.E. Henley’s poem ‘Invictus’ in St Paul’s paled in comparison to the increasing popularity of the King. His approval rating was 56 per cent compared to 49 per cent a year earlier, and the approval of Kate was 69 per cent against Meghan’s 25 per cent. Even Charles Spencer’s presence, Harry knew, was not an unequivocal show of support. While they were filming for Harry’s Invictus Netflix series at Diana’s grave at Althorp, the Spencers’ ancestral home, Harry and Meghan had asked Charles Spencer whether he would agree that Archie and Lilibet could change their surnames from Mountbatten-Windsor to Spencer. ‘Absolutely not,’ Spencer replied emphatically. Harry reportedly reeled with surprise.

As Harry read the lesson in St Paul’s from Corinthians about ‘service’ and the ‘common good’, he gazed down at his mother’s siblings, apparently unaware of the discrepancy in his family relationships. Those who speculated about Harry’s hope that Charles’s cancer would have a ‘reunifying effect’ were mistaken.[652] King Charles had stayed the previous night at Windsor Castle, but his ‘full’ programme denied Harry the chance of a meeting. Palace officials suspected that Harry’s motive was to bestow credibility on his next stop.

Late the following afternoon, after the service, Harry met Meghan in Heathrow’s Windsor Suite. Having arrived from Los Angeles, the Duchess was waiting in a secluded area. The couple were heading to Nigeria for what they hoped would be seen across the world as a royal visit. This was the Big One, the opportunity for the Sussexes to eclipse both the King and William.

In the early hours of 10th May, at Nigeria’s Abuja airport, thirty-one suitcases belonging to the Duke and Duchess of Sussex and their entourage were taken off the delayed British Airways flight by security-cleared handlers and loaded on to an army truck. Standing on the warm tarmac, the Sussexes were officially welcomed by senior military officers. Watching the celebratory hugs and reunions, Meghan and Harry’s entourage, including four bodyguards, were steeled for a hectic three-day visit. Overseeing the group was Josh Kettler, a Californian with a mixed career, recently recruited as Harry’s chief of staff. The Archewell press release extolled Kettler’s virtues and the Sussexes’ ‘thrill’ to have him on board.

Sitting in a minibus surrounded by twelve armoured cars with soldiers holding AK-47s, the ‘special guests’ headed towards the capital as the temperature rose to 36 degrees. Local traffic stopped as onlookers glimpsed the blurred faces speeding past. Recognition fuelled Meghan’s pride.

Officially, the Sussexes were in Nigeria to promote the Invictus Games. In reality, the painstaking discussions over the previous eight months between David Wiseman, Invictus’s 39-year-old director, and Air Vice-Marshal Abidemi Timothy Marquis, a 56-year-old Nigerian former counter-intelligence expert and the military’s director of sports, had focused on Harry’s agenda. Invictus would help Harry to promote himself as a senior member of the Royal Family. Nigeria was also the perfect battleground on which to weaponise a portrayal of the Royal Family as racist.

Harry’s host, Nigeria’s defence chief General Christopher Musa, embraced Invictus. As a tool in his war against Boko Haram, a brutal Islamist terror group ravaging the country, Invictus reassured his soldiers of proper care in the event of injury. Few outsiders, Musa knew, could embolden his soldiers to fight harder than the internationally recognised Prince. As Wiseman repeated, Invictus was Harry’s: ‘It’s very much his thing.’[653]

Planning for the trip had started in September 2023. During the Invictus Games in Düsseldorf, David Wiseman had told Marquis that the Sussexes would welcome an invitation. ‘A sort of royal tour,’ suggested the former Yorkshire Regiment infantryman, who had been wounded in his chest by a Taliban bullet. The Air Vice-Marshal was enthusiastic. Meghan, he knew, was popular among Nigerians. Many had followed her on Suits, most had watched her wedding and all of them knew about her interview with Oprah Winfrey. Her visit would highlight the announcement in 2022 that genealogy tests had shown her ancestry to be 43 per cent Nigerian.[654] Accordingly, Wiseman reassured Harry that the majority of Nigerians were convinced that Meghan was the victim of the Royal Family’s racism and Harry had been forced into a heroic exile to protect his wife.

Making enquiries around Abuja to discover the Sussexes’ plans weeks earlier, the British High Commissioner informally suggested to Nigeria’s government officials that the couple should not be welcomed by the country’s president. London, the British envoy said, would not approve of the exiles embarrassing the King. His successful lobbying did not minimise the Sussexes’ ambition.

During countless emails and Zoom calls, Wiseman listed the Sussexes’ proposed agenda. It would include mental health, female empowerment, sport, education and social messaging. He also wanted a few public events with children, women – and wounded soldiers. Plus, everyone lined up to meet the Sussexes should be vetted. In the closely choreographed itinerary, the media would be excluded, particularly from their appointments with General Musa and the state governors. Controlling the media would strictly be the Sussexes’ responsibility. Unlike the usual hordes of journalists on royal tours, the Sussexes had appointed only reporters from Harper’s Bazaar and People magazine to witness their success. Both could be relied upon to describe the Sussexes’ enthusiastic welcome, capture attention in Britain and America, and, most importantly, focus on Meghan’s designer clothes. The ‘What Meghan Wore’ website would signal her fashion choices, notably clothes by the Los Angeles designer Heidi Merrick. Every name mention and click earned Meghan royalties.[655]

Strangely, at that moment in London, Kate had announced that her office would no longer give details of the clothes she was wearing.[656] ‘The style is there,’ said a Palace spokesman, ‘but it’s about the substance.’ Any distraction from her work would be avoided.

Within hours of the Sussexes’ arrival, the visitors were cheered by thirty students at the Lightway Academy, a progressive school in Abuja. Wearing a Nigerian bead necklace and a peach-coloured dress, Meghan set the tone among the girls – fans of Suits and admirers of Diana. ‘Thank you for welcoming me home,’ said the consummate performer. After praising the students’ dance, she continued: ‘Nigerian women are brave, resilient, courageous, powerful, beautiful.’[657] Emotionally, Meghan spoke of Nigeria as ‘my country, my home’, and told her small audience during an awkward discussion about female empowerment and mental health, ‘As I look around this room, I see myself in all of you.’ Meghan brought every topic back to herself. ‘You see why I married him?’ she told the students. ‘He’s so smart. And so inspiring because he speaks the truth.’

Unashamedly, Meghan was upstaging Harry. While Harry was famous as Diana’s son, sixth in the line of succession of the world’s most famous monarchy, Meghan was trying to escape from being simply Harry’s wife. Playing to the audience, the Duchess was on a mission to replicate Diana’s 1990 visit and act as a future Queen, but with the difference that the precursor to any conversation was Meghan speaking about herself. ‘As a mom . . .’ the monologue started, before recounting how every day started with her cooking breakfast for her children and getting them ready for school.

After fifty minutes, the visitors departed. Everyone had been reminded that Archewell had made a donation to the school. That appeared to be a mistake. Archewell’s accounts did not list a donation.[658] After a quick change of clothes – Meghan was dressed in all white – they were driven in an armed convoy to meet General Musa at Abuja’s defence headquarters. Noticeably excited to meet international celebrities, the officer agreed with Harry, ‘The power of sport can change lives.’

The tour’s highlight for General Musa was to visit wounded soldiers in Kaduna with Harry. Ten years of service in the British Army and his lifelong experience as a royal honed Harry’s bravura appearance. ‘Fifty of them were lying on their beds,’ Harry reported, ‘and I’m sure no one would mind me saying that their morale was low. I could see it in their eyes.’ The former army captain spoke with genuine warmth to the casualties about a promising future despite their appalling injuries. ‘Meet fellow sufferers in the Invictus family,’ he said. ‘With sport, you will recover your resilience. You will feel unconquered.’ Sport would be a vehicle for their recovery. Just as Diana in 1990 had held the hand of a Nigerian leprosy patient, Harry took one soldier’s hand. ‘Get better, be strong,’ urged Harry. Energised by Harry’s enthusiasm, desultory young men lifted into wheelchairs came to life. They pledged not to allow their injuries to define their lives.

To prove his commitment, Harry played wheelchair basketball with a small team of injured soldiers against a team led by General Musa. All of the men had lost one or both legs. ‘Get them trained for Vancouver,’ Harry told their commanding officer.[659]

Not mentioned during the visit was the existential challenge facing Invictus. None of the founding nations were fighting wars. Although Invictus’s promotional photographs showed men without legs energetically playing sports in wheelchairs, the numbers of recently injured had dramatically declined. David Wiseman’s task was to recruit new countries that were fighting wars. Ukraine, Israel and Nigeria were obvious candidates. All three had young limbless ex-servicemen. All three accepted Wiseman’s invitation to compete in Canada.

From the hospital, Harry headed to meet the governor of Kaduna state, Uba Sani. During the formal meeting, Sani presented to his visitor traditional Hausa clothes and paintings of Harry and Meghan. ‘How are we going to get those back to Los Angeles?’ Harry mumbled as they headed back to the city.

Journalists excluded from the events were briefed the following day, Saturday 11th May. Meghan had been wearing Diana’s cross pendant necklace to show continuity and respect to the Royal Family.[660] ‘The Markle Sparkle’ one tabloid reported. ‘The Threat to King’ was another tabloid headline.

Saturday started with a reception at the Defence Headquarters of the Nigerian Armed Forces. Wearing a dark brown and white dress, Meghan stood for ‘God Save the King’. Amid applause, the senior female politician Abike Dabiri gushed, ‘She is beautiful, intelligent, diligent, hard-working and she stands firm in the midst of challenges. Prince Harry, you married the best – our daughter and friend.’ After handing Meghan gifts and traditional Yoruba clothes, Dabiri christened Meghan ‘With your Yoruba name – Adetokunbo meaning “the Crown has come home from abroad”.’ Meghan had good reason to feel that her destiny was indeed as the queen-in-waiting.

Next, the convoy took Meghan back to her hotel to change into a white strapless linen dress, and then back on the road to a panel discussion about female empowerment. Mo Abudu, the panel’s moderator and chief executive of EbonyLife media group, asked the audience to pick a Nigerian name for the Duchess. ‘Ifeoma,’ proposed an Igbo tribesman, meaning ‘a treasured thing’. Another suggested ‘Omowale’, meaning ‘the child has come home’. Centre stage, Meghan blended as a Nigerian into the ceremonies and musical performances.

Then a speedy drive back to the hotel to change yet again, this time into local Nigerian clothes. Before Meghan re-emerged, the wife of Nigeria’s president, Oluremi Tinubu, was recorded criticising Meghan’s outfits. ‘We do not accept nakedness in our culture,’ she said about Meghan’s favoured off-the-shoulder dresses. ‘It’s not beautiful at all.’ One half of Nigeria’s 230 million population is Muslim.

Halfway through the trip, Buckingham Palace’s officials were fuming. ‘Meghan’s and Harry’s speeches,’ said one, ‘and their whole attitude has been designed to give the impression that they are still fully paid-up royals.’[661] In the midst of his ‘royal tour’, Harry had deliberately annoyed his family. ‘These trips are about us being able to go out and focus on the things that mean so much to us,’ Harry told People magazine. ‘And being on the ground, to us, is what it’s all about.’ The Sussexes’ Nigerian hosts spoke of Britain’s loss and quoted a Nigerian proverb: ‘The cow never knows the value of its tail until it’s chopped off.’ The senior army officers escorting the Sussexes were entranced. For the hosts, Meghan was a hero.

Beyond the public meetings, during the journeys and private meals, the army officers became intently interested as the Sussexes’ conversation strayed into the reasons for their flight to California. Meghan’s hosts had watched her Oprah Winfrey interview. Ever since then, most Nigerians were convinced that King Charles and his family were guilty of driving Meghan to near-suicide and forcing the family to flee from Britain. They believed Meghan’s denunciation of the Royal Family as racists.[662] This was the moment for Meghan to dazzle.

Over a dinner conversation in the military’s headquarters, Meghan told her story of two senior royals asking Harry while she was pregnant what colour the unborn child would be. Meghan, dressed in a strapless white St Agni gown and a Diana necklace, commanded the attention of her uniformed audience. All were captivated by her smouldering vengeance. Unsurprised by her account, the Nigerians were not alone in sharing her anger. Meghan’s victimhood was echoed around the room. Even though Britain’s prime minister at the time, Rishi Sunak, was of Indian descent and black people had secured senior ministerial appointments in Whitehall, the Sussexes’ hosts agreed that those were ‘cosmetic’. ‘The Palace threw you under a bus,’ a Nigerian general scoffed. ‘The King should have protected you.’ Her hosts believed Harry’s complaint that Meghan had not ‘fitted the mould’ and that the Palace had wanted him to marry a white woman.[663]

During that meal, Harry remained silent. He did not correct Meghan’s familiar errors about his ‘race’ conversation with Charles, but he did spring into life when Diana was mentioned. ‘She was murdered,’ he announced. His Nigerian hosts agreed. Mysterious forces had combined to kill Harry’s pregnant mother.

One mealtime conversation centred on Nigeria’s bid to host the 2029 Invictus Games, an ambition promoted by General Musa. Harry and Wiseman encouraged the idea, although their immediate focus was on the 2027 Games. A bid by Washington DC had been rejected in favour of Birmingham. The British city had been selected by Harry to challenge the Royal Family and the British government to recognize his status by giving him official support. Curiously, the dates coincided with Camilla’s eightieth birthday. Asked by a Nigerian general whether Meghan would be warmly received by Britons, Harry smiled. ‘Meghan’s definitely coming to Birmingham,’ he replied with a mischievous smile. ‘Meghan’s supporters will welcome her.’ Harry must have envisaged a showdown, especially by inviting King Charles to the event.[664] The Nigerians agreed that using the British Army to embarrass King Charles, William and Kate was Harry’s rightful purpose to prove the Sussexes were even more popular than the King.

By the end of Saturday, though, some were reassessing the trip. When Meghan said to the Lightway children, ‘I see myself in all of you,’ she seemed to have overlooked their impoverished background. Nigeria was wracked by inflation and crime, and many employees went unpaid. Seemingly oblivious to that misery, over the previous thirty-six hours, Meghan had staged a fashion parade of designer clothes and gold jewellery. And she had noticeably ditched a scarf in Nigeria’s colours because it clashed first with her Johanna Ortiz strapless dress and then with ‘The Windsor’, a backless Heidi Merrick dress.[665]

To Meghan’s good fortune, since all their events were behind closed doors, the contrast between the splendour of Meghan and her local audiences passed unnoticed by those British and American newspapers keen for every detail. Tellingly, beyond the staged events, the trip aroused little interest in Nigeria. No national newspaper reported her presence.

* * *

The Sussexes were about to spend one day in Lagos.[666]

‘Hope everything goes well today,’ a British journalist said to Miranda Barbot, the Sussexes’ publicist, on Sunday 12th May. ‘What could go wrong?’ Barbot rapped back.

Trouble started at Lagos Airport after the Sussexes landed on the short flight from Abuja. Since Meghan refused to fly by military transport, the entourage of about thirty people had flown on Air Peace’s brand new 120-seat Embraer 195-E2. The private airline, one of the region’s biggest, was owned by a high-profile Nigerian businessman, Allen Onyema. In the nature of Nigerian politics, Onyema readily agreed to the military’s request for a freebie: they ruled the country. Naturally, Onyema was standing alongside the welcoming party of senior military officials at Lagos Airport. The pay-off was inevitable. The businessman made sure that he walked alongside the Sussexes as they crossed the tarmac. The photograph of the threesome also recorded his plane in the background. Air Peace, claimed his publicists, had won ‘royal approval’. Taking free flights had become normal for the Sussexes and, relying on their staff, they had no reason to be suspicious.

As the Sussexes stood next to Onyema watching a dance troupe at the airport’s Presidential Wing, they ought to have been made aware that their host was ‘wanted’ in the US for alleged fraud. The US federal indictment filed in November 2019 accused Onyema of laundering $20 million from Nigeria through American bank accounts. ‘His trail of deceit and trickery,’ said Robert Murphy, the investigating agent in Atlanta, ‘has come to a skidding halt.’[667] Onyema had allegedly used laundered money since 2010 to buy a Lexus, a Rolls-Royce, a Mercedes and designer goods at Prada and Louis Vuitton. ‘Allen Onyema’s status as a wealthy businessman turned out to be a fraud,’ said Murphy. Inevitably, Onyema dismissed the allegations. Safe from extradition, he enjoyed accompanying the royal celebrities during the packed day.[668]

Being the guest of an alleged fraudster was not uncommon for visitors to Nigeria, renowned as one of the world’s most corrupt nations. Throughout the day, the Sussexes appeared to be untroubled by associating with a man indicted in America. The opportunity to secure media attention and status was their priority.

After visiting a school, meeting the Giants of Africa basketball team, watching street-style dances and a polo match, broken by lunch with a group of prominent Nigerians, the tour ended at the State Governor’s House. In her third outfit of the day, Meghan had changed from a cream strapless dress into a yellow floor-length Carolina Herrera outfit to hear more praise for Harry, Invictus and especially herself, a Nigerian woman who ‘had come home’.[669]

At the end of the three days, the Nigerian officers and the Sussexes were thrilled. The Sussexes appeared to have promised donations to various charities. In the event, Archewell’s accounts showed that just $10,000 had been committed to Nigeria.[670] ‘So we look forward to travelling more,’ said Harry on his eve of departing. Plans for another foreign ‘state trip’ were well advanced. The couple flew back to Los Angeles.

Tina Brown, the writer and former Vanity Fair editor, hailed the visit for recalling the original hopes for the Duke and Duchess. ‘After all the trashing of Harry . . . actually when I saw him and Meghan in Nigeria, I had a nostalgia,’ she told the BBC. ‘I felt this is what could have been, these two – who are enormously appealing to the public, and who are very good at it – were out there in Nigeria looking very attractive and being appealing people. And what a pity it is they’ve gone.’ There was, she said, ‘a Harry-shaped hole in the monarchy’.[671]

CHAPTER 34

Battling

The mighty ESPN American sports network’s offer of the Pat Tillman Award to Harry for creating the Invictus Games confirmed Tina Brown’s opinion about the Prince’s loss to Britain. The award recognized ‘exceptional individuals who exemplify courage, perseverance and service’. Harry appreciated any honour for his humanitarian virtues. The Los Angeles ceremony on 11th July 2024 was the sporting equivalent of the Oscars.

The award commemorated Pat Tillman, an American NFL football star on a £3 million contract with the Arizona Cardinals. After Islamist terrorists attacked America on 11th September 2001, Tillman abandoned his profession and enlisted as a Ranger to fight in Afghanistan. After he was killed by ‘friendly fire’ on a roadside in 2004, his widow Marie and his mother Mary established the award with ESPN. Kate Jackson, ESPN’s executive responsible for approving the awards, ranked Harry among the ‘incredible individuals’ who ‘change the world’.

Unlike the previous ones, Mary Tillman was not told in advance about Harry’s nomination. After hearing the media reports, she denounced ESPN: ‘I am shocked as to why they would select such a controversial and divisive individual to receive the award.’[672] As opposed to her son, she said, Harry had walked away from honour and duty for money and fame. His lack of loyalty to the Crown should have eliminated him from consideration: ‘He publicly disrespected his family and ran away from service to his country as a royal. He is unworthy of this award.’

Within one day of Mary Tillman’s denunciation, 12,000 Americans signed a petition demanding that Harry should not receive the award.[673] Ten days later, the petition had attracted 68,000 signatures. The backlash stunned Harry. Disapproval distressed him. Any criticism was taken as a personal wound. ‘The reaction certainly took the shine off the award,’ admitted his office.[674] America’s overwhelming support for the Sussexes had evidently faded. The social media hashtags #MeghanMarkleExposed and #HarryandMeghanaregrifters reflected the Sussexes’ problems.[675]

No one could doubt Harry’s commitment to veterans though. As the patron of the British charity Scotty’s Little Soldiers, he supported 680 children whose fathers were killed in action. ‘Just remember,’ said Harry in a recorded conversation with children, ‘your lost parent wants you to be happy.’[676]

Mary Tillman was not at Los Angeles’s Dolby Theatre to watch Harry’s appearance. Or see the welcome by his host, Serena Williams. On that day, many assumed that Meghan’s friend and their joint agents William Morris Endeavor had influenced ESPN to give Harry the award. To keep her identity separate from Harry’s, Meghan had initially refused the invitation to support Harry, but she did appear on the official photograph with Serena Williams.

Appearing unusually nervous, Harry read his crafted speech, praising the Invictus Games for uniting injured veterans with ‘humanity to form a family. They exemplify the very best in all of us.’[677] The genuine applause for Harry could not conceal how the controversy about the Sussexes had spread to America. In Britain, Newsweek reported that Meghan’s popularity had collapsed with just 1 per cent of boomers feeling ‘very positive’ about her. A YouGov poll in May reported that Meghan was disliked by 65 per cent of Britons, including 45 per cent whose views were ‘very negative’. Harry’s ratings were only 25 per cent positive.[678] The image of a universally loved Harry had disappeared. America was divided. Once again, Harry was battling.

His appearance at a BetterUp conference in San Francisco to speak about ‘Beyond Burnout: Transforming C-Level Stress into Strength’ – for $1,500 a ticket – was overshadowed by employees complaining about BetterUp’s ‘toxic atmosphere’. While Harry spoke about ‘building resilience’ to cope with ‘unique pressure’, he was also in the firing line from one hundred ex-employees complaining about ‘the worst company I’ve worked for’.[679]

There were similar bad vibes coming from Netflix. Executives watching the polo series’ ‘dailies’ – the video rushes from polo matches across America – were unenthusiastic. ‘No one cares a shit about polo,’ one commented. His sceptical colleagues agreed. Netflix’s viewers had no relationship with polo’s pampered players and their eccentric sport. Netflix’s publicists ventured that the best advertising tag was a series to ‘pull the curtain back on the grit and passion of the sport’. Netflix’s chief content officer, Bela Bajaria, was philosophical: ‘That’s the best they can offer and we’ve got to take something.’[680]

Harry’s original pitch to Netflix promised to closely observe him and Meghan socialising with the super-rich polo set, surrounded by fast-moving, beautiful horses. But contrary to the original understanding, Harry had refused with a brief exception to play any games for the camera. Part of the reason was Meghan’s dislike of polo and horses. Another reason was Harry’s fear of being closely associated in public with racy playboys. That would damage his image as a servant of charities. Instead of Harry as the star, viewers would see his friend Nacho Figueras.

Overhanging all those irritations was Harry’s broken relationship with his family. He insisted on continuing his appeal against the government to secure armed protection in Britain. In sporadic conversations with Palace officials, he insisted that his father could persuade the Home Office to reverse Ravec’s decision for considering bespoke protection on a visit-by-visit basis. The officials’ denial of that possibility was followed by Harry’s continued demands for a suitable time to speak to his father. Disconcertingly, the officials repeated their response: ‘His Majesty is unavailable.’ Charles could see no advantage of an argument with his belligerent son. The result was evident on Father’s Day. William posted a message to Charles. From Harry there was silence.[681]

The schism between Harry and Britain was widening. Having been blacklisted from Hugh Grosvenor’s wedding, he heard that another old friend Hugh van Cutsem had appeared on the popular TV series Clarkson’s Farm, which could have been seen as a slap in the face. Guilty of making disparaging remarks about Meghan, Jeremy Clarkson represented in Harry’s opinion a ‘long-standing pattern of writing articles that spread hate rhetoric, dangerous conspiracy theories and misogyny’.[682]

Harry could not let go of his hatred of the media. Despite Meghan’s advice to stop the lawsuits, his commitment to the battle was entrenched. The tabloids, he believed, were ‘central to the breakdown of my relationship with my family. They’ve caused part of the rift.’ He even cursed the media’s ‘torrent of abuse’ whenever the tabloids accurately described his criticism of the Royal Family. His hostile accusations, he complained, were unsympathetically reported. That disrespect re-energised his crusade against the tabloids.[683] He refocused his sights on Rebekah Brooks, successively editor of the News of the World and the Sun, and currently the chief executive in Britain of Rupert Murdoch’s News UK.

Harry had met Brooks some years earlier at a Sun-sponsored Help for Heroes event in the Imperial War Museum. Exuding charm, Brooks persuaded Harry that she was ‘OK’. In hindsight, he felt ‘duped’ because she was ‘essentially masquerading by using the military community to try to cover up all the appalling things that she and her newspapers had done’.[684] In 2014, Brooks stood trial at the Old Bailey for phone hacking. She was acquitted. The verdict ‘absolutely astonished’ Harry. He was equally angry when Brooks ‘ignored’ his attempts to settle his hacking dispute against the Sun before his wedding. She would not agree to a public apology. In retaliation, Harry banned her journalists from his wedding ceremony.

News UK was a vulnerable target. The News of the World had been closed following the exposure of its journalists’ illegal hacking and several employees – including a past editor – had been jailed. By 2024, News UK had paid compensation on 1,650 claims, but in their settlement agreements they never admitted culpability. Harry, David Sherborne and the solicitors were determined to change that situation. Citing ninety-three newspaper reports allegedly obtained by unlawful activities, Harry and his aggressive co-claimant, the actor Hugh Grant, accused News UK’s journalists of ‘burglary to order’. News UK’s private investigators, said Grant, broke into the houses of celebrities, including his own and Harry’s, to plant bugging devices and steal documents.[685] News UK denied those allegations.

Harry was intent on personally harming Rupert Murdoch and Rebekah Brooks, but the judge refused Harry’s attempt to include those two ‘trophy’ targets in his trial.[686]

By April 2024, the estimated legal bill for Harry, Hugh Grant and other claimants was over £10 million and, once the pre-trial hearings were under way, was expected to reach £30 million by September. Thereafter it would soar. Any ‘celebrity’ who lost his or her claim after a trial could expect to pay ruinous legal expenses of up to £10 million, albeit the costs were largely covered by insurers. But in exceptional circumstances, even victory could be financially ruinous. Hugh Grant was the first to surrender. According to Sherborne, Grant was offered a ‘large amount’ by News UK and was ‘forced’ to accept – albeit, by his insurers. Forty claimants had started the action against News UK in 2019. It was now down to two: Harry and the peer Tom Watson, a former Labour politician. Refusing to capitulate, Harry was determined that Rebekah Brooks should be humiliated in the witness box.[687] ‘One of the main reasons for seeing this through,’ he said, ‘is accountability because I’m the last person that can achieve that.’ Even if the amount he won was ‘a hundred times’ less than the settlement offer, he pledged not to surrender.[688] His insurers made that decision.

Hugh Grant had another good reason to pull out. The judge, Timothy Fancourt, disapproved of Sherborne making unprovable allegations on Harry’s behalf. Not least that the Sun planted ‘bugging’ and ‘tracking’ devices on Chelsy Davy’s car. After failing to produce any evidence, Sherborne withdrew that assertion.[689]

Evidently, Judge Fancourt was similarly irritated by Harry’s sanctimonious attitude. In the witness box, Harry had accused the Mirror and News UK of destroying evidence. Fancourt discovered that Harry had done the same. Harry had ‘wiped [his] entire chat history’ with J.R. Moehringer. All the relevant documents, admitted Harry, had been destroyed, despite him being told by the judge to keep them. ‘That’s troubling,’ observed Fancourt. Equally suspicious was that Harry had failed to disclose many relevant documents handed over to him by Buckingham Palace. Fancourt accused Harry of ‘obfuscating’ and creating an ‘obstacle course’ for News UK. The Prince was ordered to sign a witness statement to explain his conduct and pay £60,000 in legal costs.[690]

A judge’s criticism did not trouble Harry. Reassured by his lawyers of eventual victory, only Meghan’s complaints caused any friction. His courtroom battles were damaging to her brand. For two years, she had tried to keep silent about the Royal Family and Britain. On the eve of launching her Netflix series, she wanted the focus on her, not on Harry’s battles. She needed another curtain-raiser.

At the end of July 2024, Meghan flew in a private jet from Santa Barbara to the Hamptons with Jamie Kern Lima, the billionaire cosmetics founder of IT Cosmetics. Lima’s rags-to-riches story – surviving after a six-year battle to stave off bankruptcy which climaxed in the sale of her company to L’Oréal for $1.2 billion – impressed Meghan.[691] Instinctively, Meghan equated herself with Lima. ‘Oh, Jamie,’ Meghan said with total sincerity, ‘I feel like we haven’t talked about our blood type. But yours is probably an A positive like mine. Because even my blood is overachieving.’ [692]

Both were heading for a party hosted by Amy Griffin, the wife of billionaire hedge fund owner John Griffin. Among the other guests were the billionaire Sara Blakely, the founder of the women’s shapewear company Spanx, and Gwyneth Paltrow.[693] Gossip later suggested that Paltrow and others had deliberately avoided being photographed with Meghan.[694]

To impress Lima in the run-up to her Netflix series, Meghan sent a basket of jam and other American Riviera Orchard products with a printed card signed, ‘With Compliments HRH Duchess of Sussex’. To please Meghan, Lima posted a photograph of the basket with Meghan’s card. That provoked fury in London. Meghan was accused of breaking her agreement with the Queen not to use ‘HRH’.[695] That same day, Meghan’s spokesman blatantly denied that Meghan used her HRH title.[696] And then he refined his denial. Meghan, he said, did not use the HRH ‘for commercial purposes’ but only ‘informally among friends’.[697] Appearing later on an episode of Lima’s eponymous podcast, Meghan could not resist telling Jamie Lima that her life among the Royal Family was like ‘being in the trenches’.[698] Yet, once again, she had used that very family to promote herself.

CHAPTER 35

Colombia

In spring 2024, Meghan had received an invitation out of the blue from a Colombian politician to pay a four-day ‘state visit’ to the South American country. The politician, Francia Márquez, was Colombia’s controversial vice president. Márquez’s explanation for her unexpected initiative excited Meghan.

After watching Meghan and Harry in their original Netflix series – Harry & Meghan – wrote Márquez, she felt a kinship with the Duchess. As the descendant of African slaves and the first Colombian to reach such high office, she wanted to join with Meghan to ‘build bridges, open doors and address a problem which concerns all of humanity’. Known for leading the country’s anti-imperialist call for reparations from former colonial powers, Márquez was openly impressed by the historians’ denunciations of the British Empire and Commonwealth in the series. Meghan, she assumed, sympathised with her battle against the white supremacist exploitation of black people and the end of capitalism. As Colombia’s minister of equality, wrote Márquez, she shared Meghan’s passion for empowering women and protecting young people from cyberbullying. Not mentioned was Márquez’s assumption that at the end of their visit, Archewell would donate generously to her causes.

Meghan had every reason to embrace Márquez as a compatriot offering her a platform. Even Márquez’s opponents could not deny her remarkable backstory. The 41-year-old lawyer had slept as a child on a dirt floor, worked in a gold mine at sixteen, was abandoned when pregnant and led marches to stop illegal gold mining. But Meghan evidently did not consider Márquez’s motives for the invitation. To her countrymen, the reasons were obvious: the beleaguered left-wing politician needed to boost her reputation. Accused of corruption and fearful of assassination, she was forced to travel across her drug cartel-dominated country by helicopter. Under her left-wing government, poverty in Colombia had increased from 30.9 per cent in 2016 to 34.5 per cent in 2022, well above Latin America’s average of 24.1 per cent. Extreme poverty had also increased in the same period, from 12 per cent to 16.9 per cent.[699] Despite those grim statistics, Márquez had allegedly used public funds to build a large private house.

To agree upon the details of their visit, Meghan dispatched three trusted women to Bogotá: her chief of staff Miranda Barbot, her publicity chief Ashley Hansen and Shauna Nep, Archewell’s co-executive director earning $300,000 annually.

Meghan’s representatives met Andrea Alfonso, a professional diplomat, and Tatiana Escobar, a lawyer assigned to Márquez’s office. Alfonso explained that the invitation stemmed from Márquez’s shared interest to make the internet safer. To the Colombians’ surprise, the visitors did not question the events that the government proposed. Rather, they focused on the Sussexes’ security as they travelled across the violent county. Once they were assured of receiving the same intense security as Márquez, they agreed on a schedule. Márquez was unaware that Meghan intended to use the visit to promote herself as a fashion influencer.

To protect the Sussexes from potential assassins, there would be no advance notice of their visit. Every venue would only be told of their identity shortly before their arrival. The media, Barbot insisted, would not be given access. No foreign journalists were to be allowed entry to any event – except the Harper’s Bazaar columnist Bianca Betancourt, alongside Archewell’s photographer and cameraman Eric Charbonneau.[700] Betancourt was chosen to focus solely on Meghan’s fashion choices and ‘accurately’ praise the visit without providing details. Branding was Meghan’s priority. Even before her arrival in Colombia, Meghan had arranged that her ‘fashion portfolio’, or post-London ‘freedom style’, would feature in Harper’s Bazaar and in the New York Times.[701]

On the eve of welcoming the Sussexes, Márquez began to fear the backlash. The former housemaid was frequently condemned by her opponents as ‘the biggest fraud in the black community’ for doing nothing for the poor but spending money on herself. As a known anti-royalist, her critics said, she was cynically using the Sussexes to divert attention from the scandals of a corrupt, violent government.

On Márquez’s orders, the source of funding for the Sussexes’ trip was to remain secret. Although Márquez would claim that Archewell paid for all their hotel and travel expenses, the costs have not appeared in Archewell’s accounts. As the government’s guests, the Sussexes would not expect to pay. Their hotels – the presidential suite at the Four Seasons in Bogotá and the best suites at the Sofitel Legend in Cartagena and at the Marriott in Cali – cost about £2,500 per night. In addition, they would need eight rooms for their entourage. To rebut those Colombian politicians questioning the £2.9 million cost of the Sussexes’ trip, Márquez would publish ‘official’ accounts identifying the total government costs as just £44,725. The remainder, she said, was funded by ‘philanthropic resources’.[702] That was a reference to Open Society, an international charity financed by George Soros, the billionaire fund manager. Márquez agreed with Meghan that Soros’s involvement should be kept secret, including their use of a private jet.

The only hiccup before the Sussexes’ departure was the resignation of Harry’s chief of staff, Josh Kettler. On his appointment, Kettler was heralded as ‘guiding [Harry] through his next phase’. Three months later, both sides agreed ‘he wasn’t the right fit’. Kettler was the nineteenth employee known to leave Montecito since 2020. Other appointments and resignations were not published.[703] [704]

Harry was not in a good mood when the private jet landed in Bogotá on 15th August in secrecy. On the journey to the city centre in a convoy of bulletproof cars driven by special forces, surrounded by nine armoured cars filled with heavily armed military, Harry looked glum. He was under pressure. Not least because of reports that William reportedly would ban Harry from his coronation.[705]

Fifteen minutes after landing, the convoy arrived at the presidential palace, the Casa de Nariño. The visitors were welcomed by Francia Márquez and her partner, Yerney Pinillo. For thirty minutes they chatted over tea, coffee and traditional Colombian cheese bread. Then they headed for a quick change before the first event. Advised by a team of stylists, Meghan had brought outfits by eleven designers for every public appearance. The ‘Meghan Effect’ would be enhanced by her make-up artist and hairdresser travelling in her entourage.

Dressed in a $2,150 metallic jacquard dress, wearing $875 Jimmy Choo sandals, and a gold Cartier necklace and rings valued at $23,550, plus a Tank Française watch inherited from Diana,[706] Meghan arrived at the National Arts Centre (CNA) to watch a dance group.Next, the Sussexes joined a panel discussion with Márquez in a half-filled room about the perils of fake news on social media for social cohesion. The audience was more interested in Meghan’s metallic outfit.[707]

For the following event, Meghan wore clothes by White Mango and Banana Republic with a Cesta Collective basket bag handwoven in Rwanda. ‘With Cesta,’ Meghan said, ‘I really started to understand how many women’s lives were being impacted and uplifted through their work.’ Living in mud huts, the ‘uplifted’ women making the bags earned ten pence an hour, a total of £2.48 for each bag. The bag sold in America for $724.[708]

As a philanthropic businessperson on a humanitarian mission, Meghan also touted a £556 Mini Fan Bag. The bag had been previously promoted by Vogue and Net-a-Porter. Her publicist offered a quote from Meghan about her gift to support designers of ‘smaller, up-and-coming brands that haven’t got the attention that they should be getting’. Followers of her Instagram account were guided to her ‘ShopMy page’ to buy her choice of clothes and accessories, aware that she would take a commission.[709]

The next morning, dressed in a navy Veronica Beard suit and black Manolo Blahnik heels, with a £3,775 Loro Piana ‘Loom’ handbag and Diana’s gold butterfly earrings, Meghan led Harry into the Colegio Cultura school for another discussion about the impact of social media. The headmaster, Leonel Parra, had been told to expect ‘an important’ visitor. The school building was locked down by armed soldiers when the couple arrived three hours late. As Harry started to speak to a student, Meghan’s eyes closed, her hands became tightly clasped and she gave him a sharp look. He nodded obediently and stopped talking. Meghan addressed the student in Spanish. Soon after, Meghan did what had now become an almost ‘love swoon’ ritual – leaning her head on to Harry’s shoulder, looking up at him doe-eyed and holding his hand.

Next, they headed to the Fanny Mikey theatre to watch fifteen minutes of a romantic Spanish drama. Their visit, the director Xiomara Suescún was told, was planned to raise a substantial donation from the Sussexes. ‘That man’s not wearing underwear,’ Harry observed of an actor with painted buttocks. ‘Don’t look at him from the front,’ joked Suescún. Noticing their laughter, Meghan swiftly moved close to Harry and pulled him away.[710] Ignoring Suescún, she posed affectionately with Harry for their photographer, Eric Charbonneau. ‘Did you understand it?’ Suescún asked Harry after the performance. ‘So-so,’ replied Harry. Suescún laughed. ‘It’s about a girl who’s meant to marry a rich man. But at the last moment she runs off to marry somebody poor.’ Harry looked baffled.[711]

Exiting through the theatre’s garage, Meghan did a quick clothes change into a pink and gold minidress and headed for a dance display. Harry, the CNA’s staff noticed, had become ‘stiff’. The Colombians realised that he was cast as the supporting act for Meghan’s visit.

On the following day, dressed in a £1,595 Johanna Ortiz ‘showstopper’ dress, Meghan visited the La Giralda school. Locals reported that all the children had been ordered to curtsy.[712] ‘You’re the same age as my son Archie,’ said Meghan to a curtsying girl. Like the other designers of Meghan’s clothes, Ortiz testified that after her appearance the ‘Meghan Effect’ had sparked ‘a phenomenal amount of orders’.[713]

The day’s highlight was lunch for thirty government officials and businessmen. Dressed in a £5,000 sleeveless cerulean Oscar de la Renta dress described by Harper’s as ‘fantastic’, with a Logan Hollowell necklace and earrings that had belonged to Diana, the Duchess swept into Márquez’s official residence.[714] Harry followed. With the exception of Eric Charbonneau, the media were kept out. ‘Everything Márquez does,’ said one of the politician’s aides, ‘ends up being mocked, criticised or ridiculed. So, no media to avoid that.’

Rey Guerrero, a trusted chef, had been hired by Márquez six months earlier. ‘I started researching what they liked to eat,’ revealed Guerrero. Harry, he discovered, ‘has a big sweet tooth and loves a specific kind of chicken from a place in London, but obviously I wasn’t going to cook fried chicken.’ Instead, Guerrero picked seafood – arropado, or wrapped – and Diana’s favourite mango sorbet drink. And for Meghan, he baked a lemon cake. ‘They really enjoyed the richness of the Pacific cuisine,’ recalled Guerrero. ‘A lot of love and surprise.’[715]

Sitting on the side of an undecorated room, Harry made little effort to look interested. People nodded towards him and then switched away. The focus throughout the tour was on Meghan.[716] As she spoke to the officials, Harry picked at a plate of food. His morose face barely changed as he was accosted by Guerrero offering a glass of viche, a strong traditional liquor. ‘Very good for your sex life and fertility,’ said the smiling Colombian in Spanish. After the translation, Harry forced a fleeting laugh.[717]

By the third day, Harry was wilting. Meghan, ever the professional, was in Harper’s Bazaar’s words ‘radiating warm Californian energy’.[718] The Sussexes were unaware of the widespread protest against the millions spent on the visit. ‘Instead of worrying about the economy that affects everyone, they are worried about bowing to the English nobility,’ said an opponent of Márquez.[719]

That morning, the Sussexes arrived by helicopter in Cali, the capital of the cocaine cartels. Hundreds of soldiers and police lined the street to keep the public away.[720] Fawning officials greeted Meghan at a school on La Boquilla beach. After listening to children hammering on drums, she spoke about human rights. Her audience lived in a neighbourhood infested by crime and drugs. Among the hosts was Taliana Vargas, the wife of Cali’s mayor and a former Miss Colombia. After a big fake smile, Meghan gaslit Vargas.[721]

Next came a helicopter ride to San Basilio de Palenque, historically the first town on the continent for liberated African slaves, founded after a revolt in 1599. For Márquez, Palenque was ‘the symbol of resistance and voices against injustice’. Highlighting ‘Archewell’s lifelong philanthropic endeavours’, Harper’s Bazaar also reported that Meghan had ‘executed a flawless outfit change’ into a white linen skirt and wore a Cartier necklace and a watch owned by Diana.[722]

In intense humid heat, surrounded by a group of locals, the Sussexes walked across a grim square towards a memorial to a slave uprising. Just a few people heard Harry apologise for his family’s role in the slave trade. ‘He should ask for a pardon,’ said Segundo Reyes, the president of the town’s police. Another local urged Harry to ‘repent’.[723] After the translation Harry nodded.

‘The locals were also not impressed by the royals,’ recalled Ricardo Maldonado, a photographer. ‘Palenqueros would not even give a damn if the Pope came.’ A tour of the museum about slavery planned to take fifteen minutes was over within three minutes.[724] Outside, a red-faced Harry spoke about an ‘incredibly moving experience’. Harry and Meghan made an attempt to look interested as local musicians played discordant notes and community leaders spoke about their suffering and poverty.[725] But then their façade collapsed.

Márquez had spotted Meghan embracing and then rubbing the back of her partner, Yerney Pinillo. Meghan was oblivious to the effect of her behaviour. The photographers perked up.‘Flirtgate’ was a bonus. Furious about the gift Meghan was creating for her political opponents, the vice president strode angrily towards the couple. Instinctively, Harry stuck his arms out to stop her and then, conscious of cameras snapping, turned his movement into a handshake.

The next venue afforded a conversation between Meghan and Márquez.[726] Harry sat alone in the nearly empty stalls of a theatre as Márquez introduced Meghan, who was now wearing a Mango shirt, a £1,634 Silvia Tcherassi sequin skirt and magenta Manolo Blahnik heels. Stressing the financial obstacles facing her community, Márquez spoke about Colombia’s black population needing special financial help.The Sussexes, explained the vice president, were expected to make a serious donation to match George Soros’s Open Society’s donations. Meghan did not mention that Archewell’s total budget in 2024 was less than $2 million. Open Society’s was $400 million.

Ignoring the appeal for money, Meghan replied in Spanish about the need for ‘Colombian women to empower each other’. Women’s voices, said Meghan standing next to the female vice president, ‘are not being heard’. Then Meghan moved on to speak about herself. Firstly, she reiterated the bogus story about her campaign as an eleven-year-old to pressurise Procter & Gamble to change the script of their advertisement for Ivory Clear washing-up liquid from ‘Women all over America are fighting greasy pots and pans’ to ‘People all over America’,[727] and then she promoted Archewell for being ‘very, very dedicated to creating a sense of community’.

Her source of inspiration, said Meghan, was her mother – the same mother who had disappeared for long periods throughout her school years. In reply, Márquez described how her mother had lost her fingerprints while working in a mine. One result was that she could not obtain a passport to travel. Women and children in Colombia, continued Márquez, faced random violence – rape, beatings and murder.

Taking the microphone, Meghan told her Afro-Colombian audience the cure to their hardship: ‘wash things over with love, kindness and generosity’. Only Harry in her audience would have known about Meghan’s treatment of her father, her friends and her ‘bullied’ staff.

Concluding what Harper’s described as ‘a powerful conversation’, Meghan focused on herself again: ‘I’m looking at this time as my chapter of joy. My intentionality is to enjoy this chapter and be able to love through every piece of this as best we can.’ In her audience were eyewitnesses of local drug abuse, torture, rape and murder. As she intoned with a smile the Brené Brown meme, ‘There is something so liberating about being able to be yourself and be comfortable in your skin; and be surrounded in a space that is excited to see you exactly the way you are,’ the audience appeared unsure how to react.[728] And then, with another big smile, Meghan moved on to her core message: being ‘a mom’. Lilibet, Meghan enthused, has ‘found her voice and we are so proud of that’. Meghan seemed unaware about the bathos of her sentiments, which she would repeat many times.[729]

Few in the audience could understand how a three-year-old’s words in Montecito equated with Márquez’s plight. ‘Something very painful for me,’ explained Márquez in her final contribution, ‘are the 6,000 young people assassinated every year in Colombia. I think of my two children who I had to send out of the country because of threats to their lives.’ Meghan’s expression suggested that she was totally unaware of Márquez’s personal pain of being separated from her sons – the only safeguard from the widespread murder of Colombian children. Tone-deaf, Meghan responded to her host, ‘Colombia is a beacon of culture and innovation.’ The meeting ended in disarray. Márquez’s appeal to Meghan for a donation appeared to be ignored.[730]

After another clothes swap – the eighteenth in four days – Meghan appeared at an Afro-Colombian music festival in a green dress made by the Colombian designer, Andrés Otálora. As usual, during the four days, the ‘What Meghan Wore’ website identified the shops selling the clothes she had selected for the trip.[731]

It was the moment for Márquez to pounce. In front of a crowd excited by the fevered music, the vice president stood with the Sussexes and the mayor to challenge Harry. As one of the world’s campaigners for reparations to ‘repair the historical debt owed’ from the colonial powers, Márquez asked Harry to comment. The Prince obliged. He denounced the ‘unjust’ system that had generated wealth for the British Crown from ‘enslaved people’. Márquez smiled. She was satisfied. Harry smiled. No one in Britain, he would have surely assumed, would hear about his disloyal comments. Thankfully, he would soon be returning to his sun-blessed mansion overlooking the ocean.[732] As usual during the four days, the ‘What Meghan Wore’ website identified the shops selling the clothes she wore that evening.

Although the majority of Colombians remained unaware of the Sussexes’ visit, Andrea Alfonso reported a ‘success’ and anticipated Archewell contributing millions of dollars to Márquez’s projects.[733] Although the Sussexes bombarded the media with announcements of their generosity,[734] Archewell’s annual accounts revealed their donation of just $8,310.[735]

Meghan was delighted by the trip.Every day, websites and the mainstream media in America and Britain had featured Eric Charbonneau’s photographs of her in all the different outfits alongside her smiling husband. Fortunately, none reported the patchy reception by the small groups inside the schools and venues. Triumphantly, the Sussexes had orchestrated the image of a radiant British royal couple on a ‘state’ tour.

On the plane back to California, the Sussexes’ publicist Ashley Hansen collapsed.[736] Stressed by the long hours, suffering anxiety and depression, she had faced a challenge to balance her life with the Sussexes’ demands. The negative agenda about her employers seeping into the public consciousness from British newspapers and social media, plus the strained conversations with journalists, had drained her. During the return flight, she later said, ‘The flight attendant thought I was actually dead. I was so out hard sleeping, I did not move the entire time.’[737]

By the time Hansen finally awoke, another of the Sussexes’ employees was already planning her resignation.

CHAPTER 36

Sidelined

At 4.29pm on Monday 11th September 2024, Kensington Palace released a three-minute glossy video showing the Princess of Wales with her family celebrating the end of her chemotherapy treatment. ‘The last nine months have been incredibly tough for us as a family,’ she said emotionally. ‘The cancer journey is complex, scary, unpredictable for everyone, especially for those closest to you.’

The video was criticised by some as syrupy but no one could dispute Kate’s desire to terminate the malicious online speculation about her health: ‘With humility, it also brings you face to face with your own vulnerabilities in a way you have never considered before . . . and be grateful for the simple yet important things in life which so many of us take for granted. Of simply loving and being loved.’[738]

Exactly 100 minutes later, in the now-familiar tit-for-tat battle, the Montecito publicists responded. At 18.09, Netflix released a video to promote Harry’s polo series starting in December.[739] The emphasis was on Harry who ‘with unprecedented access gives a glimpse into the sport of kings’. Since Harry had refused to participate in any of the matches and was practically invisible until the last episode, everyone had agreed to a low-key release. ‘We’ve got a giant clunker,’ was the sentiment inside Netflix’s headquarters. ‘It’s a runny omelette,’ sniped one executive.[740]

Bela Bajaria, Netflix’s head of content, had signed off on the series. She would be judged by far broader metrics than the success or failure of any one show, especially one as minor as Harry’s. Netflix had suffered serious big-budget failures including Marco Polo and The Ridiculous 6 without consequences. Flops could be absorbed by a corporation producing content on a massive scale while its subscription base grew and annual revenue headed in 2024 towards $39 billion.

Both Bajaria and Ted Sarandos acknowledged that Harry and Meghan were no longer Netflix’s ‘golden duo’, but they brought value to Netflix’s stable. When trying to persuade other celebrities to make a show with the streamer, Netflix cited their trusted relationship with the Sussexes. Meghan, Sarandos said, ‘is underestimated in terms of her influence on culture. People are fascinated with Meghan Markle.’[741]

Sensing Bajaria’s disillusionment, Meghan had persuaded Harry to let the polo series disappear. Harry would refuse to do any promotional interviews and not even host a screening. The Sussexes’ priority was Meghan’s new homemaker series. On the eve of his fortieth birthday, Harry agreed. Sidelined in Colombia, the reality of his isolation from his family and Britain had hit him two weeks earlier.

Unannounced, Harry had secretly flown to London to attend his uncle-in-law’s memorial service in Snettisham in Norfolk. Eighty-two-year-old Robert Fellowes had played a critical role as the Queen’s private secretary when Diana died, not only giving controversial advice to the Royal Family about their conduct but also consoling his wife Jane Spencer, Diana’s sister. Since that fateful night in 1997, Jane had become Harry’s surrogate mother, watching his matches at Eton and acting as godmother to Archie. As Harry’s allies, not least at the recent service in St Paul’s for the Invictus Games, the Spencers encouraged Harry’s defiance of his father. Charles had never been forgiven by the Spencers for his neglect of Diana.

Across the aisle from Harry in the small fourteenth-century church sat William. The brothers had not spoken for nearly two years. They continued to ignore each other. Their feud continued at the wake in a marquee. Harry stayed overnight in Britain without making any attempt to contact or visit his father in Balmoral. The following day, he flew back to Los Angeles.

The belated newspaper reports of his unexpected visit sparked speculation that Harry was looking for a return to Britain. Swiftly, Harry ordered his spokeswoman to scotch the suggestion. Harry, said Hansen, had ‘no interest’ in Britain. His future was among his new friends and new interests in California.[742]

The latest opinion polls reported that Harry remained popular among Americans – 49 per cent, stated YouGov, were positive and only 24 per cent negative. By comparison, only 38 per cent of Americans were positive about Charles and 33 per cent were negative. To Harry’s irritation, 54 per cent were positive about William and only 14 per cent negative.[743]

The bad news was Harry’s unpopularity in Britain. Only 26 per cent said they were positive about him, while 75 per cent were positive about William and 63 per cent were positive about Charles; and 60 per cent of those polled were either opposed or undecided whether Harry should resume any royal duties in Britain.

Visiting journalists nosily seeking titbits about Harry’s life in Montecito were reminded of his feud in the recently opened local bookshop, Godmothers, co-owned by Jennifer Rudolph Walsh, Harry’s literary agent, and the cosmetics manufacturer Victoria Jackson. Prominently displayed on the shelf for ‘Hometown Heroes’ was his autobiography.[744] Clearly, Harry was proud of his book despite the anger his disclosures had generated in London. No one at Penguin Random House ever heard the author voice any regrets about his subversive agenda. That was reinforced during the summer as James Holt organised an international media blitz to move Harry out of Meghan’s shadow, assert Harry’s global importance and further embarrass his family. And then his campaign was delayed. Unexpectedly, another torpedo was heading towards Brand Sussex.

‘Why Hollywood Keeps Quitting on Harry and Meghan’ was the Hollywood Reporter’s headline on 11th September 2024, prompted by the resignation of their publicist Christine Weil Schirmer. ‘They’ve chewed up yet another American advisor,’ said an observer.[745] ‘Everyone’s terrified of Meghan,’ an insider told the magazine. ‘She belittles people, marching around, barking orders like “a dictator in high heels”.’ Meghan’s ‘barks’, added the recently departed employee, reduced ‘grown men to tears’. Another ex-employee confirmed that ‘everyone is terrified of Meghan Markle’. Describing the Sussexes’ behaviour, the source added: ‘She doesn’t take advice. They are both poor decision-makers who change their minds frequently.’[746]

Until then, few in America had believed the 2018 British media’s allegations of a toxic atmosphere at Kensington Palace caused by Meghan’s bullying of her staff. Newspaper columnists on the New York Times and elsewhere had accepted the Sussexes’ riposte that they were victims of a ‘calculated smear campaign’ inspired by the Royal Family’s racism.

Many would have even listened to Meghan’s self-justification at the time on her Archetypes podcast: ‘I find myself cowering and tiptoeing into a room and – the thing I find most embarrassing – when you’re saying a sentence and the intonation goes up, and you’re like, “Oh my God, stop whispering and tiptoeing around it. Just say what it is you need. You’re allowed to be clear. It doesn’t make you demanding. It doesn’t make you difficult, it makes you clear.”’ [747]

However, compounding the damage done by the Hollywood Reporter headline, the Daily Beast found another eyewitness. She described Meghan as a boss who became a ‘demon when the worm turns’. That insider said about the Sussexes, ‘There definitely were bad, very bad, even psycho moments. I witnessed people being chewed up in person and over the phone and made to feel like shit.’ [748] In Britain, there was pleasure among the expanding Sussex Survivors Club that ‘Duchess Difficult’ had once again failed to suppress stories of her bullying.

Meghan claimed that she was oblivious to any criticism because she could ‘tune out the negative noise’.[749] Frequently, she repeated Georgia O’Keefe’s quip, ‘I have already settled it for myself, so flattery and criticism go down the same drain and I am quite free.’ [750] Few believed she was so thick-skinned.

Meghan ordered Ashley Hansen to launch a detoxification counter-attack. Contacting Dan Wakeford, the friendly editor of the tabloid magazine US Weekly and formerly of People magazine, Hansen denounced the Hollywood Reporter’s quotations as ‘fabricated’. Under the headline ‘The Truth About Meghan: Her Staff Break Their Silence’, she placed fawning accolades by former members of Meghan’s staff about their saintly employer.[751] ‘The best boss ever, was wonderful to work for,’ attested one ex-employee. Staff were given baskets of freshly cut flowers, fruit and eggs from the Sussexes’ rescue chickens to take home, said another. She made her team ‘feel like seeds being watered’ said a third. Staff were grateful that when a great idea was offered at a meeting, ‘she makes sure to give props to the person who generated the idea.’ When Meghan heard that an employee had adopted a dog, she instantly sent a ‘luxury-brand leash and a new collar’.

Mandana Dayani, employed for eighteen months until 2022, described being treated to ‘incredible lunches’ and Meghan’s ‘latest beautiful concoctions’ during their weekly meetings in Montecito. Catherine St-Laurent attested that her eleven months with Meghan had been ‘incredibly meaningful’. Like the others, St-Laurent was silent about the cause of her abrupt departure. Even Josh Kettler swooned that the Sussexes were ‘dedicated and hard-working’ and he had been ‘warmly welcomed’. He steadfastly refused to reveal why he had abruptly quit – or was fired. He also omitted any relationship with the Sussexes in his updated online biography.[752]

Only Ashley Hansen herself recalled how she herself was treated ‘with love and care’ when she asked for time off work for surgery. Meghan had sent flowers and care packages. And yet despite her positive comments, amid the hysteria inside Meghan’s home, like her predecessors, Hansen too woke up to the reality of life with the Sussexes. She prepared to announce her own departure from Archewell and reset her life by fleeing to a remote retreat barring all contact with the outside world. She was the twentieth major resignation since the Sussexes set up their business.[753]

In a move likely to divert attention from Meghan’s crisis, Bryony Gordon, a British journalist who had confessed to having suffered from alcoholism, depression and drug addiction and was an advocate of Harry’s,[754] was invited to visit Montecito. The Sussexes’ trusted messenger described ‘a pretty ordinary couple existing in an absolutely extraordinary situation. There’s no airs or graces with them.’ [755]

There were certainly no special celebrations on Harry’s fortieth birthday. Unlike the riotous black-tie dinner for his thirtieth birthday at Clarence House, ten years later there were few friends to invite in Montecito and no one was welcomed into their home. Harry just gave the BBC a statement: ‘I was anxious about thirty. I’m excited about forty. Whatever my age, my mission is to continue showing up and doing good in the world.’ On the Palace website, Charles and the Waleses simply wished ‘The Duke of Sussex a Happy 40th’. Neither signed off with their names.[756] Their post was illustrated with a photo of Harry taken in 2018. Meghan had been cropped out of it.

After taking his children to school and cycling with David ‘Langers’ Langdown, his security guard, Harry’s publicist fed speculation that he would spend the evening hiking in the Santa Ynez Mountains with his polo friend Nacho Figueras.[757] Days later, he posted an Instagram video of himself spending the day at the joyless Kelly Slater’s Surf Ranch in Lemoore, California.

Harry was fed up. Not just with his family but also with his fate. The trips to Nigeria and Colombia had cast him as yet another ‘spare’, the second fiddle, the support for Meghan’s brand. What had been mutual survival and then mutual interest had become his separate survival. There was a lot of gossip that he and Meghan were on divergent paths. The combination of his family’s perfunctory messages and her self-interest appeared to incentivise Harry to strike deep to reassert himself.

The Prince’s revival started at the annual fundraiser for Santa Barbara’s emergency services hosted by Kevin Costner. Ten days after the Hollywood Reporter’s derision, Meghan disappointed the hosts by failing to appear at the One805Live! concert in Montecito, despite accepting the invitation. ‘She looked bored to tears last year,’ admitted an organiser. A ‘sick child’ was the excuse. But Harry’s presence was a ‘big plus’ for those paying $1,600 for a ticket.[758] He enjoyed mingling with first responders and supporting his community. Presenting an award to a helicopter pilot, Harry joked that he felt more comfortable flying a helicopter than speaking on stage. ‘He really was terrific,’ volunteered the organiser.

Harry arrived alone in New York. To relaunch himself as a philanthropist, he appeared at eleven public engagements over the following twelve days. But first his publicists sought to wipe out the gossip about Meghan’s tyranny – and the speculation about their marriage problems.

The publicists’ theme had taken days to finesse: ‘What we are seeing is a functional and healthy relationship with two working partners – not the contrary,’ said their publicist. The friendly People magazine ‘revealed’ their supposedly shrewd PR move: the Sussexes had evolved a ‘twin-track approach’ – he was into philanthropy while Meghan focused on her business.[759] British diplomats were impressed by his itinerary. ‘A canny operator,’ one said. Harry was using ‘backdoor’ diplomacy to assert his royal position.

Harry’s first speech at the Clinton Global Initiative highlighted the fatal impact of social media on ‘thousands’ of vulnerable children.[760] All the young children projected on to a screen behind him, he told his audience – which included Bill Clinton, Bill Nelson, the head of NASA, Queen Mathilde of Belgium and Laurene Jobs, the widow of Apple’s co-founder – were dead. Social media was to blame. Calling for ‘compassion rather than hate’, he urged his audience that, ‘As long as we are debating over lies, we will forever be divided.’ Some would question how the author of Spare, a book of hate, justified that appeal. Others would question Harry’s statement: ‘The Archewell Foundation and me and my wife believe that information integrity is a fundamental right.’[761] Seventeen untrue statements in the Oprah Winfrey interview undermined that pronouncement. And two High Court judges in London had openly suspected Harry’s veracity.

In quick succession, he went to a dinner hosted by the World Health Organization to honour survivors of childhood violence; made a speech to the Halo Trust founded by Diana and presented awards for winners of Diana’s foundation; and made a speech on climate change and promoted Travalyst alongside Bill Gates in the ‘Titan’ category of Time magazine’s ‘100 most influential leaders’ on climate action. In contrast, Prince William and his 2024 Earthshot Prize were ignored by Time’s editors.[762]

Potentially the most difficult event was the African Parks presentation at the Metropolitan Club chaired by the American journalist Katie Couric. The media was excluded from hearing the panel’s discussion about a $1 billion ‘action plan’ to achieve African Parks’ ‘ambitious goals and measurable successes in combating climate change, protecting vital ecosystems and enhancing local livelihoods in Africa’.[763] Harry preferred to be protected from questions by the media at the very time that new allegations of abuse, rape and torture in the Congo surfaced.[764] Under pressure from Survival International to resign, Harry’s office replied that the New York event ‘showcased the transformative work the organisation is undertaking across the continent, emphasising their innovative “conservation at scale” initiatives’. The organisation denied any abuse of tribesmen and claimed that all ‘allegations of misconduct are thoroughly investigated and acted on’. Harry’s critics were unconvinced. ‘Harry has neither the tools nor the experience to navigate out of the crisis,’ said an insider.[765] Instead, Harry endorsed African Parks’ expansion plans by joining the board of directors, one of eight white men with one white woman.[766] However, he did not oppose African Parks’ commissioning of an investigation into the allegations by Cherie Blair’s law firm, Omnia Strategy.[767]

Harry arrived thirty minutes late at his last formal event. Organised by the Lesotho delegation to the United Nations, it was to support Sentebale. Smiling, he embraced Queen Masenate Mohato Seeiso and other members of the royal family. He was among friends. ‘I wish I could spend more time in Africa,’ he said. ‘I have this sense of complete relaxation and normality in Africa.’[768]

Not mentioned was his failure to visit Lesotho for five years, despite him saying, ‘Africa’s in my soul.’[769] Since Harry’s marriage in 2018, said Chief Khoabane Theko, Seeiso’s brother who lived near a Sentebale centre, ‘I haven’t seen him.’ Harry’s fading attention, said Theko, had ‘killed the spirit of the charity’.[770] Contrary to Buckingham Palace’s original proposal in 2018 for the Sussexes to live as philanthropists in South Africa, Meghan’s apparent preference for not living in Africa had outrightly sabotaged the plan carefully organised by Christopher Geidt and the Foreign Office.[771]

To boost Harry’s street credibility, James Holt had arranged two more engagements. In a filmed visit to an East Side tattoo parlour, Harry declined to have one on his neck. ‘I was thinking like my lower back or my arse,’ he told the tattooist Jelly Roll. ‘No one,’ Roll replied, ‘wants to see your arse, Harry.’ Next, he made an appearance to mark Hallowe’en on Jimmy Fallon’s Tonight Show. Walking through the set – a haunted maze – he screamed ‘Jesus Fuck!’[772]

His next stop was London. No protection officers were waiting at Heathrow and the Palace had not offered him any accommodation. His successful appearance in Lancaster Gate at the WellChild awards to celebrate the resilience of seriously ill children renewed speculation that he would fly to Scotland to meet the King. But Harry did not approach his father.[773] The following morning, he flew to Lesotho. It was a make-or-break moment.

CHAPTER 37

Sentebale

In her ‘Return to South Africa’ plan, Sophie Chandauka had arranged for Harry to host a fundraising programme for Sentebale in Lesotho. While Harry’s publicist briefed that he would go for a prolonged trip away from the strife in Los Angeles and London to live in the bush, his true mission was to recover control of Sentebale. That objective had begun in May 2024, just days after his return from Nigeria.

Sentebale, Harry had been persuaded, could only survive as part of the Archewell brand. The obstacle to that reorganisation was Chandauka. Her insistence on obeying the governance rules for charities challenged his authority. Indeed, it seemed to Harry that Chandauka was using these rules as a weapon to assert herself. For Harry, anyone refusing total sycophancy was cast as an opponent. Ever since the Florida polo match, Chandauka had fallen into that category. Harry knew she would refuse to allow a charity to become a branch of Archewell. Hitherto, the public had never known or witnessed Harry’s treatment of those who refused to bow to his orders. That was about to change.

At Sentebale’s board meeting on Zoom on 24th May, Harry unexpectedly announced that his good friend Brian Satz, a music director and event producer from New Jersey, would join the board. As the leader of the American friends of Sentebale, Satz had raised £593,508 for the charity. Harry’s announcement ‘shocked’ Chandauka. All the rules of governance, she protested, had been ignored: Satz’s appointment was not on the agenda, Harry refused any time for discussion and Satz had never been to South Africa. But within five minutes of Harry’s announcement, Mark Dyer declared, ‘As no one has voted against Brian’s appointment, it’s been approved. This meeting’s over.’ All the Zoom screens went blank. Chandauka was outraged by the coup.‘This is not how we will do things,’ Chandauka emailed to the board members. She was ignored. Harry, she believed, was tolerating her as ‘window dressing’, but she feared she would become the fall guy if anything went wrong.

Within one hour, Satz sent his photograph and biography to be posted on Sentebale’s website. ‘This was not a valid appointment,’ Chandauka replied with a copy of the governance rules.

‘Who do you think you are?’ emailed Dyer. ‘This is what Harry wanted.’

‘This isn’t how we do things,’ Chandauka shot back. As a patron, Harry was not a board member, she wrote. Harry had no authority to propose Satz. The Prince had ignored the rules.

Four weeks later, on the eve of the June board meeting, Satz emailed all the board members, ‘I’m a member of the board and Harry wants me to attend the meeting.’

‘Your appointment was invalid,’ Chandauka replied.

‘This is very offensive,’ Satz countered.

Harry had introduced Josh Kettler, before he resigned as his chief of staff, into the dispute. Back and forth in Zoom meetings, Kettler had urged Chandauka to accept Satz. Forlornly, Kettler admitted that he had never read the governance rules and retreated, only to be ordered by Harry to resume the fight. The Zoom meetings ended with Kettler’s defeat. At Harry’s request, Dyer entered the fray in a manner which an eyewitness called ‘disrespectful and provocative’.[774]

The crunch battle occurred at the July board meeting on Zoom. The atmosphere, Chandauka reported, was ‘hostile. I didn’t feel safe with Dyer and West.’ Previous agreements were being distorted or ignored. Harry’s conduct was particularly difficult. Sentebale, he insisted, should leave Botswana because President Mokgweetsi Masisi ‘didn’t treat me well’. And after the key fundraising polo match in the Dominican Republic was cancelled, Harry refused to arrange an alternative match. He would only appear, he insisted, if Sentebale was guaranteed a profit above £500,000 – an impossible target.

Those were the curtain-raisers as Harry arrived in Lesotho in October 2024. He and Chandauka had not spoken since the Florida polo match. After a ‘frosty and crotchety’ greeting, Harry announced in a noticeably dismissive manner that any further communication between the two should be channelled through his assistant, Beth Herlihy, and ordered that he was not to be photographed with Chandauka. Over the following six days, Harry never spoke to Chandauka. In Harry’s version, Chandauka refused to speak to him.

Upset by the tension, Chandauka noted Harry’s refusal to be briefed about the charity’s growing financial crisis. The charity had less than £1 million in the bank and donations would not equal the £4.5 million raised in 2022. Established financial backers in Africa and Europe had resisted giving money after Harry’s attacks on the Royal Family. The Sussex brand, Chandauka believed, had become ‘toxic’. The only hope was new American financiers but attracting young American philanthropists was difficult.[775] Rich white men riding horses was no longer the right image to raise money for disadvantaged black communities. ‘We really didn’t know whether we would raise the money,’ Chandauka admitted.[776] And one revelation raised questions about Harry’s true commitment.

Chandauka discovered that a potential American donor to Sentebale had been approached by an Archewell employee. He was asked to donate his money to the Sussexes’ new non-profit organisations rather than Sentebale. Another potential donor was apparently persuaded to contribute to Travalyst rather than Sentebale.

New donors had to be found, and were, by an American consultant, Alix Lebec. Hired by Chandauka for about £20,000 a month to introduce potential donors, Lebec had produced eight potential American contributors to visit Lesotho with Harry. For Harry and Dyer, Chandauka’s strategy of spending large sums on consultants without any guarantee of donations seemed risky, but her self-confidence silenced their questions. In her scenario, much depended on Harry’s performance in Lesotho during the four-day visit.

On the first day, a power blackout across Maseru, the capital, produced mixed reactions. ‘It was really humbling,’ recalled Ki Smith, a gallery owner from New York. ‘And I think that that was a really great way to transition into an incredible trip.’ Other potential donors were less impressed. Harry, one decided, was adrift. He looked helpless. Another noticed that during a visit to a village, no one recognised the Prince. One American agreed to make a substantial donation. Ki Smith warmed to Harry. ‘This is someone that really cares,’ he decided.

The climax of the trip was a dinner in Johannesburg’s Saxon Hotel. Chandauka and Iain Rawlinson, the former banker attached to Global Philanthropic, had pulled every lever to attract about thirty influential South African corporate players and prospective donors, including the chief executives of Google and South African Breweries.[777] The costs were borne by a New York law firm. The following day, another thirty influential South Africans gathered at the hotel to discuss Sentebale’s role in relieving the plight of children in South Africa. Both Chandauka and Rawlinson hailed the event as a success, except that Harry had refused to stay overnight. Instead, he flew to Rwanda by private jet for a board meeting of African Parks.[778] He had left Johannesburg without thanking Chandauka or acknowledging Rawlinson’s efforts. Both concluded that Harry’s attachment to African Parks was motivated by his personal relationships with billionaires, despite the damage to his brand.

By the time Harry returned to Montecito, he was committed to bringing Sentebale under his control. Chandauka, he decided, would be replaced by Brian Satz. Harry knew he could rely on the support of all his hand-picked trustees, including the 82-year-old former Conservative politician Lynda Chalker. Apparently unable to master Zoom technology, Chalker rarely joined board meetings.

The trigger for Harry’s coup was Chandauka’s decision that his old friends Mark Dyer and Damian West should resign as trustees. Both had served nearly eighteen years, double the number of years recommended under the governance rules. Their removal, Chandauka decided, became more urgent after Dyer criticised her fundraising campaign as ‘pointless’ and ‘a failure’. Tellingly, one potential American donor told Chandauka that Harry had called. He had hinted that Chandauka would be removed as chairwoman in the near future.

An explosion erupted at Sentebale’s October board meeting. ‘It was ugly, awful,’ Chandauka recalled. ‘Harry, Dyer and West challenged everything. In front of everyone, they shouted at me, interrupted me and were rude.’ Iain Rawlinson witnessed Chandauka subjected to Dyer’s aggressive questioning and disrespect. Dyer retorted that Chandauka could not answer the existential question: how could the charity survive when its income had plummeted? Chandauka might have had good ideas, said Dyer, but the strategy had failed. The £1 million in the bank when Chandauka arrived had nearly disappeared. After a lifesaving £750,000 donation had been withheld, the charity faced a deficit of £1.2 million, projected to increase within four months to £1.6 million. ‘I feel disrespected and undermined,’ Chandauka snapped back. Harry ignored her complaint. He wanted her fired.

‘They unleashed the Sussex machine on me,’ Chandauka complained.[779] In her opinion, Harry, Dyer and other white privileged men were undermining a black woman. That imbalance of power, thought Chandauka, amounted to bullying. For their part, Harry and Dyer portrayed Chandauka as ‘a bully, a racist and out for revenge’. On 7th November, Chandauka emailed Harry complaining about the ‘appalling treatment’ she had suffered. ‘I was being beaten up,’ she wrote. ‘I won’t tolerate being treated like this.’

Acting as a ‘whistle-blower’, the lawyer started a formal process accusing Harry of bullying her about funding. Her complaint was to an allegedly independent trustee, Tim Boucher. Within hours, Harry emailed Chandauka, ‘You can’t be a whistle-blower.’ The Prince denied that he was a bully and announced that he would personally preside over the investigation of her complaint. ‘You’re trying to destroy all the work we’ve done for twenty years,’ he added. Chandauka replied that the blame should be directed towards Dyer and Harry himself.

Unknown to Chandauka, with Harry’s authority, Dyer had asked Robert Oakley, the charity’s solicitor at Bates Wells, for advice on how to remove Chandauka. Despite the charity’s financial crisis, Bates Wells’ £66,000 invoice showed that Harry’s lawyers Schillings had activated Chandauka’s removal. By serving Harry, Bates Wells seemed unconcerned by a possible conflict of interest with his client, Sentebale.

‘Behind the scenes, something is happening,’ Chandauka told a colleague. ‘Harry’s trying to remove two black women.’ She meant Carmel Gaillard, the temporary chief executive, and her. The Prince’s battle to oust the lawyer was about to take an ugly twist.

CHAPTER 38

American Hustle

Meghan was also combatting allegations of bullying. ‘No one understands me,’ she wailed. So many prejudiced writers raked up her past to present a one-sided story in a piece in the New York Post, ignoring her great achievements.[780] Netflix insiders spoke of feeling ‘exhausted’ after working on Meghan’s lifestyle series. Some predicted that it was her ‘make or break’.

Still confused why her father, former school friends and so many in Britain had betrayed her, Meghan confided in two women friends about her inability to trust people or ‘let them into my life’. Blind to accusations of her own disloyalty and emotional manipulation of her family, friends and employees, she could not understand how so few respected her demand for privacy.

On 2nd October 2024, Meghan had arranged to speak at Girls Inc, a teenage mentorship programme in Santa Barbara, to celebrate the International Day of the Girl. At school, she told her audience, ‘I was one of the most bullied people in the world.’[781] That surprised her father Thomas Markle and also her best school friend, Ninaki Priddy, and her teachers. None had ever previously heard Meghan complain of being bullied. Nor did they recognise her self-portrayal as ‘very lonely’ without any friends and ‘no one to sit with at lunch’. She seemed to have forgotten about her frequent appearances in school plays and membership of many clubs.

Days later, her publicists went into overdrive. To rebut the Duchess Difficult label, Meghan attended a fundraising gala for the Los Angeles Children’s Hospital. Meghan’s appearance had totally changed. Heavy make-up covered her puffy face; her hair was in loose waves rather than primed straight. She wore a red flesh-flashing Carolina Herrera gown with a thigh-high split last seen at a 2021 gala, and stood on the red carpet tightly holding the hand of her friend Kelly McKee Zajfen. Her publicists briefed that the Saturday night was her ‘Revenge Moment’. Just as Diana had worn a sensational black dress at London’s Serpentine Gallery on the night in 1994 that Charles would confess on television that he had had an adulterous relationship with Camilla Parker Bowles, Meghan sought to prove that she would not be cowed by allegations of aggressive behaviour.[782]

That comparison was picked up by the British TV personality Lizzie Cundy, who, by chance, was at the gala. Cundy had first met Meghan in London in 2013 during the actress’s search for fame. Over a drink, Meghan had confessed that she had failed to make a breakthrough in Hollywood and was searching for a British boyfriend.[783] Eleven years later, the previously unsuccessful actress was a global star, but in trouble. Cundy was certain that after standing on the red carpet, Meghan left the venue.[784] Meghan’s publicists confirmed that because of her tight schedule she had immediately returned to Montecito. Yet the gala’s publicist insisted that Meghan had stayed for the dinner and mingled afterwards with the guests. He could not explain why Cundy and others were certain that she was invisible that evening.[785] Either way, the appearance failed to bury more bad news.[786]

* * *

Harry’s trust in the German film director who had been given access to him at the Invictus Games in Vancouver the year before – on the advice of his publicist – had proved misplaced. Ulrike Grunewald’s documentary Harry: The Lost Prince included an interview with Richard Mineards, a Montecito neighbour, who said, ‘I personally don’t think that Meghan is an asset to our community.’ Meghan did not recognise his criticism about her refusal ‘to get involved with the community’. Many staged photographs proved she had visited Montecito’s shops, restaurants and the farmers’ market. ‘Meghan feels hurt by a lot of people – but especially her neighbours,’ said her new spokeswoman. ‘She feels betrayed by them telling people this, rather than offering friendship and support.’[787] To prove her resilience, Meghan arranged to appear alongside Tyler Perry at the Paley Center Honors gala in Beverly Hills. The dial still did not move.

On 5th November, Donald Trump swept to election victory, humiliating the Hollywood celebrities who had endorsed Kamala Harris. In a move that could be seen as trying to bury bad news, Netflix released the full trailer for the polo series that day. The ruse failed. ‘Harry and Meghan’s Projects Can’t Stop Flopping’ was The Cut’s headline. Other media outlets hastily panned the series as ‘tedious’ and a ‘dull indulgence’.

Even the previously sympathetic Tina Brown somersaulted. Meghan, she wrote, had ‘run out of road’.[788] Coming down the track, Meghan knew, was a Vanity Fair article marking five years since the Sandringham summit. Since she was denied control over the content, she refused to co-operate with the magazine’s writer. She feared duplicity by former employees despite the non-disclosure agreements. There was worse to come.

Lurking were lawyers’ letters from the owners of ‘Royal Riviera’, a New York clothing studio trading for years under the name American Riviera Orchard, which was identical to Meghan’s proposed new brand. The New York company’s lawyers had protested to the government’s trademark agency that Meghan’s name breached their own patented trademark. The US Patent Office upheld their complaint. So far, Meghan had prevented outsiders discovering that setback – compounded by her failure to hire a chief executive for the business.[789] As she struggled to find solutions, a fake story about a removal truck spotted outside her house ignited rumours about her marriage.[790]

‘Apparently, we’ve bought or moved house ten, twelve times,’ Harry joked in New York that week. ‘We’ve apparently divorced maybe ten, twelve times as well. It’s hard to keep up.’[791] As a throwaway remark to a select audience, Harry added that he and Meghan had no intention of returning to Britain. That country, he said, was not safe for his wife and children, and their lifestyle in California was so much better. The previous year, Harry had told the High Court, ‘The UK is my home. The UK is central to the heritage of my children.’ Like Meghan, Harry could, when required, produce a masterful performance, as he had proved during that week in New York when he was seemingly co-operating with Sophie Chandauka.

On 4th December, fifty potential donors had been invited to a reception at the Ki Smith Gallery in New York’s Lower East Side as a fundraiser for Sentebale. The gallery was known for staging ‘guerrilla art’ exhibitions. The idea for the exhibition in New York had arisen at the polo match in April. A charity auction of African art held by Sotheby’s at the ground in Wellington had raised $148,060 instead of the expected $550,000.[792] But despite that failure, Ki Smith agreed to stage a fundraising exhibition in New York. Titled ‘Friend’, it featured op art over two floors. Smith agreed to donate any commission to the charity.[793]

Mingling with the guests, Harry knew the charity’s trustees had asked Chandauka to resign. She had refused. Now, all the trustees were on the verge of resignation. Lynda Chalker had already resigned, complaining that Chandauka was ‘almost dictatorial’ – a line which Chandauka said was written by Dyer. Clutching a glass of wine, Harry worked the room to meet guests, all of whom were unaware of the crisis. Nearby, Chandauka was also engaging the potential donors.

After Harry’s brief speech of thanks praising his charity’s ‘spirit of inclusivity and community’, Chandauka chaired a twenty-minute discussion. ‘It’s amazing to work with Prince Harry,’ she told the guests, ‘because he is so authentically connected to the organisation. He has a lot of energy; he has lots of ideas. He’s excited about the innovative ways of doing things. And you can’t ask for more.’[794]

That night, Harry had no interest in resolving the conflict other than by removing Chandauka, which was encouraged by Dyer. No one cautioned Harry with realistic advice about avoiding a crisis. Least of all Meghan, who was preoccupied with her own survival. Just as infuriating was the Palace’s refusal to engage with him.

To prove that the Royal Family was immune to Harry’s subversion, Buckingham Palace was organising its biggest Christmas Day celebration at Sandringham. Over seventy members of the family were invited. Camilla, recovering from pneumonia, would light the brandy on a 22-pound Christmas pudding. Andrew was invited, despite the King having just sharply reduced his allowance and being faced by the latest embarrassment – the exposure of Andrew’s financial relationship with an alleged Chinese spy.

Demonstrating the Royal Family’s resilience, William was sent to Paris for the reopening ceremony of Notre-Dame, restored after the devastating fire in 2019. Diplomats arranged for William to meet President Trump, a fan of the monarchy. ‘He looked really nice,’ Trump said afterwards. ‘I told him that.’[795]

The Sussexes’ retaliation was swift. The following day, their Christmas card featuring the first pictures of their two children was released.[796] To some it appeared that they were using their children to win sympathy, a ruse which annoyed Harry but Meghan was reportedly adamant. Her Netflix series and American Riviera Orchard brand would be launched in three weeks followed by her podcast series of interviews for Lemonada called Confessions of a Female Founder. In her search for good publicity, her children were vital props. Christmas was unusually stressful.

Meghan and Harry had every reason to welcome the new year and a new start. To demonstrate their happiness, Meghan released a video of herself ‘joyfully’ running across Montecito’s empty beach on New Year’s Day and carving ‘2025’ in the sand. By the end of the day, her newly restored Instagram site had attracted 170,000 fans. By comparison, Gwyneth Paltrow had 8.7 million Instagram followers.

For the next twenty-four hours, Meghan held her breath. All the carping and criticism of the previous year would hopefully be buried. Her publicist was working flat out to showcase her as a global lifestyle grandee. Within days, Netflix would stream a glitzy 110-second trailer for With Love, Meghan.

Days of editing, re-editing and sound mixing had produced Meghan the celebrity star who ‘re-imagines the genre of lifestyle programming’. As a Duchess and a family homemaker, she promised to entertain with elegance. As a generous hostess she would ‘add beauty to our lives and, most importantly, help bring people together’. Meghan featured in eight episodes sharing with friends ‘candid conversations and top tips’. Focused on ‘things that are close to her heart’, viewers were promised that Meghan ‘loved surprising people with moments to let them know I was really thinking of them’. Filmed in a beautiful modern kitchen, surrounded by expensive utensils and cookware, ‘she shares some of her favourite tips and tricks for cooking, gardening, crafting and more.’ Cynics might observe that everything was coloured beige, except the Eton mess pudding and a carrot, but that did not undermine Meghan’s eager tease: ‘We’re not in pursuit of perfection. We’re in pursuit of joy.’ All her products, labelled American Riviera Orchard, would be for sale.

Her ‘super joyful’ signature item was a breakfast platter of fruit shaped like a rainbow, because ‘it makes the morning a lot more fun’. Some platters were filled with yogurt ‘clouds’ and some with flower sprinkles. All combined, in her words, ‘for a really sweet start to the weekend’. She added, ‘It’s a delight being able to be a present parent.’ Or, ‘as a woman, a mom and a wife’. Fortunately, no one had yet noticed one serious problem.

Launching the American Riviera Orchard product range – from dog biscuits to wine – would cost millions of dollars. Meghan had failed to find a financial backer willing to risk cash on her brand or hire a chief executive to organise the manufacture and distribution of her products. Finding investors, Meghan acknowledged, depended on improving her profile.

On 2nd January 2025, the Netflix trailer was streamed and racked up big audiences. Over 27,000 comments were posted within the first seventy-two hours. Overwhelmingly, the remarks were negative.

‘Thank you for loving me so much and celebrating with me,’ Meghan posted. Her future depended on never giving the slightest hint of taking any notice of the critics. She then disappeared from view. Five days later, a fire broke out in Pacific Palisades, a wooded residential area in Los Angeles. As the fire spread, Netflix delayed streaming the series until 4th March.[797] The fatal emergency engulfing 38,000 acres of California justified the postponement, but there was another reason. Netflix’s publicists had heard that Vanity Fair’s cover story to be published that week was crushing. Called ‘American Hustle’, the 8,000 words written by Anna Peele resurrected all the previous exposés describing the horror of working for ‘Meghan the Bully’, which began in The Times of London followed by The Cut and The Hollywood Reporter.

Vanity Fair’s informants reflected the Sussexes’ limitations and insecurities. Bereft of originality and ideas, Meghan blamed her staff for disappointments. ‘Meghan would become cold and withholding toward the person she perceived to be responsible,’ wrote Peele. Meghan’s bullying, complained one victim, was ‘really, really, really awful. Very painful’. She continued, ‘And when you’re not in, you are to be thrown to the wolves at any given moment. Really, like a Mean Girl teenager.’

‘She’d throw around phrases like “lack of accountability”, “disappointment” or “we know what you did, and yet we still decided to support you”. But when staff tried to get clarity, asking what exactly they had done wrong, she’d dismiss them with lines like, “I think it’s best we keep it to ourselves and not advertise it in front of the team. We’re here to protect you, not throw you under the bus.”’

Neither of the Sussexes could cope with criticism. One former employee said there was a ‘gnawing at your sense of self’, adding: ‘You don’t tell them “No”. I left because I couldn’t live with myself any more.’ Some members of the Archetypes team took extended breaks. One required therapy.

In the midst of the arguments with staff in their home, Harry failed to spot that Meghan’s anger was expressed without raising her voice. ‘Meghan has a habit of using a whisper shout,’ explained an eyewitness of her controlled rage. ‘So, when Harry is in the room, he just hears her talking normally and doesn’t understand why people describe her as aggressive.’ In reply to the complaints, Harry said, ‘Meghan is misunderstood.’

Just as humiliating for the couple were the anonymous comments from their neighbours calling them ‘the most entitled, disingenuous people on the planet’ for monetising their search for privacy. Asked for a comment, Meghan’s spokeswoman admitted that the couple found the article ‘distressing’.[798] Not least because the brickbats were quoted across the world. ‘These claims,’ continued their spokeswoman, ‘rooted in anonymous, unverifiable sources, form part of a broader and deeply troubling agenda that seeks to dehumanise a woman who has consistently stood up for fairness, dignity and truth.’ The spokeswoman added, ‘The Duchess has faced years of unfounded attacks masked as journalism in a never-ending smear campaign, beginning only once she was affiliated with the institution. Meghan remains undeterred by the noise and firmly focused on her family and work.’[799]

The most far-fetched suggestion in the profile was Meghan’s proposal to a publisher to publish a book if she divorced. That was easily rebutted, but not the allegations of her unpopularity in Montecito. Although Sharon Stone had attested that ‘Harry and Meghan waved to people in the street,’ Meghan was not seen waving in Montecito or anywhere over the following two weeks. The focus had switched to Harry.

Harry’s ‘life’s work’ was, he believed, about to be fulfilled. Six years earlier, he had pledged to hold the British press to account. As the self-appointed champion of the ‘voiceless’, he spoke about ‘slaying the dragon’, Rupert Murdoch. His principal target for destroying the mogul’s empire was Murdoch’s senior executive in Britain, Rebekah Brooks. Harry blamed her for unleashing private investigators to probe unlawfully into his life. He also accused her of permitting the destruction of millions of incriminating files stored in the newspapers’ computers. Brooks – and Murdoch’s corporation – vigorously denied Harry’s accusations.

Most believed Harry’s repeated pledge that he would not settle his claim before the trial, despite the damage to his family relationships. He was, he said, ‘the last person’ who could achieve accountability, to obtain closure for those who did not have the deep pockets to have their day in court. He ‘relished’ his day in court.

The ten-week trial was due to start on Monday 20th January 2025. That morning, the courtroom was packed in anticipation of a spectacular drama. Over the previous months, David Sherborne had prepared himself to destroy Brooks and other News Corp employees in cross-examination. He would cast them as liars involved in a ‘criminal enterprise’. Yet the star witness was still in Los Angeles. At the last minute, both sides were scrabbling to settle the case. News Corp wanted to protect its executives from public humiliation in cross-examination, while Harry’s insurers feared that even if he won the case, they would be liable to pay millions of pounds of costs. Taking millions of pounds on offer from News Corp to settle was too good to reject, and with pressure, the amount could be enormous.

As the deadline to settle the case was extended, on 22nd January Harry agreed to compromise. News Corp would admit ‘unlawful activity’ at the defunct News of the World but not by any Sun journalists under Brooks’s editorship.There was no admission of phone hacking, surveillance or misuse of private information by the Sun. Any ‘incidents’ of unlawful activities were done by private investigators on their own initiative. News Corp’s only admission was ‘serious intrusion’ of Harry’s privacy – the details of which remained unexplained. News Corp did not admit destroying any records. They only ‘acknowledged and apologised for the distress caused to the Duke, and the damage inflicted on relationships, friendships and family’.[800] In return for backing down, News Corp paid Harry over £10 million. Much of that money would be grabbed by his insurers and lawyers.

Outside the court, Sherborne puffed up the settlement as a triumph against the Sun’s ‘criminal enterprise’. Hours later, News Corp’s lawyers condemned the barrister for his ‘hugely misleading . . . misquotations . . . and spin’.[801] He had been unable to prove that News Corp had authorised any illegal activity against Harry or that they had deliberately destroyed evidence. Other newspapers mocked Harry for surrendering. The self-styled dragon slayer had ended his campaign with ‘a humiliating climbdown’, reported the Daily Telegraph. ‘His lofty aims and ideals appear rather hollow.’[802]

Meghan was relieved. While she supported Harry 100 per cent, Meghan wanted Harry ‘to live in a world where he is not burdened by his past’.[803] But most would have judged that she just wanted the focus wholly on herself.

At the end of January, Netflix had a preview launch in Los Angeles for the network’s new season, including Meghan’s imminent series. To remind the public about her series, she re-emerged as a ‘surprise’ guest at actress Kerry Washington’s forty-eighth birthday party.[804] The videos and smiling photos posted the following day of Meghan at the small party suggested that she had brushed aside the critics. As usual she looked great. But her trolls were remorseless. Some claimed she had gate-crashed the party and was kicked out.

The carping was an inauspicious curtain-raiser to Netflix’s launch of the 2025 season four days later in the Egyptian Theatre. Meghan had every reason to be fearful. Not only did her series With Love, Meghan fail to feature in Netflix’s glossy brochure, but Bela Bajaria did not even mention Meghan in her speech. Instead, the comedian John Mulaney offered a jaw-dropping surprise. After uttering a mocking aside about the dismal ratings registered for Harry’s polo series – ranked by Netflix at number 3,436 – Mulaney mentioned his own talk show series commissioned by Netflix. ‘This is a fun experiment,’ Mulaney said about his series. ‘Not since Harry and Meghan has Netflix given more money to someone without a specific plan.’ The audience roared.

Panic gripped the Sussexes’ home. The media grasped the derision heaped by Netflix’s former stand-up comedian star Katherine Ryan. She chided Meghan’s series as ‘highly inauthentic’, ‘fake’ and ‘phony’.[805]

Meghan’s agent called Bajaria. Early the following day, Netflix’s chief content executive responded with an exaggerated post about how ‘excited’ she was with all the Sussexes’ projects. Meghan’s cookery show, Bajaria exclaimed, has ‘great takeaways’, especially her unusual recipe for spaghetti cooked in a frying pan: ‘I was like, “Oh My God, I really want to do that pasta.”’[806]

Few were fooled. Meghan’s publicists suggested that the couple head down to Los Angeles to be seen comforting the victims of the widespread and devastating wildfires that had gripped the region. An Archewell cameraman was waiting for their arrival at a soup kitchen in Pasadena set up to help a group of homeless people. After recording a video of her listening and hugging victims, the scene was posted that day by the publicists to her now 1.6 million Instagram followers.[807] By nightfall, one of her publicists spotted another opportunity. A homeless fifteen-year-old girl from Altadena had mentioned her loss in the fire of a Billie Eilish T-shirt. After contacting her Montecito neighbours singer Adam Levine and his wife, Victoria’s Secret model Behati Prinsloo, Meghan had sent the girl not only an Eilish T-shirt but also a lunchbox and other signed merchandise. ‘I just wanted to share with you guys,’ Meghan gushed in a post on her Instagram site about her success.[808]

Instead of getting credit for her efforts, Meghan was mocked as an attention-seeking pseudo-royal. Hollywood film-maker Justine Bateman carped online: ‘Meghan Markle and Harry are no better than ambulance chasers. What a repulsive “photo op” they achieved. They are “touring the damage”? Are they politicians now? They don’t live here; they are tourists. Disaster Tourists.’ Thousands shared Bateman’s post, followed by her next message awarding the couple a gold medal in their ‘very aggressive Victims Olympics campaign’.[809] It was all a far cry from the New York Times’ praise of Meghan two years earlier as ‘accessible . . . just a working mom’.[810] Every attempt to appear genuine rebounded on her.

Even President Trump could not resist taunting the Duchess. On8th February, he was asked by the New York Post whether he would deport Harry if he had inaccurately completed his visa application. ‘I don’t want to do that,’ replied the president. ‘I’ll leave him alone. He’s got enough problems with his wife. She’s terrible.’[811]

Silently, Harry could thank Trump for ignoring the Heritage Foundation’s campaign. Days later, his visa application was finally released by the court. Every critical section over the eighty-two pages was covered by black ink to protect him from ‘harm and harassment’.

That day, Harry opened the Invictus Games in Vancouver. ‘Invictus’ means unconquered.

CHAPTER 39

Vancouver

Meghan needed a global stage for genuine admiration and cheering fans. To her good fortune, Harry agreed that she could also star at the Invictus Games. Just before flying up to Vancouver in a private jet financed by Invictus, she alerted her Instagram followers.

‘How should we address them?’ the Canadian organisers asked.

‘Meghan insists on “Ma’am” and Harry should be called “Sir”,’ replied Nick Booth, the chief executive of the Games. Booth had been parachuted into the post after the dismissal of two Canadian executives.[812] Both had resented the pushy Sussexes, not least their exorbitant expenses for security, accommodation and a private jet. Unlike Harry’s own financial contributions to Sentebale, his lifestyle expenses for Invictus were financed by government and corporate funding of the Games.

Booth, a leader of True Patriot Love Foundation in Canada, was classed as a sycophant by the ousted executives. As Harry’s doorkeeper, Booth used the Prince, alias an ‘attractive asset’, as a fundraiser to secure more money – the Games had been $30 million underfunded – to arrange TV coverage and tilt the media’s focus firmly towards the glamour of Harry and Meghan.

In the opinion of the ousted Canadian executives, Meghan was a distraction from the injured veterans. ‘She’s bling, not rehabilitation,’ protested one of the men. ‘Harry can’t decide whether Invictus should be styled on the Olympics or a more intimate warrior games embracing the military family.’ Caught halfway, they warned, the competition would once again be ignored by the media after the star-studded opening pop concert in Vancouver’s Convention Centre. ‘We need bigger ambitions to bring in the audience,’ said the Canadian executives.

Their criticism was echoed by Dominic Reid, the long-time head of the Invictus Foundation. Past coverage, admitted Reid, had been ‘disappointing’. He acknowledged that the media totally ignored the competitive aspect of the event. Reid blamed the Invictus leaders for allowing the Games to become the Harry and Meghan show. The media just followed their lead. And yet Nick Booth, with Harry’s encouragement, did not seem concerned. To get global attention, Booth was focused on the opening ceremony.

On 8th February 2025, Katy Perry performed for 30,000 ecstatic fans in the Convention Centre. Before her appearance, about five hundred competitors from twenty-three countries had paraded across the venue, preceded and followed by eighty Canadian navy bandsmen and ninety Highland pipers. Stirring military music endorsed the Canadian government’s promise to honour the Prince and the veterans.

Few of the cheering audience noticed that 97 per cent of the competitors were walking. Only a handful of the sportsmen were pushed in wheelchairs. Hardly any were limbless. The fans had come to see Katy Perry. For them, the Games was a music spectacular, not a bond between the nation and its armed forces.

Watching the parade from midway up the tier were Harry and Meghan. They had arrived at the stadium by car from their hotel’s penthouse suite across the street and were then transferred to an electric golf cart. Filmed by an Archewell cameraman, they were driven through an underground passage lined with hundreds of veterans and volunteers cheering ‘Harry, Harry!’ The video of the orchestrated welcome was posted on Meghan’s Instagram feed. Unexpectedly, more videos about the Sussexes in Vancouver were filtered on to her curated Instagram account. In one video, Meghan thanked the Indigenous Peoples for the hospitality on their sacred land and in another, the Sussexes met a group of children.[813] As usual, Meghan’s introduction of Harry focused on her giving their children breakfast.[814] Other videos revealed her outfits – Hermes, Ralph Lauren, Altuzarra, etc. Those were the curtain-raisers to the Sussexes’ sudden appearance opposite the media box in the stadium. The Meghan Games had been launched.

Sitting in full view of the audience, the Sussexes were conscious that every move was carefully scrutinised by the bank of manned long-distance camera lenses. As Harry attentively watched the parade, sitting upright and even leaning away from his wife, Meghan shifted to tilt her head on to his shoulder. Then she held his hand. Beyond her permanent smile her eyes betrayed a fear of staleness. She needed to inject drama for the cameras. She kissed her Prince. One kiss on his face and then, as Harry rose to make his speech, she also stood up and, with her hands cupped around his face, plonked a kiss on his lips. In what one observer called her ‘limpet cling’, she struck a besotted pose as ‘a gesture of ownership that speaks of enduring bonding’.[815]

The seventh Invictus Games was opening just as Canada, on the eve of a general election, had been plunged into a trade war with America. Canadians were outraged by President Trump’s bid to seize their country as the fifty-first state. After reading Trump’s denunciation of Meghan as ‘terrible’, Harry could no doubt resist retaliating. Hailing the competitors’ ‘courage, values and humanity’, he saluted the Invictus ‘spirit of unity’ in a ‘moment of difficulty and division when there is no shortage of crises, no absence of uncertainty, no lack of weak moral character in the world’. Canadians were doubly grateful for the support of a member of the Royal Family. The Prince loved the rapturous applause. Spontaneous and genuine, Harry assumed he had recovered the spotlight. The following day, the true nature of the Games was revealed. Most of Canada’s media ignored the event and Harry’s speech. The focus was on Meghan. She had stolen Harry’s moment.

At the opening basketball match between Nigeria and the United States at the Vancouver Convention Centre – a series of giant, vacant hangars – the mood was sullen. Merely forty-three ticket-buying spectators sat morosely together in a hall fitted with seats for over 2,000 people. On the other side of the court, about a hundred people brought in by the organisers were corralled to surround the Sussexes when they eventually arrived. The edited TV pictures would suggest that the hall was full. Among the guests was the Nigerian Air Vice-Marshal Abidemi Timothy Marquis. In return for arranging the Sussexes’ successful visit to Nigeria, Marquis expected to be warmly welcomed by the couple and for Harry to nominate his nation as the venue for the 2029 Games. Marquis was downhearted. Without explanation, Nigeria’s best basketball players and their coach had been denied entry visas by the Canadian government.

In an uncanny silence, the eight-man Nigerian scratch squad wheeled themselves on to the court. They faced twenty-two professionally trained Americans. While two men in the Nigerian team had lost a leg, none of the Americans were limbless. All were apparently suffering PTSD – post-traumatic stress disorder – but played in wheelchairs. Throughout the game, there was barely a murmur from the spectators. Halfway through the match, the Sussexes slipped into their seats.

Harry and Meghan’s presence at the game was the day’s media photo opportunity. Nine zoom lenses focused on the Sussexes’ tightly controlled narrative. The couple clapped silently. Meghan stared lovingly at Harry and the Prince watched the slow match intently. Nearby, a vetted TV station recorded them on a tight lens. Ten minutes after their arrival, the whistle blew. The Americans had trounced the Nigerians 24–0. There were no cheers. The American team wheeled themselves off the court into a secluded area beyond anyone’s view – and effortlessly they all got up. Unseen, all the Americans walked away. None of them appeared to be physically injured.

After the basketball players disappeared, the Sussexes posed for selfies with the American competitors’ families. Patiently waiting to greet the couple, Marquis finally saw his opportunity and approached Meghan. Her embrace was a brief brush pass before moving quickly away. Harry swung a handshake and rushed on to speak at length to an American government official. Nigeria’s ambition to host the 2029 Games was evidently forgotten. Harry had already decided that it would be staged in America. Deflated, Marquis left the hall. Ten minutes later, Meghan and Harry returned to their penthouse suite. Her staff were feeding Instagram with shots of Meghan walking hand in hand with Harry, hugging veterans’ wives and looking soulfully at a wheelchair-bound Nigerian competitor. Instantly, all her labelled clothes were linked to websites.

Across the street from the Sussexes’ hotel, the competitors in the empty hangars knew that the world was not interested in them. Subject to the Sussexes’ PR machine, the media chose not to reveal the truth – that Invictus’s 2,000 yellow-shirted volunteers around the deserted Convention Centre outnumbered paying spectators by about twenty to one. Just one middle-aged Italian veteran in a wheelchair reappeared constantly, pushing himself around the vast canteen. He had lost his leg in a truck accident in the Balkans. He was surrounded by 1,200 members of the competitors’ families, all enjoying free food twice daily. Invictus’s annual report would ignore the reality.[816]

The following day, Invictus’s Winter Games opened in Whistler. In minus 17 degrees, about five hundred tourists were crammed into the ski resort’s square for the opening speeches. After the indigenous Canadians and state politicians had spoken, Harry and Meghan appeared. The royal celebrities thrilled the crowd. Both made brief, unscripted comments about their ‘excitement’ to be in the mountains and disappeared, just as two Canadian Air Force bombers thundered over the skiers.

‘Bring on Invictus Birmingham 2027!’ Harry shouted days later at the Games’ closing ceremony alongside Justin Trudeau. The outgoing Canadian prime minister had flown in from Ottawa specially. Harry could not hold back his tears as Trudeau concluded, ‘Service to your country is the noblest of all. Your strength and resilience is inspiring.’ Whether the British government would similarly honour the veterans in Birmingham was Harry’s challenge.

Few journalists had stayed in Vancouver to see Trudeau. Only hours after Meghan’s appearance in Whistler, the media had lost all interest in the Games. Meghan had unexpectedly flown back to Santa Barbara in a private jet. A new crisis had burst.[817]

CHAPTER 40

Meghan, As Ever

Eleven months after trailing American Riviera Orchard on Netflix by gifting jam to fifty friends, Meghan was told to abandon the label. A mere two weeks before the Netflix series started, even Meghan understood the damage. She had ignored the warning about the failed application for registering the patent. On her lawyers’ advice, American Riviera Orchard was renamed as ‘As Ever’. Meghan described her experience as ‘a learning curve’.[818]

The application for the ‘As Ever’ trademark had been made in October 2022 but was rejected because a Chinese clothes company had registered the same name. The revised application was approved in 2024. With typical indecisiveness, Meghan had left it to the last moment before dashing from Whistler back to Montecito, but she needed to explain the change to her brand name. Without a budget and without a director, she recruited a member of her staff to shoot a video in her garden to be posted on Instagram and X to tell the world.

Looking thin and exhausted in a jerky, badly lit video, Meghan spoke breathlessly to camera: ‘Last year, I thought, “You know what, American Riviera, that sounds like such a great name. It’s my neighbourhood, it’s a nickname for Santa Barbara.” But it limited me to things that were just manufactured and grown in this area.’[819] Nervy laughter punctuated the actress’s explanation for dismissing American Riviera Orchard as a ‘word salad’ defying ‘artistic’ nuance. In contrast, she intoned, ‘As Ever’ was her inspiration, one unmotivated by any urgency.[820] To win public sympathy, her voice was laid over pictures of herself walking with Lilibet, shot from behind.[821] Once again, Lilibet featured rather than Archie.

Unable to complete the video in one shoot, the result was a sharply edited selection of takes.[822] Later she called a friend for reassurance.[823] Was she sinking or swimming, many asked? The answer was struggling. Four months later, her post had been viewed 26 million times.[824] Not for the majority out of admiration but to witness an extraordinary spectacle.

‘I couldn’t share with you in the past few years [my] passion for food and home,’ she asserted, referring to her former life in the Royal Family. Her series, With Love, Meghan, she said, was her ‘new chapter’ and ‘part of that creativity that I’ve missed so much’.[825] As usual she offered a dose of borrowed philosophy, on this occasion from the Japanese concept of kintsugi: ‘If you break something that is precious and valuable, it’s not broken. That fracture makes it more beautiful. The break makes it more beautiful.’ If any relationship was troubled, she continued, ‘You’re not broken. It can be fixed, it can be sealed and healed at the same time.’ Her words were challenging.

As Ever’s motif was two palm trees with two hummingbirds. When describing the design, Meghan cited two palm trees in her Montecito garden and how, soon after they bought the house, a hummingbird had flown into a room. Her genius was to merge the two as symbols of ‘resilience and joy’. The Spanish town of Porreres was unconvinced. Her logo was identical to the town’s coat of arms adopted in 1370. Since her Tig lifestyle blog days, Meghan had been famous for surfing the internet for ideas.

Soon after, on 17th February, Meghan posted a mood board artfully designed with photos and quotations of home-concocted wisdom. ‘I love you with all my butt . . . I would say heart but my butt is bigger.’[826] Some mocked her, but there was a fascination about her destiny.[827] Every potential pitfall and any sniff of failure excited interest. Her trajectory was uncertain. Up or down? Few could imagine how Meghan would realise her ambition to be a billionaire. If she failed, her uncharitable downfall would be the stuff of a Hollywood drama series.

She knew that her promise to sell the merchandise featured in her show was careless. None of the products were available in any quantity. Even the jam’s existence was shrouded in mystery.[828] The Instagram video of As Ever raspberry jam jars at the end of a busy production line looked real, but the brief clip showed fewer than thirty jars. ‘As Ever is more than a brand – it’s a love language,’ promised the website. To promote her jam, Meghan posted on Instagram an image of Lilibet’s hand nearing a bubbling pot in her own kitchen that supposedly contained her homemade spread. ‘Beautiful,’ says her daughter, although As Ever jam was apparently manufactured 2,000 miles away in Illinois.[829]

Meghan pleaded with Netflix executives to bail her out. Josh Simon, Netflix’s vice president of consumer products, agreed to help but failed to make a statement himself.[830] Speaking on Netflix’s behalf, Meghan explained that Simon ‘came on, not only to be a partner in my show but also in my business. And not just jams. There are so many products I want to share with you.’[831] The details of their agreement were ambiguous. ‘I can’t speak to the specifics of the terms of the deal,’ Meghan said. ‘We are very, very much in harmony on how we see the growth of this, and the trajectory over the next five to seven years.’ How the project would end – either in a buy-out or a public flotation – she was unsure. She limited herself to further ambiguity: ‘I felt that the partnership was the right move for the global expansion we want.’

To silence the doubters, Meghan added that Netflix was not just a financial backer but would also manufacture and package her products. ‘We are on calls daily, working through product development, SKUs and inventory. We have a field trip tomorrow to look at different manufacturers and suppliers as we expand the brand.’[832] In Meghan’s version, Netflix appeared to be committed to mass marketing all As Ever products.

The cracks appeared soon after. Meghan’s claim that her products would be sold through Netflix’s stores in Texas and Philadelphia was denied by Netflix.[833] Netflix also refused to confirm the corporation would be manufacturing As Ever’s products.[834] Distribution had been contracted out to Snow Commerce in Cincinnati, Ohio. The Latvian company had attracted criticism for past failures around order fulfilment and poor customer service.[835] Anonymous Netflix employees cursed their association with Meghan.[836]

Meghan sought to rebut criticism of being ‘tone-deaf’, ‘play-acting’ and lacking a clear, core message. She put her faith in her latest recruit, Meredith Maines, a publicist previously employed by Google and American Idol. Like Meghan, Maines was also attached to rescue dogs.

‘The constant scrutiny of Meghan,’ Maines announced, was ‘motivated by clickbait and systems that make sport out of attacking women’. Too many damaging narratives, she felt, had been left ‘unchecked’, not least by Buckingham Palace’s failure to close down ‘false stories before they spiralled into character assassination’.[837] She would seek out media allies willing to understand Meghan’s ‘authenticity’ as a business founder and ‘mom’. Maines’s hunt for allies to recreate Meghan’s brand led to the usual sympathisers.

Maines started with Cory Shields, a former Amazon publicity executive writing for US Weekly magazine. Shields blessed Meghan with ‘a clear vision who understands how to build a brand. She operates with the same level of strategy, discipline and market awareness that defines the most successful entrepreneurs in any industry.’[838]

For Fortune magazine, Meghan posed as a global entrepreneur, anticipating a mega-sale or stock market flotation of As Ever within seven years.[839] ‘From our standpoint, certainly for me, even in the expansion of the brand, things should still feel accessible,’ Meghan told Fortune, adding with gravitas that, ‘At the moment all of our products are currently made in the US, so we don’t anticipate tariffs affecting us directly.’[840]

‘The success of brands like these,’ commented the magazine favourably, ‘has usually started with a multimedia approach, and that’s very much the path Meghan has taken here.’

To add more firepower for the Sussexes, Maines recruited Shahed Fakhari Larson of UNLMTD Partners, an expert in crisis management and communication.

On 4th March, the day before the With Love series streamed, Meredith Maines arranged for People magazine to publish a positive profile. Billed as Meghan’s ‘most intimate interview in years’, the champion of female empowerment spoke as ‘Meghan, the Duchess of Sussex’.[841] Her unique selling point showcased the talent of ‘a woman, a mom and a wife’. Cooking, crafting and gardening with friends, she told People, was a natural extension of her pre-royal life: ‘I see myself as an entrepreneur and female founder.’ Even at the moment of seeking acclaim as an icon of the American Dream, Meghan was confused about her identity. Was she the Duchess of Sussex, Meghan Markle, Meghan Sussex or, as she later signed in a message to a Ukrainian politician, Her Royal Highness.[842] Could she simultaneously be a member of the Royal Family and a swinging, anti-royalist Californian girl?

Posing for People magazine as a champion of ‘home cooking’, she seemed unaware that her ‘super easy-going’ celebrity lifestyle – couture clothes, private jets, expensive restaurants, children’s carers and other staff – in an idyllic house worth by then over $25 million was an unusual sales pitch for a working mom’s daily routine. Sprinkling foraged petals on her children’s breakfast cereals before school drop-offs and playdates, and frequently enjoying lunches with local friends in restaurants before ending the day hosting parties, was summarised in the ‘working moms’ core message: ‘I love the heritage feeling of it.’

Concerned about how she was perceived, she described her friendship with the local ‘working women with normal jobs’ and ‘stay-at-home moms’ she had met at children’s birthday parties and the local fitness class – ‘I just walk in and say, like, “Hi.”’[843] But there were irritations. She complained that women had stared at her when she entered a Montecito yoga class.

Some asked whether Meghan was serious or joking, but self-mockery to win endearment was beyond her. Her super-controlled narrative crushed any natural warmth. Fearful of critics, she threw up barriers for self-protection. An impediment was her word salad. To deflect any suggestion that her ideas were shallow, everything she said was spoken with deep affirmation. ‘I’ve always loved taking something pretty ordinary and elevating it,’ she told People in a room filled with flowers. ‘I think about flowers like an outfit,’ she continued solemnly. ‘What story are you going to tell?’ she asked rhetorically, without an obvious answer.

Within hours of streaming, the series’ highlights showed Meghan dropping flower sprinkles on food, cutting raw vegetables and transferring common pretzels out of their supermarket wrapping into her own gift bags adorned with calligraphed labels.[844] Among her few unoriginal tips was to offer guests ice cubes containing frozen flowers. That sparked the question: who were Meghan’s ‘Tips for Enjoyment’ aimed at? Did her audience need to be told that fresh mint tea was best made using fresh mint? Or be told twice that the teabag should be ‘steeped in hot water and shared with loved ones at midday or by a fire’? The profound insight into Harry’s ‘joyful’ life with Meghan was her list of fillers for Archie’s party bags: seeds, sugar snap peas and sweet basil.[845]

Among the unintended highlights in her Netflix series was the moment she told actress Mindy Kaling that she used to eat Taco Bell and pizza with hot sauce. ‘I don’t think anyone in the world knows that Meghan Markle has eaten Jack in the Box and loves it,’ Kaling helpfully replied. Rather than laugh, Meghan corrected her ‘guest’: ‘It’s so funny too that you keep saying “Meghan Markle”. You know I’m “Sussex” now?’ Then followed a mouthful about the ‘meaningful’ importance of changing her surname because ‘it’s part of our love story’. Her family with Harry, she said, had never shared a surname. In reality, their shared surname was Mountbatten-Windsor. And reporting from Nigeria and Colombia, Harper’s Bazaar and Time magazine had called her Meghan Markle, the same name she had used at the Project Healthy Minds conference in New York.[846]

‘Who Is the “Real” Meghan?’ asked Rolling Stone in its review of the series. ‘It’s so difficult to work out who she really is.’[847]

‘Meghan Markle’s As Ever is selling an identity crisis,’ Newsweek columnist Margaret Hartmann concluded. She’s a ‘fairytale princess’ who is either a British duchess or a Californian mom.[848]

The writer Nadira Goffe, previously an admirer of Meghan as a victim of the racist Brits, was now dismissive of Meghan flaunting her wealth. Goffe no longer wanted to be identified as a Meghan supporter.[849]

‘Pointless’ was the Guardian’s judgement about the series, and that was among the least nasty comments. Scoring 11 per cent on review site Rotten Tomatoes, it was referred to in the comments as ‘a gormless lifestyle filler’, ‘a waste of time’, ‘so boring I wanted to go into a coma’, and ‘superficial and shallow’. Meghan was criticised for focusing on appearance rather than taste.[850] As for the flower sprinkles, ‘the dusting can’t hide the blandness of the cookie’.[851]

In tens of thousands of posts on YouTube, critics noticed that she held her $240 knives incorrectly, her long hair would fall into the food and her couture clothes were inappropriate for cooking: ‘I just love the authenticity of a bunch of rich women, in super-expensive jewellery and full glam, supporting their diamond and Cartier-wearing friend in designer clothes, making frittata and sponge cake in a house that’s not even hers.’[852]

Worse, Meghan was accused of being fake. Her recipes could be traced back to celebrity cooks and other TV shows. Viewers spotted recipes that had been previously published on food blogs, particularly on Pamela Anderson’s blog.[853] Some blamed ‘misogynoir’ [hatred of black women] or racism for the criticism. But that was trounced by the opinion of Carla Hall, a well-known black chef. Previously a friend of the couple, on the day Archie was born, 6th May 2019, Hall had ignited a scandal when she asked Harry and Meghan whether they would raise their child as black? Her question provoked a torrent of criticism, accusing Hall of racism.[854] Six years later, Hall’s sympathy for Meghan had disappeared. As the author of Cooking with Love, Hall accused Meghan’s series With Love, Meghan of plagiarism. There were ‘questions about her integrity’, Hall wrote, because Meghan had ‘leveraged others’ achievements into personal gain’. Not least, alleged Hall, Meghan had used ideas from her own book Soul Food, published in 2018. Hall had encouraged readers to ‘cook with love, live with joy’ – an uncanny resemblance to Meghan’s own pitch.[855] Hall was equally irritated about finding echoes of her ‘Sweet Heritage’ brand, offering recipes to feed ‘self-discovery – exploring who you are, manifesting your best life’, in Meghan’s Netflix series.[856]

The lifestyle pitched by Meghan seemed designed to generate envy. Meghan’s venture, a New York Post columnist wrote, was ‘costly vanity’. Meghan McCain, the daughter of the late Republican politician John McCain, picked on Meghan for being ‘utterly tone-deaf’ during a cost of living crisis. ‘Do something to help people instead of your ego,’ McCain advised Meghan. ‘This is why the world doesn’t like you.’[857] Wisely, Meghan had disabled the comments on her new Instagram page.

To counter the bad reviews, it seems probable Meghan’s PR team bombarded the web with praise. ‘You’ve made my day,’ wrote one ‘admirer’. ‘Such great news,’ wrote another.[858] The puffery failed to sink the criticism. ‘With Love, Meghan is a Montecito Ego Trip Not Worth Taking’ was Variety’s headline. The series, the magazine continued, ‘is made with a great deal of love, in the sense that the greatest love of all is the one that a person has for herself.’ New York Magazine was more damning: ‘With Love, Meghan is an utterly deranged bizarre world voyage into the centre of nothing, a fantastical monument to the captivating power of watching one woman decorate a cake with her make-up artist while communicating solely through throw-pillow adages about joy and hospitality.’ Time magazine concluded about the Sussexes, ‘The more they say about themselves, the less real they seem.’ Recalling Meghan’s distress in 2019 about the ‘almost unsurvivable’ negative media after her ‘faux pas with avocados’, Newsweek commented that the episode was trivial compared to the tsunami of ridicule dumped in 2025 on Montecito.[859]

Even the New York columnist Robert Couri Hay turned against the Sussexes: ‘They took a dramatic turn to the dark side. There’s a money grab. She seems more transactional now. In the long term, she couldn’t handle it. They’ve failed in America.’[860]

With her ‘As Ever’ products launching alongside the series on 2nd April, there had been intense scrutiny of the eight products on sale: wildflower honey with honeycomb priced at $28 (£21.60), flower sprinkles at $15 (£11.60), a jar of raspberry jam at $14 (£10.80), shortbread and crepe mixes at $14 and herbal tea mixes for $12 (£9.30 each). A spokeswoman for As Ever said that ‘tens of thousands’ of items were available for sale.

Within the first forty-five minutes, all the products had been sold out. Meghan swooned that it confirmed ‘that customers – people – believed in me’.[861] She praised the extraordinary spectacle of the launch as ‘a big milestone’. On Instagram, she wrote: ‘Our shelves may be empty, but my heart is full! We sold out in less than one hour and I can’t thank you enough . . . for celebrating, purchasing, sharing, and believing.’[862] In another post she was jubilant: ‘It’s just the start @aseverofficial 🎉 Here we go!’[863] Others called it an unprecedentedly botched launch. Sympathisers would say that Meghan’s ‘business model’ was thoughtful. Others would say Meghan was out of her depth and that she had fallen flat.

Meredith Maines hit back. She encouraged media outlets to speculate why Meghan’s series had sparked such polarising extremes of anger and sympathy.[864] Maines aired the familiar theory that Meghan was the victim of racism. To scotch the critics, Maines arranged an interview with the New York Times. Setting the scene of Meghan as a self-styled ‘entrepreneur and founder’, journalist Julia Moskin was allowed into her Montecito house to rebut one serious criticism: Meghan was no longer a feminist but just an ‘unrelatable’ old-fashioned woman ‘riding the tradwife wave’ who told People magazine that being ‘a mom and a wife . . . is a wonderful feeling’.[865] To provide support, her mother Doria Ragland was present. Under Maines’s gaze, Meghan’s narrative to the New York Times promoted several inaccuracies, including that her mother was her sole responsible parent during her childhood. Also omitted was how Meghan had been plagued by doubts and fears and suffering sleepless nights before the launch of the series.

Maines had not interrupted when the Times reporter assumed that Meghan intended to produce and sell more jam. By then, because the reviews for her raspberry jam were especially unforgiving,[866] Meghan had decided to ‘pause’ production.[867] In truth she considered abandoning jam altogether, but then changed her mind. Thankfully, Netflix did not report that the audience over the first days was insignificant. In America, With Love, Meghan (WLM) barely registered in the top 100. Worldwide, Meghan’s series ranked 383rd with 5.3 million viewers. In contrast, the drama Adolescence had 145 million viewers. Only in Britain and Hungary did WLM reach the top ten – for one day before disappearing from the lists. In comparison, the original Netflix Harry & Meghan series was viewed in 29 million households in its first four days, hitting the number one slot. Although a second series of WLM had already been filmed for streaming later in the year, insiders at Netflix assumed that the Sussexes were on ‘borrowed time’ until their five-year agreement ended.

Pushing on, Maines arranged another interview with Fortune magazine. The business bible could have been expected to probe Meghan’s operation: to identify the products’ manufacturer, the distributor and, most important, As Ever’s finances. Instead, it offered a platform for Meghan to applaud her own success: ‘I wanted to create products that look more prestige but are more accessible and affordable. I think during any time of recession, people still want to find creature comforts, items that can bring them joy.’[868]

By then, the fact Meghan’s products had sold out merely exposed Meghan’s failure to find a financial backer. Launching a brand, and manufacturing and distributing sufficient products, would cost at least $7 million. No one had been identified as employed by Meghan to find the bank or venture capitalist to mastermind the launch. Unwilling to risk her own money to test the water, Meghan had produced a cottage business and hoped that publicity would propel her ambition. To big herself up, she even mentioned building As Ever hotels and restaurants.[869]

Fortune magazine did not probe either her lack of expertise or cash. Instead, her questionable gushes were quoted verbatim: ‘Just having a global powerhouse that believed in me,’ she said about Netflix, ‘and the site selling out in the first 45 minutes of the launch, everything, every single piece that we had been working on, that told me that customers, people believed in me in this vision. That’s all you really want as a founder. That becomes your proof point that those late nights and the midnight musings are worth it.’[870]

To prove that she was a born businesswoman, she described how as an eleven-year-old she made and sold cookies, and ‘I’d buy the remnants of fabric from the fabric store and elastics, and use my little home sewing machine to make scrunchies and sell them.’[871] Interestingly, Thomas Markle, with whom she was living at the time, denied that happened.[872]

Fortune did not describe the reality that As Ever was simply a branding operation. Meghan had paid to have the As Ever label stuck on to products made by The Republic of Tea, who were also manufacturers of Netflix’s Bridgerton merchandise associated with the streamer’s hit show. Repackaging pretzels on screen during her series was the model for her business.[873] She never denied that all her products were merely re-labels of other corporations’ products.[874] But more importantly, she had never disclosed that her products were not original. American Riviera Orchard and As Ever were just smokescreens.

Maines would not allow other journalists access to Meghan to ask the ‘founder’ challenging questions. Instead, Meghan delivered a homily: ‘I think it speaks to this chapter many of us find ourselves in, where none of us are one note. But I believe all the notes I am playing are part of the same song.’[875] Some would call it a battle song for Meghan’s survival. And also for Harry’s.

CHAPTER 41

Contrasting Lives

Meghan was nowhere to be seen as Harry fought his latest battle.

In mid-February 2025, soon after his return from Vancouver, Harry asked Tim Boucher, a Sentebale trustee, to call Sophie Chandauka.

‘Will you resign immediately?’ asked Boucher.

‘Why should I resign?’ she replied. ‘I’m still a whistle-blower.’

‘If you go,’ said Boucher, ‘Harry will fund the organisation.’

Chandauka asked the fifteen executives and fifty-strong team in Lesotho whether she should resign. Many urged her to resist. Having witnessed Harry’s aggressive behaviour towards Chandauka during the last Zoom board meeting, and recalling his absence from Lesotho for five years, they did not want to be dependent on him.

On 16th February, Mark Dyer submitted a motion to the board to remove Chandauka from Sentebale on the grounds that she failed to get along with anyone, including Harry. Dyer had ignored the procedures required by the governance rules. Chandauka’s lawyer stopped the meeting. In a fury, Dyer called the lawyer.

‘If she stays, we won’t speak to her,’ he announced.

‘It’s a hostile takeover,’ Harry declared.

At Harry’s request, Sentebale’s trustees secretly approved Chandauka’s dismissal. Pertinently, Sentebale’s lawyers advised Harry that he was acting without authority. It later appeared that Harry’s name was repeatedly mentioned on the lawyer Bates Wells’ invoices.

‘I’m fighting in the dark,’ Chandauka told her supporters. To stop her ‘ejection’, Chandauka applied to London’s High Court to pause any board meetings for six weeks. Unopposed, on 5th March she succeeded. Temporarily, the trustees were unable to remove her. Five days later, to avoid the legal costs to fight Chandauka in court, Harry adopted radical tactics.

On 10th March, the trustees signed a ‘private and confidential’ letter addressed to Chandauka outlining the reasons for her dismissal. ‘It’s a horrible letter,’ Chandauka told friends. ‘It’s all about discrediting and destroying me. It’s hugely defamatory.’ To provoke a revolt against Chandauka, the ‘private and confidential’ letter was emailed to all of Sentebale’s staff.

Until then, to protect the charity, the court proceedings initiated by Chandauka had been kept private. Harry and Mark Dyer must have decided their best ploy to force Chandauka’s resignation was a public assault. Over the following two weeks, they agreed that the remaining trustees should resign on 25th March, accompanied by a statement criticising Chandauka.[876]

On the eve of the resignations, Harry handed a statement to The Times. The impression Harry created for his global audience was of a cherished charity being destroyed by one woman’s gross mismanagement. Hours after his public onslaught damaged Chandauka’s reputation, Harry and Prince Seeiso, the charity’s co-founder in Botswana, announced their own resignations. Both said they were ‘truly heartbroken’. And they continued: ‘It is devastating that the relationship between the charity’s trustees and the chair of the board broke down beyond repair, creating an untenable situation.’

Doubting that Harry sincerely wanted to save Sentebale, Chandauka had already chosen their replacements – two African trustees: Nerissa Naidu, a South African businesswoman, and Dr Margaret Ikpoh, a practising GP in Britain, and the English former banker Iain Rawlinson.[877] Two hours after Harry’s resignation, she adopted the very tactics used by Meghan and Harry to attack the Royal Family – full-blast media. In a series of interviews, she denounced Harry for wanting ‘to force a failure and then come to the rescue’.[878] She accused Harry and Dyer of ‘playing the victim card and using the very press they disdain to harm people who have the courage to challenge their conduct’. Chandauka described herself as the scapegoat for ‘daring to blow the whistle’ on ‘weak governance, weak executive management, abuse of power, bullying, harassment, misogynoir – and the cover-up that ensued’.[879] Bluntly, Harry was accused of the evil which Meghan levelled at the Royal Family – white elitism. Speaking ‘first and foremost as a proud African’, Chandauka asserted, ‘I will not be intimidated. I must stand for something. I stand for those other women who do not have the ways and means.’

Harry and Dyer had not anticipated Chandauka’s retaliation. While Dyer briefed the media about the ‘horrors’ caused by Chandauka’s mismanagement, Harry fired back through Alex Rayner, an old Etonian friend: ‘He is just beyond heartbroken and flabbergasted that the charity he founded as a teenager has been taken hostage by the chair. It feels tantamount to a hostile takeover. He feels as if he has had one of his fingers cut off.’[880] But Chandauka would not be cowed.

Dramatically, she appeared in Sky TV’s studio to be interviewed by Trevor Phillips. Astutely, she brought Iain Rawlinson to sit next to her. ‘The number one risk for this organisation,’ said Chandauka, ‘was the toxicity of its lead patron’s brand.’ In a broadcast streamed across the world, Harry was accused of covering up an investigation into ‘harassment, bullying and misogyny at scale’.[881] Harry’s alleged bad behaviour attracted thousands of comments.[882]

‘Blatant lies,’ retorted Harry.[883] Too late. His tag – ‘life of service’ – flopped. Hostilities abruptly stopped after the Charity Commission agreed to Chandauka’s request for an investigation.[884] Harry was paralysed. Simultaneously, African Parks’ denial of abuses towards tribesmen had been exposed as untrue. Omnia Strategy, the London law firm, reported that ‘human rights abuses have occurred’ against the Baka people. African Parks’ rangers were culpable. Survival International called on Harry to resign.[885] He refused.

Days later, Harry’s appearance at an Upfront Summit in Los Angeles, a prestigious conference for influential billionaire venture capitalists and tech giants, looked embarrassing.[886] At the end of a rambling address recycling his emotional laundry – mental health, social media and the Royal Family – the audience was silent. Few clapped. He was dubbed ‘the relic of a media cycle’. His ‘rehashed’ brand was dying. The Prince had become a ‘background noise’, a non-essential nonentity.[887]

Life for Harry was appearing more and more directionless. His days were spent exercising, occasionally collecting his children from school and smoking cannabis. His only purposeful activity was planning the next Invictus Games and plotting his battles in London’s High Courts.

On 4th April 2025, The Times portrayed the Royal Family’s contrasting lives. At the top of page 15, the newspaper reported that Rio de Janeiro would be William’s next venue for The Earthshot Prize. The organisation’s new CEO was Jason Knauf, the Sussexes’ former communications chief. At the foot of the page was the report of Harry’s ‘heartbreak’ about Sentebale. The Charity Commission intended to investigate whether Chandauka’s payment of £400,000 ($500,000) to consultants was a conflict of interest, one of many damaging rumours spread by the former trustees.

In the middle of the page was a stunning photograph of Meghan illustrating her tip that As Ever’s £11 jam should be spread over a crepe ‘for a romantic breakfast in bed’. The former champion of privacy was seeking publicity for her Lemonada podcasts.

To engineer another make-or-break moment, Meghan’s publicists manufactured another news clash. On the very day that Charles and Camilla started a state tour of Italy – only hours after Charles had received his latest cancer treatment in a London hospital – Meghan’s Confessions of a Female Founder podcast series for Lemonada was launched. In a strange move, her publicists revealed she had suffered an obscure illness during pregnancy. Her announcement was accompanied by childhood photographs taken by her father.

Her podcast’s introduction was succinct: ‘I’m Meghan and this is Confessions of a Female Founder, a show where I chat with female entrepreneurs and friends about the sleepless nights, the lessons learned, and the laser focus that got them to where they are today.’

From the outset, the series followed a familiar pattern of embellishing her past – self-pity, self-love and her self-judgement. Citing many foreign trips with her mother to taste food, she said: ‘We would just try so many different flavours in different places.’[888] Previously, she had only mentioned a single trip with Doria to Jamaica.

Meghan also described a blissful childhood with Doria. But her mother was actually absent for over ten years of her childhood, during which time Meghan had lived with her father. On the podcasts, she described herself as a latch-key kid eating TV dinners. But previously she had prided herself as a child choosing ‘healthy farm food’.[889] She also mentioned living for ‘several months’ in Argentina while ‘interning at the US Embassy’. In reality, she had spent five weeks at a school attached to the embassy and then failed the entrance examination. The following year, she returned to holiday in Argentina with a local boyfriend and, finding herself broke, was bailed out by her father.[890] The rewriting of Meghan’s biography was matched by the Sussexes’ endless hunt for headlines.

On the same day that Buckingham Palace expected photographs of Charles and Camilla’s state visit to Rome to feature on the front pages, Harry unexpectedly arrived in London.[891] The Palace’s planned media campaign was wiped out by Harry’s entrance at the High Court. He was appealing against the Home Office’s refusal to provide automatic protection in Britain. ‘This one always mattered the most,’ he said.[892] He had spent the previous night at a hotel in Windsor while his father was at Highgrove. They had barely spoken since his dash to London after the King’s cancer diagnosis in February 2024.

Harry’s presence in the court was perfectly judged to win maximum publicity. Journalists poured into the room to watch the Prince. His argument – that he was ‘singled out for different, unjustified and inferior treatment’ – was, as his lawyers ought to have known, certain to fail. The Home Office’s promise to provide him with ‘bespoke protection’ was advantageous. Just because Harry disliked the uncertainty did not make Ravec’s decision unlawful.[893]

Harry had shifted his argument. The reason the Sussexes had left Britain, his lawyer Shaheed Fatima told the judge, was because ‘they considered they were not being protected by the institution’. Originally, Harry claimed his privacy was unprotected from the media. Now he said he had been unprotected and left undefended from assassins.

After leaving the courtroom at the end of the second day, Harry suspected he had lost. Keen to get his version out first, Harry wanted to give a media interview. Instead of cautioning the Prince that he could only lose by attacking the courts and his family, Meredith Maines summoned the Daily Telegraph’s Victoria Ward. Maines did not anticipate Britain’s reaction to Harry’s anger.

‘People would be shocked by what’s being held back,’ Harry told Ward about the security evidence submitted during the closed session of the trial. ‘My worst fears have been confirmed.’ The Palace’s lies, he said, were ‘difficult to swallow’. He was the victim, he said, of blackmail by the Palace. His protection, he said, had been withdrawn while they were in Canada to prevent ‘Megxit’ and force them back to Britain.[894] Harry knew that his allegation was inaccurate. The Canadian government had publicly announced its refusal to pay for armed protection once he had decided to live permanently in California as a non-working royal. Canadian taxpayers, said the Ottawa government, would not bear the expense.

The second part of his message was an attack on his father. If only the King had intervened, said Harry, he could have secured armed protection for him – and reconciliation would have followed. He wanted peace, Harry said.

The interview rebounded. To say that his move to California was driven by the denial of armed protection in Britain was fanciful. Harry’s version fuelled the lack of trust within the Palace. Camilla, Kate and William urged the King not to consider any peace initiative from his younger son. Without William’s explicit agreement, Charles considered it unwise to speak to Harry. To survive, the House of Windsor could tolerate no division. Cultivating a compromise was impossible, especially in light of the King’s continuing cancer treatment and his sensitivity about his heir’s intention to change the monarchy after his succession. Uncertain about how long he would live, Charles allowed William to thwart Harry. The rift deepened.

That evening in London, Harry was evidently lonely. The previous day he had refused an invitation to the wedding at Chelsea Old Town Hall of his friend Lord Charles Vivian, one of the so-called ‘band of brothers’ photographed on the night of Harry’s wedding in 2018. Harry’s excuse was the lack of armed protection. Though, despite his sense of vulnerability, after the Telegraph’s interview, Harry headed to Fulham to find old friends John and Georgina Vaughan. Although he knew the street he could not recall their house number. He rang at least three doorbells until he was told that the Vaughans had rented their house out some years earlier and their current address was unknown. The doorbell videos of the unaccompanied Prince on strangers’ doorsteps, only hours after pleading he needed armed protection, mocked his fears of assassination in London.[895]

The image of Harry wandering alone down a London street reflected the Sussexes’ reality: Harry was lost in London, with frayed family links and few friends. Meghan was alone in Montecito, giving her critics the impression that she was listening again and again to her Lemonada podcasts and rewatching herself on Netflix, failing to understand why she was targeted by ridicule rather than deluged with praise.

Meghan had just appeared on an episode of a podcast produced by the cosmetics entrepreneur Jamie Kern Lima. Widely ridiculed, it showed the two Montecito mothers having an ‘intimate’ heart-to-heart conversation. ‘My very first question,’ said Lima, ‘and I think so many people also have this question for you. Meghan, how are you? And are you OK?’

Appearing often on the verge of tears, Meghan spoke about her children and repeatedly referred to the ‘power of yet’ as her parenting philosophy to boost her kids’ esteem. She spoke of the ‘power of yet’ as if it was her own invention, but the concept was well known, and had even featured on Sesame Street eleven years earlier.[896]

Meghan appeared to be clinging to her children to promote herself generally. ‘Rare’ photos became a blizzard of images. Archie was shown feeding fish in the garden and watering plants; Lilibet was playing with Serena Williams. More photos followed, taken on Mother’s Day and at ‘incredibly special’ birthday parties, also in the kitchen making bagels and Valentine cakes,[897] in the garden picking roses, on their Montecito balcony looking at the ocean, cuddling on the beach on a ‘surprise’ holiday, and so many more. The question was whether Meghan wanted her children, who were addressed on her insistence as ‘prince’ and ‘princess’, to lead normal lives. In Britain, many royal children, including those of Anne, Princess Royal, never used their titles. ‘I think everyone has a basic right to privacy,’ Meghan had told Oprah Winfrey. Her children were not being given that choice.

In the midst of her conversation with Jamie Lima, Meghan pulled out a letter from her children. ‘I wasn’t expecting this,’ she simpered. Blinking back tears she recited their ‘love’ for her and soulfully put the letter back in her pocket.

‘Meghan’s not spontaneous,’ recalled Thomas Markle. ‘Everything she says is pre-planned and rehearsed. I know when she’s faking it for the cameras. She’s trying so hard to be perfect that she tenses up every time the camera is on her. Unfortunately, Meghan has never been authentic.’[898]

In her Lemonada podcasts and Netflix series, Meghan focused on self-discovery and self-love. Whitney Wolfe Herd, the co-founder of Tinder and once the world’s youngest female self-made billionaire, was the star of the first episode, recorded just before As Ever’s products were launched. The dominant theme was Meghan’s description of her own crisis at 3am the previous night. She was ‘absolutely consumed’ about the packaging for the As Ever products. ‘Boxes. It’s all I could think about,’ she said. ‘My brain went in a loop and you can’t stop overthinking. I would sit there doing the unboxing in my head. Is there tissue paper? What about the packing of peanuts, but they’re biodegradable? Where does the sticker go and what size is the box going to be?’[899] By the time the episode was streamed, the truth about As Ever was known.

The podcast series swiftly fell out of Spotify’s top 100 and never reached Apple’s top 200. Insiders leaked that Beyoncé and Taylor Swift had rejected Meghan’s handwritten invitations to appear. Instead, Meghan interviewed Beyoncé’s mother, Tina Knowles, a 71-year-old former hairstylist.[900] Initially, the producers decided the interview was best forgotten. Then, at the last moment, to avoid insulting Beyoncé, it was posted. Focused on Meghan’s business life, the highlight was her anticipation of a future business partnership with Lilibet.

And then in mid-April 2025, another ‘turning point’ fizzled out. Netflix announced that a second season of With Love, Meghan had been recorded and would be streamed. But other than sticking a label on her chosen Napa Valley rosé wine manufactured by the Fairwinds Estate, the Sussexes’ future was uncertain.[901] There was nothing gloriously new to be unveiled. Harry and Meghan faced unemployment and a diminishing income.

Meghan’s neighbour Ted Sarandos compounded her misery by ending the rolling contract that had started in 2020.[902] Three months earlier, Sarandos had praised Meghan as ‘underestimated in terms of her influence on culture. People are fascinated with Meghan Markle.’ But since then, Netflix’s auditors had scrutinised Meghan’s value. Despite radical changes, her second series, due to be streamed in August 2025, was less promising than the first. Meghan simply portrayed her idyllic lifestyle and confessed that she could not cook. Her recipe for roast chicken was utterly conventional and she admitted, ‘I don’t like baking because it’s so measured.’ Swishing around her rented kitchen, she watched a succession of uninspiring chefs perform, accompanied by a series of inconsequential conversations and autobiographical anecdotes, all punctuated by her word-salad phrases that included ‘moving meditation’ and ‘creating calm’.

To mitigate the outcome, Sarandos agreed that Netflix would possibly commission a third series of Meghan’s show. First, she would need to provide an outline of the content. Netflix would have first refusal on her synopsis. To further soften the blow, Netflix’s publicists offered as Sarandos’s sign-off quote: ‘She’s a rock star. She’s got a purpose, building a new world.’[903] Later, Sarandos added that the series, rated number 136 on Netflix’s charts after two weeks, was ‘successful on every level’.[904] Netflix’s financial risk was minimal. Meghan was on her own, but that did not deter her from boasting that Netflix had assigned eighty people to develop As Ever. ‘The two of us together make an incredible partnership,’ she said unblinkingly.[905]

Meghan’s next decisions suggested that she blamed her employees for the mishits. She once again approved dismissals – more radical ones than ever. Meredith Maines took control of the firing and hiring.[906] Contrary to Ashley Hansen’s portrait of Montecito’s ‘zen’ atmosphere as ‘always very calm and peaceful and warm’,[907] an eyewitness recalled ‘submerged hysteria’. Maines’s statement sought to hide the mayhem: ‘As the Duke and Duchess’s business and philanthropic interests grow, I have made the strategic decision to move toward a more traditional communications structure of specialist agency support.’

Maines’s task was to restore the Sussexes’ status. Too many admitted that association with the Sussexes risked a backlash. Since nominations to receive awards no longer arrived and invitations to celebrity parties had dried up, Meghan seized the offer of an award for championing women at the Los Angeles Natural History Museum gala. The award was approved by the co-chairman, Rick Genow, her long-serving lawyer. Soon after, the event was postponed.[908] The only opportunity for exposure was Time magazine’s 100 Summit in New York.

Time’s organisers had been surprised that Meghan accepted the invitation to be interviewed on stage. Not only were the Sussexes not listed among the magazine’s ‘Most Influential’ but Time had slammed With Love, Meghan under the headline ‘A Royal Prime on Entertaining That Couldn’t Be More Boring’.[909] But having lost support from Vanity Fair and New York Magazine, the Sussexes needed allies and, Meghan insisted, positive exposure.

A four-car convoy – two police cars, one for their bodyguards and their own SUV – arrived on 23rd April at the police-guarded Manhattan venue. Wearing a £3,755 Ralph Lauren trouser suit and jewellery worth tens of thousands of pounds, including a diamond piece given to her by King Charles, Meghan emerged flustered from the SUV. Disappointed by the absence of a crowd – just two elderly ladies stood behind the police line[910] – she theatrically embraced a waiting staffer for the camera and was ushered backstage. Standing with Time’s editor-in-chief Sam Jacobs before entering the spotlight, she shunned approaches by the representatives of the magazine’s commercial partners, including Amazon and Pfizer. Noticeably, she was contemplating her rehearsed lines.

The night before, Kate had posted a video of Louis on his seventh birthday running around Anmer Hall on the Sandringham estate. Hours later, Meghan posted an Instagram of herself kissing Harry. But unexpectedly that morning, British newspapers had also published a birthday photo of Louis, without two front teeth, sitting on a tree stump in a field of bluebells. Before going on stage, Meghan had clearly calculated her response.

The magazine’s chief executive Jessica Sibley welcomed Meghan in the hall for a session entitled ‘The Power of Flower Sprinkles’.[911] After some mutual gushing, Meghan spoke about her ‘busy and ambitious’ year. Turning to the audience, Sibley asked how many had watched Meghan’s show. Six hands rose, including Harry’s. Meghan’s smile did not falter. To conceal an awkward moment she urged the audience to ‘add a little splash of magic’ to every day with flower sprinkles. Sibley showered more praise on her guest. Then Meghan retaliated against the news coming from London.

Archie’s first tooth, Meghan proudly announced, was loose. The tooth fairy intended to rush 3,000 miles back to Montecito ‘in time for it – that is all that matters’. As a parent, she told the audience, everything ‘becomes so microscopic in importance compared to what’s happening with your children’. Sibley’s beam never faded. The fate of Archie’s tooth was serious news. The session ended with applause.

The following night, the Sussexes failed to appear as expected at Time’s gala party in the Lincoln Center. Some assumed Meghan had indeed returned to Montecito.[912] Instead, she and Harry spoke at the ‘Lost Screen Memorial’ to about fifty parents in memory of their children who had died, casualties of social media.[913]

Meghan’s speech was familiar: ‘I’m told that in 2019, I was the most trolled person in the entire world – male or female.’ And during eight months of that year, she said, ‘I wasn’t even visible. I was on maternity leave with a baby. It’s almost unsurvivable.’[914] Meghan’s memory was imperfect but few would have remembered that she had been frequently seen, not least at her baby shower in New York.

A private jet flew the Sussexes back to Santa Barbara. Early on 2nd May, Meghan posted photographs of Harry and their two children in the garden. As presumably intended, the photos overshadowed that day’s birthday picture of Charlotte, Kate’s ten-year-old daughter. Hours later, the High Court delivered its verdict on Harry’s four-year battle against the government for armed protection. Harry had lost.[915] He was ‘devastated’, said Maines.[916]

No one apparently offered Harry judicious advice to accept defeat gracefully. His lawyers had scuttled away, pocketing at least £1.5 million. Holed up in Montecito, he lamented, ‘I wish someone had told me beforehand that there was no way to win.’[917] Even less help came from Meghan. Caution was also alien to Maines. ‘Harry wants to strike while the iron is hot,’ she was told. She supported Harry’s wish to be interviewed in Los Angeles by the BBC.

Maines had made the arrangements for a ‘victory’ interview before the verdict was announced. Usually, she would have approached a BBC editor in London, then waited for a reporter to be assigned. But Meghan had been wooing the BBC’s UN correspondent in New York, Nada Tawfik. She especially liked Tawfik’s critical coverage of Donald Trump’s anti-migrant policies. In Tawfik’s favour was also her lack of knowledge of the Royal Family. Her questions would not be forensic and, critically, she would not challenge Harry from either the Palace’s or the government’s perspective. Offered an exclusive by Tawfik, the BBC’s editors in London failed to grasp how they were being played. Instead of sending an experienced royal correspondent, they agreed that Tawfik should fly to Los Angeles before the verdict was announced.[918]

After Tawfik was told that Harry had lost the case, she assumed that the interview would be cancelled. Instead, she was told to meet Harry at a house in Santa Barbara owned by an acquaintance of the Sussexes. Shortly after the setting up of the camera, Harry appeared with Maines. ‘He seemed properly thrown off course,’ said a BBC eyewitness. ‘He had not cooled down.’ His first comments were about antagonistic British journalists. Agitated, he sat down for what was planned as a ten-minute interview. He could not stop talking.

As usual, his agenda looked like vengeance. The privileged Prince was outraged that politicians, officials and judges led by the King himself had refused to bow to his wishes.

‘I have all of the truth,’ he told the camera.[919] During the legal process, he said, ‘I have discovered that some people want history to repeat itself, which is pretty dark.’ Harry meant that the same courtiers in Buckingham Palace who ‘preyed upon my mother . . . continue to incite hatred towards me, my wife and even our children’.[920] He added that, ‘All I’ve been asking for is safety.’[921] He damned Buckingham Palace officials for having ‘won in keeping me unsafe [and] knowingly put me and my family in harm’s way’. He blamed a ‘good old-fashioned Establishment stitch-up’ for losing in court and lamented, ‘It’s really quite sad that I won’t be able to show my children my homeland.’[922]

The climax was Harry’s accusation that the King was entirely to blame. ‘There is a lot of control and ability in my father’s hands. Ultimately, this whole thing could be resolved through him. Not necessarily by intervening but by stepping aside, allowing the experts to do what is necessary.’ That was precisely Ravec’s role. Harry was clearly confused. Initially, he had demanded that his father should interfere but finally lamented that he had not. Harry never understood that if he had met his father and then reported any suggested ‘conversation’ between them about the court case, the constitutional consequences would have been incalculable.

Harry’s confession revealed his desperation. Fearing that his brother, as king, could banish him from Britain, he pleaded, ‘There’s no point to fight any more. Life is precious.’ And then with calculated heartlessness, he added, ‘I don’t know how much longer my father has. He won’t speak to me because of this security stuff. It would be nice to reconcile.’

Buckingham Palace was caught out by the interview. Given just thirty minutes’ notice before its broadcast, the BBC refused the Palace the opportunity to reply. Palace officials believed the BBC’s editors had betrayed them. They had pandered to the Sussexes’ scheme. Even the BBC’s royal correspondent Sean Coughlan was surprised by the corporation’s prejudice.[923] Eventually, the BBC apologised for their mistake. Reflecting the King’s anger, Buckingham Palace posted its own statement: ‘All of these issues have been examined repeatedly and meticulously by the courts, with the same conclusion reached on each occasion.’ On GB News, Harry was accused of being ‘deluded and desperate’.[924] Overnight, Harry reflected on his interview and spoke of his ‘love for reconciliation’. He had ‘forgiven’ Charles and William.

‘Harry has simply lost touch with reality,’ a Palace official eventually volunteered. ‘He’s deluded. He went scorched earth, which was foolish. The man doesn’t get the message.’ Courtiers mentioned that Harry had chosen to leave Britain, wanted privileges when he returned and no one had asked him to come back.

The Palace’s anger was not limited to Harry’s interview. On the eve of the VE Day commemorations on 8th May, the Palace appealed to the media not to focus on the family drama. Inevitably, King Charles’s and William’s solemn appearances at parades and church services were overshadowed by the Prince of Montecito’s TV interview.

‘When history comes to be written about the King, this will reflect badly on him,’ wrote Peter Hunt, a former BBC royal correspondent. The striking failure of King Charles’s reign was his inability to heal the rift with Harry. ‘The King represents an institution that is about family, unity and fostering forgiveness. His role is to bring people together and yet he can’t bring people together on his doorstep.’[925]

Nine days after Harry’s BBC interview, Meghan posted a picture of herself with her two children marking Mother’s Day. In a move surely designed to irritate the Palace, they were captioned ‘prince’ and ‘princess’. Meghan played up to William’s nightmare – a rival court in California.[926]

Staying in the spotlight was Meghan’s weapon for survival. Releasing photos and videos guaranteed her credibility. Invisibility was inconceivable. Ridicule was the risk she faced. Both Sussexes were going for broke.

CHAPTER 42

The Last Calamity

‘She messed it up. She’s run out of steam,’ concluded Ella Robertson three years after Meghan’s ill-fated appearance at the One Young World Summit in Manchester. ‘She’s got an identity crisis.’

Even though her Netflix series With Love, Meghan was slick, the ridicule on social media was toxic. Meredith Maines recommended an aggressive response to highlight Meghan’s authenticity.

Hoping that public curiosity would secure Netflix’s commission of a third series, Meghan celebrated Lilibet’s fourth birthday on 4th June with three posts for her now 3.9 million followers, including a photo of Lilibet collecting honey.[927] Next, she posted a homemade video of herself jerking energetically up and down to the soundtrack of Starrkeisha’s ‘The Baby Momma Dance’.[928] It had been recorded in a hospital delivery room in 2021 when the heavily pregnant Meghan had apparently been trying to induce Lilibet’s birth. Harry slinked in and out of view, pressing his groin close to the lens. In the background was the delivery chair.

Within twenty-four hours, the video had been viewed 20 million times. ‘You have to be authentic,’ Meghan would tell businesswoman Emma Grede. ‘Whatever people do, there’s still a whole life – a real, authentic, fun life – that’s happening behind the scenes.’[929] She believed that Americans appreciated her humour. The predictably crusty British reaction was irrelevant. ‘Twerking’ marked her eighth return since 2020 to social media: ‘It was a great way to get my voice back. It’s my space and my channel of joy.’

Amid the deluge of comments, a minority praised Meghan’s humour.[930] The majority mentioned that the privacy seeker’s video was scarcely believable, cringeworthy and embarrassing. A vocal few were convinced that Meghan’s ‘moon bump’ was fake and proved that her children were delivered by surrogates.[931] Most agreed it was a bizarre dance to choose before childbirth, odd that it should be filmed and incredible how Meghan calculated that posting the video four years after her birth could be advantageous.[932]

More substantially, few could understand Meghan’s estimation that her performance reinforced her status as a serious player. Just who did Meghan hope to influence favourably? Did she realise the risks of being judged as an attention-hunting celebrity? The denizens of the fashion and lifestyle world expected their models to be coolly sophisticated rather than recklessly vulgar.

Among her defenders was the US tech entrepreneur Christopher Bouzy. ‘Every joyful moment,’ he wrote, ‘gets twisted into ammunition by people who’ve made destroying her their full-time job. This isn’t normal criticism. It’s psychological torture designed to break someone’s spirit. Meghan Markle is a mother who can’t share her joy without it being weaponised against her. And we need to talk about what this sustained cruelty has done to a woman whose only crime was falling in love with a prince.’[933]

To boost her cause, ‘Meghan, Duchess of Sussex’ posted another mass of images. She posed wearing a range of white clothes on a beach; shared family snaps taken during a visit to Disneyland; displayed herself with As Ever’s apricot spread, honey and rosé wine, and, finally, there was a video of Harry with both children at all ages and in different locations, revealing their faces.[934] A hallowed principle had been abandoned.

Meghan and Harry were struggling to halt the downward spiral. The momentum needed to be reversed to guarantee their financial security. Rather than hunkering down, they both doubled their efforts to be seen.

Harry went back on the road. First, he flew to Shanghai to promote Travalyst at a tourism conference.[935] Few had expected to see him there, but he probably enjoyed overshadowing his father’s visit to Canada to open parliament – the first by a monarch since 1957. Despite his illness, the King completed a 24-hour round trip to support the new government’s rallying cry against Donald Trump.

One month later on 29th June, Harry spoke in New York at the Nexus Global Summit ‘Bold Voice Brave Ideas’. Introduced as a global humanitarian, his session was titled ‘Building Tomorrow: A Conversation on Service, Impact & Collective Action with Prince Harry’.[936] Instead of delivering a carefully crafted speech, Harry rambled about his familiar troubles and advocated that young people should be allowed to lead the world before instantly contradicting himself: ‘I think that the longer that we are on Planet Earth the more experience we have.’ At the end of forty-five minutes, some in the audience were looking at their phones or exchanging exasperated looks. His bumbling performance added to the credibility of a slew of bogus YouTube videos ‘showing’ him storming out of studios after tough interviews with Graham Norton and NBC’s Savannah Guthrie. The nadir was his agreement to appear in a real estate conference staged by Power House in Toronto.[937]

Harry had reached a crossroads. After nearly five years, his stardust was tarnished. He certainly did not contemplate leaving California in the near future, but restoring his roots in Britain had become essential. Fortunately, Meredith Maines had established a relationship with the King’s communications secretary, Tobyn Andreae, a former editorial executive at the Daily Mail. They agreed to meet in mid-July in London’s Royal Overseas League Club, overlooking Green Park. Also present was Harry’s British publicist, Liam Maguire, a Sandhurst officer with links to Invictus. Harry’s camp could not resist leaking the encounter to Charlotte Griffiths, a Mail on Sunday writer. In previous months, Griffiths had reported that Harry could be reconciled with his family. Her latest revelation, illustrated by a photograph of Andreae and Maines sitting together on the club’s veranda overlooking the garden, delighted Harry.[938] He was one step closer to meeting his father. William’s anger was predictable but, for the moment, irrelevant for Harry.

Harry’s progress towards restoring his status in Britain was clipped by the Charity Commission’s report on Sentebale. To win in the court of public opinion, Harry relied on the commission to dismiss Sophie Chandauka’s allegations of his bullying manner, condemn her hostile takeover and restore the charity to his control. Not least, he said, because Sentebale’s coffers were empty and the charity’s operations were collapsing.[939]

The conclusions depended on the judgement of the commission’s case officer, Chris Sladen, after reading thousands of pages of evidence. To oust Chandauka, Harry engaged Schillings to bombard Sladen with evidence to counter Chandauka’s arguments. Some believed Sladen was prejudiced. During their conversations, he appeared to focus on Chandauka’s conduct rather than on Harry’s.

In the first draft of his findings, sent to both sides for comment, Sladen criticised the charity’s poor management and ‘lack of clear policies’. But he refused to consider any complaints of individual bullying. That, he wrote, was beyond the Charity Commission’s remit. Chandauka countered that her complaint was about Harry and his supporters generating a bullying atmosphere during the Zoom executive meetings. To her surprise, the commission’s final report ignored her complaint. She suspected that it had confined its own judgement to having found ‘no widespread bullying’ due to pressure from Harry’s lawyers. The report, however, acknowledged ‘the strong perception of ill treatment’ was felt by some involved.[940]

Harry seized on Sladen’s inconsequential judgement to declare that he had been personally cleared of any wrongdoing including, more particularly, bullying. ‘That’s wrong,’ said Chandauka. The commission, she rightly observed, had deliberately refused to comment on Harry’s conduct. His behaviour was neither approved nor condemned, just ignored. And equally, the commission was silent about Chandauka’s manner. To her satisfaction, despite criticising the charity’s ‘governance weaknesses’, the commission approved her continued chairmanship. Harry was barred from returning. He was furious. Sladen’s investigation, commented the self-appointed victim, had fallen ‘troublingly short’.[941] The commission, fumed Harry, was ‘sitting on the fence’ because the report ‘criticised all parties’.

Chandauka feared that Harry’s supporters were seeking to sabotage her management of Sentebale in Botswana below the radar. Not least because the Prince had pledged to build a new charity in Africa.[942] Few believed Harry’s promise. The financial and logistical obstacles were too great, and his behaviour was unpredictable.

In the charity’s next annual report, Chandauka would boast that Sentebale’s annual income had remained roughly the same at £3.35 million. All the institutional donors had continued their support to the benefit of 78,000 children. The charity’s future without Harry, she reported, was secure.[943] In retaliation, one of Harry’s supporters briefed The Times that Sentebale’s operations in Botswana were ‘not working at all’.[944] The finances, Harry’s supporter claimed without providing any evidence, were ‘getting into the red’. Chandauka’s judgement of Harry did not improve: ‘He’s vengeful – capable of dehumanising others whom he treats like nonentities.’

Chandauka’s feelings about Harry were reflected in the anger among government ministers of the landlocked country of Chad in central Africa towards African Parks, Harry’s other charity on the continent. Peter Fearnhead, the charity’s secretive chief executive, was engaged in a bitter argument with Chad’s rulers over the management of the country’s Zakouma National Park. Previously hailed by the New York Times as ‘one of the most stunning conservation success stories in Africa’, Chad’s politicians had discovered in mid-2025 that, unknown to them, poachers had been rampant across the conservation area. Rhinos, elephants and giraffes had died or been killed. Delving into African Parks’ finances, routed through offshore accounts, the government accused African Parks of ‘incompetence’, ‘notorious financial misconduct’ and failing to protect the country’s wildlife to benefit tourism.[945]

Hidden beneath the headline accusations were allegations of corruption. Seized ivory tusks had disappeared and a chunk of the €20 million donated by the European Union had been allegedly misappropriated.[946] Fearnhead’s struggle to bury the argument was over after the Chad government announced the expulsion of African Parks.[947] Carefully remaining silent, Harry had nevertheless become associated with another scandal, one eventually resolved by Fearnhead promising better performance.

Ignoring the latest calamity, Harry was focused on a carefully orchestrated four-day trip to Britain. Arriving on 8th September, he planned to promote himself as the smiling, generous royal serving the people. To this end, he gifted £1.1 million to Children in Need and, unusually for a royal, advertised his donation. To some, it appeared as mitigation money. His only gripe was the absence of police protection except for one day. Irritatingly, he was caught in a London traffic jam. Once again, he urged the Home Secretary to reconsider his need for protection.[948]

The public’s welcome for Harry exposed the Royal Family’s vulnerability. Beset by illness and strife, the royals were testing the public’s support. As an opinion poll reported, the shine was fading. The monarchy’s popularity had fallen from 86 per cent in 1983 to 51 per cent. No less than 38 per cent of Britons – mostly the young, the politically left wing and immigrants – wanted an elected head of state.[949] That dismal reality might have convinced Harry about the family’s need for his services.

Four days earlier, a senior Buckingham Palace official was adamant that the King would not meet his son during the trip.[950] But at the last moment, Charles agreed that, after flying down from Balmoral on 10th September for his weekly medical treatment, Harry could visit him at Clarence House. That morning, according to a visitor in Balmoral, ‘the King looked very grey’.[951]

Their first encounter after nineteen months lasted fifty-four minutes. Harry gave Charles a family photograph but no photo of the two was taken or released. Although Meredith Maines would brief that their meeting was the beginning of a thaw and reconciliation, others told the Sun that it was ‘distinctly formal’, like ‘an official visit’. Four days later, under the headline ‘Reconciliation in the Air’, an anonymous insider was quoted: ‘If any details of the meeting emerge, or there is any commentary, it will be back to square one.’[952] By then, though, Harry had already broken his promise of silence.

During a train journey into Ukraine to reinforce the country’s participation in the 2027 Invictus Games, Harry told an invited Guardian journalist without any hint of regret that he’d done nothing wrong. Reconciliation, he said, was only possible by telling the truth. ‘It’s not about revenge. It’s about accountability,’ he added. ‘The book? It was a series of corrections to stories already out there. One point of view had been put out and it needed to be corrected. I don’t believe that I aired my dirty laundry in public. My conscience is clear.’ Referring to Meghan, he said he had adopted her advice to ‘just stick to the truth’. Rhetorically, he asked, ‘Who would be stupid enough to lie? It takes up too much time and effort.’

Oblivious to that misstep, Meredith Maines continued to herald Harry’s success. Harry, she said, was fashioning a new model as a working royal. He planned, she continued, to visit Britain four or five times a year for public events. Charlotte Griffiths reported that ‘high-level talks’ were under way to bring Harry and Charles together in a public show of unity. The King, she suggested, was siding with Harry against the ‘lazy’ Prince of Wales.[953]

Once again, Maines misjudged the Royal Family. In a phone call with his father, William reiterated that reconciliation with Harry was out of the question. Instantly, a Buckingham Palace courtier dampened Harry’s expectations. One visit, he disclosed, would not dispel the Royal Family’s deep suspicion. Harry would not be allowed to have a ‘half-in, half-out’ role. ‘Whoever is behind [the briefing],’ another insider said, ‘seems to have mistaken tea and a slice of cake with the Treaty of Versailles.’[954]

During the following week, Harry acknowledged that his enthusiasm was misplaced. His publicist spelled out Harry’s familiar gripe against the King’s advisors: ‘The men in grey suits are sabotaging my reunion with my father.’[955]

* * *

Throughout those months, Meghan separated herself from Harry’s woes, plotting instead how to restore her status in America. Selling As Ever products depended on making repeated appearances at star-studded events, especially after her second series ranked 383rd on Netflix’s chart. Critics of the series were puzzled by the contrived enthusiasm between Meghan and her guests and doubted any particular attraction of the As Ever sprinkles and wine. Few could grasp Meghan’s pitch for $14 raspberry ‘spreads’ – the word ‘jam’ had been discarded because her concoction was too runny. Supposedly, the spread was carefully produced in her own kitchen surrounded by caring ‘friends’ and her excited children rather than manufactured in Illinois. Who, those same critics wondered, aspired to copy someone who claimed, ‘I think there is a lot of value when you anchor into your own knowing’? [956]

Undeterred as usual by any shortcomings, Meghan planned the sale of her Christmas collection, including a ‘Signature Fruit Spread gift set’ priced at $42, a candle ‘scented with Moroccan mint, cardamom and tea leaves’, which for $64 promised to ‘evoke the freshness of a day in the English countryside’, and sage honey with honeycomb, which for $32 held ‘a special place in Meghan’s heart’. Topping the products was an unexceptional bottle of white wine for $89.[957]

Her 54-minute Netflix Christmas special to sell her wares suffered from the familiar flaws. Not least that her ceaseless ‘joy’ appeared to be breathlessly contrived and her emphasis on love for her ‘family’ at Christmas jarred with her deliberate estrangement from her father, her mother’s relations and the Royal Family. Pulling Christmas crackers with the family, she explained to an unknown guest, ‘really feels connective and sweet’. The Daily Telegraph’s headline would be: ‘Meghan’s Christmas Special Is Quite Mad and a Little Bit Sad’.

Over the previous months, Meghan’s staff and agent were galvanised to negotiate engagements in Hollywood, Los Angeles, Washington, New York and Paris. The prelude to her publicity blitz was an unexpected appearance at Kevin Costner’s annual Santa Barbara party to support the local emergency services. The previous year, she had disdained the event, but now her need for publicity overrode any concern. Overdressed for the event, she was wearing $325,000-worth of jewellery, her publicist revealed. Inevitably, it included a piece originally owned by Diana.

On Lilibet’s fourth birthday, Meghan first thanked Disney in what appeared to be a paid promotion: ‘Thank you, Disneyland, for giving our family two days of pure joy.’ Next, while Trump heaped praise in his speech on William as a ‘remarkable son’ during his triumphant state dinner at Windsor Castle, an Instagram video appeared of Meghan caring for strawberry plants in her garden. In reserve was the revelation that she had secured a cameo appearance playing herself in Close Personal Friends, a small-budget Amazon film to be shot in Pasadena. Although many would carp that the B-list actress abandoned by Hollywood in 2017 appeared to be desperate for a comeback, the announcement would guarantee publicity.[958] And then she made a surprise appearance at Paris fashion week.

The coup was masterminded by Meghan herself. Balenciaga, she knew, had been ‘cancelled’ in 2022 for featuring children alongside fetish-themed teddy bears. In the aftermath of the uproar, Balenciaga had hired a new creative director, Pierpaolo Piccioli, previously employed by Valentino. Meghan had worn a few of Piccioli’s costumes. She called him with a suggestion. In return for all her expenses, she would make a surprise entrance at his show. In the battle against their rivals for publicity, Balenciaga calculated Meghan’s proposal was a no-brainer. Nicole Kidman was paid millions of dollars by Chanel, so $250,000 for Meghan’s expenses was comparatively cheap.

Accompanied by her make-up artist Daniel Martin, a stylist and a press spokesman, Meghan secretly arrived on 4th October in the Plaza Athénée Hotel, the rendezvous for every fashionista visiting the capital. She was assigned the $22,000-per-night four-bedroom suite. None of the assembled photographers around the hotel knew where she was heading as she walked through the lobby dressed in a stunning Balenciaga white trouser and cape outfit. For a brief moment, the spectator of fashion shows had transformed herself into a glittering performer.

Even the empress of fashion, Vogue’s Anna Wintour, was already sitting at the Balenciaga show looking at two empty seats beside actress Tracy Ross. Twenty seconds before the lights dimmed, Meghan made a royal entrance. By then, the photographs of her exit from the hotel were zooming around the world. ‘You look wonderful,’ Wintour told the Duchess after the show. The only hiccups during those minutes were actress Kristin Scott Thomas appearing to turn sharply away as Meghan started to speak to her; a video posted of Meghan laughing after a model slipped on the runway; and a self-made video posted by Meghan of her drive back to the hotel in a limousine, insensitively passing the site of Diana’s fatal crash in 1997.

That evening, she did not go to Balenciaga’s after party but headed to a restaurant with Soho House’s Markus Anderson, once she had posted a glowing testimonial to Piccioli. She recalled that they had ‘worked closely together collaborating on design for key moments on the world stage . . . This evening reflects the culmination of many years’ artistry and friendship.’ Hours later, Piccioli dismissed Meghan’s version of events, telling The Cut magazine that he had not invited her to the show in Paris. She had instead asked Piccioli whether she could come.[959] His apparent snub did not undermine the stunning images of the white-clad duchess, though.

Next, Meghan was with Harry in New York to receive the ‘Humanitarians of the Year’ award from the insignificant Project Healthy Minds group, who were delighted by the publicity she bestowed. The following day, she appeared on stage at Fortune magazine’s Most Powerful Women event in Washington. Billed as a ‘high-profile, highly scrutinised founder’, Meghan spoke about ‘how she plans to leverage her significant influence to build a successful, long-lasting business empire’. Noticeably, she steered clear of any questions. The event was largely ignored by the public.[960] In between these events, she posted a video clip of herself with four-year-old Lilibet on International Day of the Girl. Her caption was the hope that her daughter would become ‘an activist’.[961] Once again, Archie was not included.

During those days, slickly edited videos were posted of her appearances, clothes, accessories and make-up accompanied by name-dropping of the ‘stars’ the self-appointed ‘hostess’ met, including Serena Williams, Ed Sheeran, Vogue’s new editor Chloe Malle and Gloria Steinem. And then some cracks started to appear. Together, Meghan and Harry looked tired. In New York, they seemed to be arguing after Meghan pushed Harry’s hand away. There was good reason for the tension.

In her latest bid to reposition herself from a fashion plate into a powerful, commercial and mature influencer of consequence, Meghan had approached Harper’s Bazaar, her trusted promoter, to signal the transition to her new status. Or, as she would call her make-or-break bid for commercial success during two lengthy interviews, ‘her own next chapter’. Part one of the interview was deliberately in public – in Beverly Hills’s Polo Lounge – and part two in Victoria Jackson’s New York house shortly before she received the Humanitarian Award.

Harper’s agreed to feature Meghan on the front cover of its valuable Christmas issue with the caption ‘Meghan, Duchess of Sussex, Meets Her Moment’. Taking a risk, Meghan had agreed to pose for a series of photographs showing a mature woman seemingly without make-up – or in the industry jargon, ‘no make-up make-up’. The resulting cover picture did not flatter the 44-year-old. Neither did the other photographs of her modelling clothes and jewellery, nor the interview. After years of uproar, Meghan’s protest to Harper’s ’ Kaitlyn Greenidge that because of ‘Megxit’, she had ‘lost her agency and her humanity’ was guaranteed to rile the victims of her Oprah Winfrey interview. Angered by the clamour of her critics, she intimated that her desire was to ‘break through that noise so people see that she is authentically trying to be herself’. Puncturing that image, Greenidge sneaked one mocking anecdote into her article. As she entered Jackson’s house, the butler announced ‘Meghan, Duchess of Sussex’ to an empty room.

‘Authenticity’ in Meghan-speak signalled her latest demand for the world to recognise that her influence was based neither on ‘deference nor dominance’ but on her ‘natural affability’. Or her genuine warmth towards everyone. Definitely not thanks to any sense of entitlement bequeathed by her marriage and royal title. Fiercely excluded from the ‘warmth’ was her father. Once again, Harper’s presented a distorted version of familiar milestones in her biography: Meghan lived throughout her schooldays with her mother – a gross error; she witnessed the 1992 Los Angeles riots – something her father had convincingly denied because he instantly drove her out of the city to safety; and that she had persuaded Procter & Gamble to abandon female stereotyping – which the company itself and her father had also emphatically contradicted.

As usual, Meghan steered the interview into two familiar zones. First, her children. ‘I hope they see the value of being brave,’ she said. Bravery, according to Meghan, was her children watching her cook, ‘when the jam was just a pot on the stove bubbling’. Secondly, she spoke about Harry: ‘He loves me so boldly, fully . . . No one in the world loves me more than him.’ That endearment was followed by a revelation about her husband: ‘You have someone who just has this childlike wonder and playfulness.’ In Meghan’s version, Harry’s foolish innocence enhanced her sense of fun. Her only error, she admitted, was trying to be ‘perfect’. That, she said, was ‘not a lot of fun’. Not least because ‘I, too, make mistakes.’ They were not listed.

In common with all her previous interviews, ‘Meghan’s Moment’ was another step on the familiar treadmill to establish her relevance and importance. But in delivering her thoughts and childhood memories, Meghan once again revealed a lack of any substance. After hours of interviews, even the favourably disposed Greenidge described a woman whose fame was entirely based on her marriage.

While deciding on the launch date of Netflix’s trailer for her new series, and before announcing the Harper’s interview, Meghan’s publicists spotted that Kate would be attending the Royal Variety Performance in London on 19th November. A clash, but also perhaps perfect timing. The contrast of Kate celebrating while Meghan was selling was ignored. For Meghan, ‘Meeting her Moment’ in the days before Christmas was make or break. If all those carefully organised events failed to relaunch her in 2026, the Sussexes’ future would become bleak.

Officials at Kensington Palace would have also monitored the Sussexes’ agenda. With the summer holidays over, William was geared to counter-attack. In preparation, he had co-operated in lengthy newspaper profiles about modernising the monarchy and prioritising his family after experiencing bereavement and the stress of Kate’s illness.[962] In an unconventional TV interview with the Canadian comedy actor Eugene Levy, he pointedly declared his refusal to be overawed by history. During his reign, he volunteered, the monarchy would certainly be changed. Noticeably, during those interviews, William added little reassurance that as King, the monarchy would recover from the doldrums and restore its popularity.[963] Many hurdles stood in his way.

William’s mood had hardened after the Duchess of Kent’s funeral at Westminster Cathedral on 16th September. In front of the public and cameras, Prince Andrew attempted to engage William in conversation. William was clearly irritated. The prospect of living close to his uncle after his family moved to Forest Lodge in Windsor Great Park was alarming, especially after the recent publication of Entitled by Andrew Lownie, a book exposing the Prince’s sordid, corrupt lifestyle. Soon after, William flew to Balmoral to discuss with the King the family’s predicament. ‘Life for the King and Queen is hell right now,’ a close relative of Camilla revealed. William found his father unusually distraught. Depressed by his own health and Camilla’s ailments, the King was fretting about Harry and Andrew. Indecisive at the best of times, the King despaired about his predicament. William forcefully demanded a solution to the Andrew and Harry problems.

Ever since Virginia Giuffre, an American girl abused and trafficked by the convicted paedophile Jeffrey Epstein, filed a legal claim in 2014 in Florida against Andrew, Charles and his mother, Queen Elizabeth, had tried to believe Andrew’s denials of any connection to Giuffre. By then, ‘Randy Andy’’s relationship with Epstein, whom he met in 1999 through socialite Ghislaine Maxwell, had been revealed to have been partly based on Epstein paying young girls to meet Andrew. Epstein’s pimping was repaid by invitations to Buckingham Palace, Windsor Castle, Sandringham and Royal Ascot.

The Royal Family’s support for Andrew had collapsed after his interview on BBC TV’s Newsnight in November 2019. His denial of knowing Virginia Giuffre was undermined by a photograph taken by Epstein in 2001 of the two together in Ghislaine Maxwell’s London flat. Andrew claimed that the photograph was faked. His folly of exposing himself to interrogation was compounded by his lack of contrition or any expression of sympathy for Epstein’s young victims. The popular impression was that Andrew had lied during the interview.

At the time, no one knew about Epstein’s email to Maxwell, sent in July 2011, soon after the photo was published, recording the paedophile’s confirmation: ‘She [Giuffre] had her picture taken with Andrew.’[964] The photo was genuine. Equally importantly, no one knew about another simultaneous email exchange in which Epstein accused Giuffre of lying about her sexual relationship with Andrew and other famous men. Andrew’s lawyers had failed to obtain those emails from the US Department of Justice, but Epstein’s other emails cast doubt on its veracity.

By early 2022, Giuffre’s legal claim against Andrew was well advanced and threatened to overshadow the Queen’s jubilee celebrations. To settle the case on the eve of Andrew being compelled to testify in America, Giuffre was paid an estimated £12 million. The settlement and the earlier removal, on the Queen’s orders, of some of Andrew’s titles and privileges with the understanding that he would retreat from public life, did not end the saga. Hanging over Andrew were the contents of Epstein’s voluminous files and emails, sealed under a legal embargo but reversible by a Congressional vote.

In his Newsnight interview, Andrew denied contacting Epstein ever again after his visit to New York on 5th December 2010. According to Andrew, he had flown to New York especially to terminate their relationship. Memorably, as they walked through Central Park, their ‘final’ encounter was recorded by a News of the World photographer. Fifteen years later, on 12th October 2025, Andrew’s lie was exposed.

The Mail on Sunday published an email sent by Andrew to Epstein twelve weeks after their 2010 meeting. Clearly, Andrew had panicked after the unexpected first publication of the 2001 photograph of himself with Virginia Giuffre and Ghislaine Maxwell. Andrew could not have forgotten about a succession of emails he sent Epstein over the next four years starting with, ‘I’m just as concerned for you,’ Andrew emailed Epstein. ‘Don’t worry about me! Otherwise keep in close touch and we’ll play some more soon!!!!’ His email was signed, ‘A. HRH Duke of York, KG.’ Pertinently, he did not question the authenticity of the photograph.

The publication of Andrew’s email in October 2025 caused panic in the Palace. A dithering sick king surrounded by obedient advisors in a seemingly rudderless court was ill-equipped to manage his brother, who had now been exposed as an outright liar. The Queen’s attempt to prevent more reputational damage to the Royal Family by removing some of Andrew’s titles and privileges had clearly failed. The threat of worse to come once other emails between Andrew and Epstein were released was serious and uncontrollable. Among those unpublished exchanges was an email from Andrew to Epstein in 2011 showing that under pressure, Andrew had lost his self-control: ‘I can’t take any more of this my end.’ Strenuously pleading his innocence and ignorance about Giuffre’s allegations, Andrew urged Epstein to ‘state clearly that I knew and know nothing about any of these allegations’. Only fourteen years later, in late 2025, did the Palace and politicians become aware of those exchanges.

During the five days after the Mail on Sunday’s publication of Andrew’s first email to Epstein, William heaped pressure on his father to end the torrid saga. In turn, Charles and his private secretary spoke to Andrew. Finally, Andrew surrendered. He gave up the Garter and all his titles including the Duke of York. His ex-wife Sarah also lost her title, reverting to plain Sarah Ferguson.

But there were caveats. Andrew remained a prince, said the Palace, because removing his birth title would require an Act of Parliament. For similar legal reasons, he could not be forced to leave Royal Lodge, his thirty-room mansion in Windsor Park. Andrew would, however, be banned from family events, including Christmas at Sandringham. In his own statement, Andrew reaffirmed that ‘I vigorously deny the accusations against me.’[965]

The damaging headlines continued. The harmful revelations published over the following days included that Andrew had asked Scotland Yard to help with an investigation into Giuffre’s background and that he was paying a ‘peppercorn’ rent until 2078 for his residence at Royal Lodge. Giuffre had committed suicide in April 2025 and her posthumous autobiography, Nobody’s Girl, was about to be published, detailing the woman’s suffering of sexual abuse, including that from Andrew.[966]

Fired up by those headlines, Labour MPs demanded a Commons debate about the Royal Family’s finances. Fearing embarrassment, William found his father uncertain about his own era, facing neither forwards nor backwards. Fearing that far more damaging revelations would follow about Andrew and Sarah after the next release by the Department of Justice in Washington of millions more of Epstein’s email exchanges with Andrew about young women introduced by Epstein which included a still unknown arrangement to host one woman in Buckingham Palace – and even compromising photographs – he cut short Charles’s indecision. The heir demanded that Andrew be evicted from Royal Lodge and be stripped of his title as prince. The alternative, Charles was told, was a crisis with untold consequences for the monarchy. Charles was given no alternative. Suddenly, legal constraints were no longer a barrier. The King simply signed a letters patent.

Late on 30th October, the Palace announced that Andrew was reduced to a commoner. He would move to Sandringham and henceforth would be called Andrew Mountbatten-Windsor. Committed to internal exile, his downfall was complete. On BBC TV a live audience cheered the news. The King feared worse to come but could not have imagined his brother’s arrest in February 2026.

No other royal in modern British history had been similarly humiliated. The tremors of the unprecedented sanctions against Andrew must have shocked Harry. In public, he remained silent. In private, he realised that his own royal status was no longer invincible. Clearly, William was taking no prisoners. Once he was crowned as king, his brother might well show no mercy to him and Meghan. Insulted by all the criticism targeted from Montecito, Harry could anticipate that the Prince and Princess of Wales’s anger about Meghan’s misuse of her royal title for profit would tip the balance. William would undoubtedly rail against her disloyalty. He might even strip Archie and Lilibet of their titles.

Initially, it appeared that Meghan showed no concern about the threat. She always possessed the potential bombshell retaliation of publishing her memoirs if she was displeased. She refused to fear an event beyond her control. Instead, she appeared smiling with Harry in the midst of the Andrew crisis at a Los Angeles Dodgers baseball game to promote her As Ever Christmas selections.[967] The fans’ reaction to seeing the Sussexes in the stadium’s best seats was unfavourable. Some booed, complaining that the real hero, legendary basketball player Magic Johnson, was forced to sit behind the couple. Viewers said that Harry looked miserable. Knowing the dice was loaded against him, his position was very different from Meghan’s.

CHAPTER 43

Make or Break

In his desire for reconciliation, Harry planned to commemorate Remembrance Day by visiting veterans in Canada and publishing a short essay about his own ‘life of duty’ and the sacrifice and service of the fallen. ‘The Bond, The Banter, The Bravery – What it means to be British’ evoked in Harry’s words: ‘The banter of the mess, the clubhouse, the pubs, the stands, these are the things that make us British. I make no apology for it. I love it.’[968]

Harry fixed the timing of his ‘royal’ visit to Toronto so he could return to California in time for a celebrity party on Saturday 8th November, just before Remembrance Day. Meghan had secured an invitation to Kris Jenner’s seventieth birthday party held at Jeff Bezos’s $165 million home – a destination for America’s royalty. After being excluded from Bezos’s sixtieth birthday party and his $50 million wedding in Venice, securing an invitation to a celebration alongside dozens of famous American titans was gold dust for Meghan. The Sussexes could network with Mark Zuckerberg, Bill Gates, Kim Kardashian’s family, Beyoncé, Mariah Carey and, relevantly, lifestyle guru Martha Stewart. Photographed arriving at the party, which was themed around James Bond’s Casino Royale, Meghan sported her usual perma-smile. Curiously, the official photos of the Sussexes inside the party were deleted at their request from Kris Jenner’s site.[969] The Sussexes’ hosts were said to be furious about the snub.

Throughout the evening, Harry struggled to grin. There was more bad news from London. Kensington Palace was angry that Harry’s trip to Canada had clashed with William’s choreographed award of The Earthshot Prize in Rio de Janeiro, which had been awarded to Colombia. Harry appeared to have deliberately embarrassed his brother’s bid to win public approval. Harry’s claim to have warned the Palace of his trip was vehemently denied by William’s officials.[970] Highlighting Harry’s ‘lies’ while he partied with the Kardashians sealed his image as a man struggling with his past and no longer fashioning his future. Not least because on the eve of Harry’s trial against the Daily Mail, there had been an unfortunate upset.

Harry and his fellow litigants had been persuaded by their barrister, David Sherborne, to start the case against the Mail. As we’ve seen, the claims made against the newspaper were corroborated by a statement allegedly signed by Gavin Burrows, a private investigator who admitted a range of crimes against Harry in August 2021, but then denied the truthfulness of the ‘original statement’. Despite the contradiction, and reassured by his lawyers, Harry assumed his claim against the Mail would be as successful as those against the Mirror and News Corp. Harry’s certainty was derailed shortly before Kris Jenner’s party. The Mail had presented to the court a new statement by Burrows. In explicit detail, the private investigator described how his original statement was a ‘forgery’ created by Harry’s lawyers. Burrows stated that not only was the statement ‘completely false’ and ‘a complete fantasy’, but he had been paid £5,000 a month by Harry’s team for assistance, despite insisting that he never worked for the Mail. Doreen Lawrence, continued Burrows, had been ‘tricked’ by the lawyers to start her claim against the Mail on the basis of the forged statement. Similarly, Harry, Liz Hurley and Elton John had also been ‘duped’ by Burrows’s ‘statement’.

Pertinently, Burrows described how he had been taken to a London park by Harry’s solicitor and Graham Johnson, a convicted phone hacker, to meet Sherborne. When the barrister arrived, said Burrows, ‘he looked like he had not slept. He was unable to stand still and spoke rapidly and slightly incoherently.’

In a further signed statement, Burrows described how Graham Johnson offered to pay him £5,000 per month and did pay him £25,000 for a book deal while encouraging him to admit that he had worked for the Mail. ‘They told me that the Daily Mail was a major target,’ Burrows stated. ‘I told them repeatedly that I had not worked for the Mail . . . I had told him a hundred times that ANL were not one of my clients.’ And Burrows also added, ‘I felt very sorry for Baroness Lawrence, as it appeared to me that she had been duped into pursuing a claim on the basis of false information about evidence obtained by me.’[971]

In the High Court after the weekend of Jenner’s party, Sherborne’s embarrassment was professionally concealed. He condemned the ‘scurrilous nature’ of Burrows’s new statement as a ‘grotesque inclusion [into the case] which is meant to be an attack on parts of the legal team’. But the damage to Harry’s claim could not be hidden. Even the Prince understood that his claim appeared to be weakened. If he actually lost the case, the embarrassment would hamper his attempts to re-establish himself in Britain. However, he fought back. In a witness statement, Harry claimed that Burrows personally had told him how he had ‘intercepted’ the voicemails of a former girlfriend Laura Gerard-Leigh and her parents. And to boost the attack on ANL, Sherborne claimed that between 2003 and 2005, they had intercepted calls involving two of the other claimants – Sadie Frost and Elizabeth Hurley. But not Harry.[972]

The hurdles of managing Harry’s return to Britain were highlighted in the Daily Mail. Illustrated by a photograph of Harry arriving at Kris Jenner’s party, the newspaper noted that while Harry wore a poppy on his tuxedo, Meghan had not. The Duchess, the article implied, had betrayed the nation whose royal title she exploited. Two days later, Meghan posted a photograph of herself wearing a poppy. She had finally understood the danger William posed to her professional existence. His revenge for her betrayal could be crushing.

The Sussexes’ fate depended entirely on William and Kate. Harry had not helped his cause by refuting in Spare the popular belief that William had been his advocate and protector in the aftermath of Diana’s death. Harry’s criticism of William for ignoring him at Eton and thereafter had hurt his elder brother. Harry’s heartless betrayal of William and Kate appeared to have sealed his fate. Reconciliation and a return to Britain was beyond imagination. Treachery in the Royal Family was rarely rewarded – as Harry and Meghan realised. And yet, as Harry infamously screamed after hearing that Meghan could be denied instant access to a tiara before their wedding, ‘What Meghan wants, Meghan gets.’ Few had anticipated the Duchess’s strategy as they headed towards their endgame.

In autumn 2025, the Sussexes faced a harsh reality. They were fast running out of money. With high security costs, the Sussexes needed every year at least $3 million after paying tax to survive. The Netflix and Spotify contracts had come to an end. Both Sussexes relied on a dribble of money from Harry’s occasional speeches and Meghan’s endorsement of fashion brands. The foreign tours and the Invictus competition had been especially lucrative. No further announcement had been issued about the sale of As Ever’s products. Profits were assumed to be dire. Yet a ‘leak’ suggested that Meghan had sold one million pots of jam and produced profits of $30 million (£27 million). Few thought that was credible. Not least because her office never confirmed the ‘report’.[973] Indeed, it later transpired that the vast amounts of unsold As Ever products were spilling out of Netflix’s headquarters.[974] And her second series was ranked 1,016th in Netflix’s most popular shows. Just two million watched over six months, a show described by the Guardian as ‘so boring, so contrived, so effortlessly whimsical’.[975] But it was just one of several stories in the new year fitting the Sussexes’ latest narrative. They contrived to present themselves as destined not only to be welcomed back to Britain but even to be given Highgrove, the King’s beloved country home in Gloucestershire, to make the royal couple appear cherished and comfortable.[976] The reality was different.

Among the Sussexes’ costly failures they realised during 2025 was the Archewell Foundation. Having failed to raise any new donations, the accounts filed in December 2025 revealed an organisation on the edge. Archewell’s income had fallen from $5.3 million to just $2.1 million, that donation a historic commitment which would not be renewed.[977] More startling, Archewell gave away just $1.2 million, mostly in small $27,500 donations, but its expenses were $3.9 million. There was no explanation of how the Sussexes spent any of that money. With no substantial donations due in 2026, and with $8 million in the bank, the Sussexes decided to wrap up their ‘charitable’ activities. Renaming the Archewell Foundation as ‘Archewell Philanthropies’, the Sussexes transferred their whole campaign to an existing group, Parents Together.[978] Naturally, the Sussexes spun their defeat as a success. The change, they said, would ‘broaden their global philanthropic efforts for meaningful reach and maximum impact’. In reality, they seemed to many to be abandoning their core purpose – philanthropy, even if it was financed by others.

The closure on the eve of Christmas appeared carefully calibrated to conceal their distress.[979] While announcing the dismissal of a slew of ‘junior’ staff, they had discreetly also fired two key employees: Archewell’s executive director James Holt, who had been in post for five years, and Meredith Maines, their media spokeswoman. Maines was the eleventh publicist to leave in five years. Liam Maguire, based in London, would in future manage their media operation. To Americans, that appeared bizarre. There was an eight-hour time difference between London and Los Angeles. Except that behind the smokescreen praising their success, the Sussexes had initiated a plan conceived months earlier to salvage their finances and reputations.

The Sussexes aimed for nothing less than to be reinstated in London by the King as trusted members of the Royal Family. The vehicle for their triumphant return – just as Harry had originally intended – would be the Invictus Games to be held in July 2027 in Birmingham. From the outset, Harry had plotted for the King to open the Games as the backdrop for Meghan, accompanied by their children, to dominate the media.

Rehabilitating the Sussexes relied on their publicists steadily placing favourable stories to grateful journalists. But no sooner had the Sussexes’ publicists choreographed a slew of videos of their public appearances and photographs of their children – with the children’s faces more exposed than previously – than Thomas Markle was reported on 5th December to be dangerously ill in a Philippines hospital.[980] Suffering a huge blood clot in his thigh, doctors in Cebu had amputated his left lower leg. By his bedside, Caroline Graham, a trusted British journalist, reported that Thomas hoped to hear from his daughter ‘one more time before I die’. Thomas added, ‘I feel so sad that our family has grown so far apart. Please let bygones be bygones.’

Likely aware that the world was waiting to see how she would respond, Meghan’s office announced that she had ‘reached out to her father’.[981] That was inaccurate. First, Meghan claimed to have emailed him – he did not receive those messages – and then she explained that she was unable to call him because she no longer had his telephone number. Yet his number had not changed in twenty years, her mother had Thomas’s number and, if all else failed, Meghan’s office could have asked Caroline Graham. Instead, Meghan’s office aggressively denounced Graham’s presence at Thomas’s bedside as ‘breaching clear ethical boundaries’. At a time when most would have expected her to show compassion for her father, Meghan asserted her need for privacy. Eventually, her office asked Graham for Thomas’s contact details. Meghan’s letter was delivered to Thomas by an American diplomat. Within hours, Meghan breached her own privacy by announcing her letter’s delivery. But she refused to fly to her father’s bedside. His hope for reconciliation was rebuffed. ‘It was surreal,’ wrote Graham, a witness to Thomas’s anguish.

Showing a disdain for the interruption, the Sussexes’ office resumed its timetable. Journalists were briefed that Harry expected Ravec to overturn its previous decision and agree that the police after all would provide armed protection during his visits to Britain.[982] A new risk assessment, Harry claimed, was under way following a female stalker approaching him during the previous visit. Although the stalker had posed no threat to his life, Harry hoped that raising the issue would embarrass the government to surrender. If the government provided armed security, Harry and Meghan believed, their status as members of the Royal Family would be restored.

Soon after, the first drip of news management of 2026 appeared. The Times reported that Harry would refuse to re-engage with Sentebale. In reality, Harry had lost any role in Sentebale and Sophie Chandauka was rebuilding the charity. Harry’s important focus was on winning his case against the Mail. The star witness appeared on 21st January.

Harry was in a combative mood. He was not in court to answer questions but to declare how ‘disgusting’ and ‘disgraceful’ the Mail and especially its editor Paul Dacre had behaved. ‘I have never believed that my life is open season to be commercialised by these people,’ said the author of Spare. After denying that he used a Facebook account under the name Mr Mischief to ‘exchange friendly messages’ and his mobile number with the Mail journalist Charlotte Griffiths, he also denied meeting her in Ibiza in 2011. ‘The only time I’ve been to Ibiza was with my wife and son,’ declared Harry. He also denied that he had spoken about Chelsy Davy to friends at a campfire in Botswana which led to a Mail on Sunday article in November 2004 under the headline: ‘Harry besotted with Chelsy, his first true love’. The story, he claimed, could only have been sourced by hacking. His assertion appeared to be disproved by a passage in Spare and an email exchange immediately after the event. The email revealed that despite Harry’s denial, a friend around the campfire had been the source of the Mail’s story.

After a brief and placid cross-examination, Harry told the judge, ‘To sit here and go through this again and to hear them claim in their defence that I don’t have any right to privacy is disgusting.’ He fought back tears: ‘They have made my wife’s life an absolute misery, my lord.’ Harry walked out, leaving many bewildered. Many were also puzzled whether Harry had proved his case or whether his denials had lit a fuse for the Mail’s journalists to explode his credibility in their testimony. The Mail’s softly-softly approach suggested that Paul Dacre had decided to persuade the judge that his newspapers were gentle and fair, never unfairly seeking to score points.

* * *

Harry would not allow the High Court embarrassment to derail his quest to use the Invictus Games for his family’s return to Britain. But in choosing Birmingham, Harry had unwittingly exposed himself to unexpected controversy: the toxic reality of a city in turmoil, mired by threats of protest.

Among the twenty-two countries invited to compete in Birmingham was Israel. Inevitably, their small team would be drawn from former members of the Israel Defense Forces (IDF) injured fighting Hamas and Hezbollah in Gaza, Lebanon and Syria. In Vancouver, their 22-man squad had been warmly received and won thirteen medals, but the competitors had been asked not to parade their identity or flag outside the Convention Centre.[983] That reticence would be futile in 2027.

One-third of Birmingham’s population is Muslim. Influenced by some Islamic mullahs and politicians in the city, the local police force decided in November 2025 to ban Maccabi Tel Aviv football fans from watching their team play Aston Villa. The unprecedented prohibition by a city safety group was based on Birmingham’s police presenting false ‘intelligence’ about the dangers the Israeli fans posed to Muslims. The phoney intelligence satisfied the local authority’s search for a reason to bar the Israelis coming to Birmingham, as confirmed by a parliamentary report in February 2026.[984]

In reality, the police knew that the violence was actually threatened against the visiting Israelis. Instead of protecting the Maccabi fans, the police concocted a scenario of hundreds of Israeli hoodlums, apparently all former IDF soldiers, planning to attack peaceful Muslims. However, within three weeks, newspapers began to report the police’s misconduct. In particular, the chief constable, Craig Guildford, was blamed for the dishonesty. Damned in mid-January 2026 by an official report, Guildford refused initially to resign. His hand was not forced by the local crime commissioner, a Corbyn sympathiser overseeing a beleaguered police force accused of being ‘rotten to the core’. Ultimately, Guildford was compelled to retire, but the Birmingham police force remained in turmoil.

The challenge for Harry and the Invictus Games was existential. Would Birmingham’s Muslim activist community allow an Israeli team to peacefully compete in their city? Based on the Maccabi experience, that would be difficult to envisage.

Some also perceived Harry’s position on Israel to be uncertain. Harry’s public statements on Israel were watched closely, particularly after the Hamas attacks murdered 1,200 Israelis and took 251 hostages on 7th October 2023. While Harry had visited Invictus competitors in Australia, Nigeria, Brazil, Colombia, Ukraine, America, Germany and Britain, he had not visited Israel. Pertinently, he had visited war-torn Ukraine twice in 2025.

Israel’s war was highlighted by Archewell’s 2025 Impact Report. ‘This year we have witnessed unimaginable suffering, from the preventable tragedy which unfolded in Gaza where thousands of innocent children and civilians faced starvation and death . . .’ [985] The Impact Report did not mention the 1,200 Israelis murdered on 7th October 2023 or the fate of the 251 hostages whose imprisonment was widely condemned elsewhere – and whose eventual release would be a part of the agreement to end the war, while at the same time they highlighted the suffering faced by innocent Palestinians. Pertinently, the Sussexes flew to Jordan on 23 February as guests of the World Health Organisation to visit Palestinian refugee camps, but did not cross the border to visit Israeli victims of Hamas.

After the 7th October massacres, King Charles and the Prince and Princess of Wales had specifically mentioned ‘the horrors inflicted by Hamas’s terrorist attack upon Israel’ as ‘appalling’ and supported ‘Israel exercising its right of self-defence’. The Sussexes stated, ‘We stand against all acts of terrorism and brutality,’[986]and offered ‘support’ for those ‘on the frontlines in Israel’. A further clue of Harry’s attitude towards Israel was his agreement to promote Spare by appearing in an extensive interview with Gabor Maté, the Canadian trauma expert, who had made controversial statements about Hamas, comparing them to the Jewish heroes of the Warsaw Ghetto Uprising against the Nazis. Harry ignored the calls in the press to reconsider being interviewed by Maté.

The anticipated reception of Invictus in the UK in 2027 poses a challenge not only to Harry but also the King. Could the monarch allow himself to be embroiled in the inevitable protests, after the negative press the royal family had suffered over the preceding months and years? And more to the point, could the King allow himself to be influenced by his son, who still demanded an apology from his father, brother and sister-in-law? Considering all the damning words and lies spoken and written by the Sussexes against the Royal Family since 2021, and the enormous damage caused by the Sussexes’ exploitation of their royal titles, the chance of the King irritating the Prince and Princess of Wales to please the Sussexes is, in Spring 2026, remote.

The Royal Family’s vulnerability was further exposed on 19th February after the early morning arrest by Thames Valley police of Andrew Mountbatten-Windsor at his home in Sandringham. Questioned about his possible misconduct in public office in a local police station, as any suspect of a crime would be, Andrew had been exposed in the Epstein files for passing confidential government documents about trade relations and policies in the Far East to the American investor in 2010. The arrest of a royal in the line of succession, the first since Charles I in 1647, triggered a catastrophic crisis for the King. On the same day the monarchy’s credibility was hotly disputed. Although no one could authoritatively predict whether Andrew would be charged, the former prince’s appalling relationships with women who had been introduced to him by a convicted paedophile compounded the King’s humiliation.

Unexpectedly, Charles was paying the price for the delayed expulsion of his brother from his Windsor home and the Royal Family. Amid the fevered public debate, fundamental changes and transparency were demanded for the Royal Family’s finances and their status. Even normally moderate voices spoke of the King’s abdication, which would be a death sentence for the constitutional monarchy.

In Montecito, the Sussexes could take little comfort from Buckingham Palace’s turmoil. In Spare, Harry had scoffed about the unequal treatment of himself and ‘my uncle Andrew’: ‘Whatever grievances people had against us, sex crimes weren’t on the list.’[987] Yet grouped with Andrew as a renegade, Harry was flummoxed about escaping from the association. The inevitability of a protracted crisis during the official process of deciding Andrew’s fate made Harry’s position increasingly difficult. While the royal calamity continued to make headline news in Britain, the Sussexes’ fate slipped further beyond their control. Their plight could only worsen.

The feud embroiling the Royal family is far from resolution, and it remains to be seen what damage will be inflicted on an already fragile family.

Acknowledgements

Writing a second book about Harry and Meghan follows the positive reaction to my first book Revenge and pertinently unearthing new, remarkable developments since 2021. It also meets the insatiable interest in the Sussexes and the ever-changing and challenging predicament of the British Royal Family.

Discovering the truth while denied access to the Sussexes depends on the trust of reliable witnesses and the determination to find what, for different reasons, has been concealed. Fortunately, many people agreed to help on condition of anonymity.

In writing this book, no one was more important than Claudia Wordsworth, an outstanding, determined researcher and an invaluable guide to previously untold aspects of this extraordinary story. As always, Claudia exceeded all expectations. I owe her a great debt.

I received significant help in America from Tom Teodorczuk, Peter Sheridan and especially from Mary Jo Jacobi; Paulina Diazgranados was indefatigable in Colombia; and I owe Mark Hollingsworth thanks in London. Many others helped but preferred to remain anonymous. Clearly, I am indebted to all of them.

Once again, I was fortunate that Alan Samson, an outstanding publisher, agreed to edit the manuscript. Alan surpassed expectations. Thanks also to David Hirst for his legal advice.

As always, I am especially grateful to my loyal agent Jonathan Lloyd of Curtis Brown, an outstanding friend and ally.

My publishers have been hugely supportive. I owe a special debt to my editor Ciara Lloyd and also to Liz Marvin, Ian Greensill and Amanda Russell.

The most important thanks are due to Veronica, my wife, best friend, wise consigliore and irreplaceable supporter. Without her, as always, this book would not have been written.

London, February 2026